<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>dhbalaji.dev feed</title>
        <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog</link>
        <description>dhbalaji, lead design technologist at Sabre Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 01:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My Picks from Thoughtworks Radar Vol 33: Frontend Trends You Should Not Ignore]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 01:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A clear, engineer-focused breakdown of the most important frontend and AI-driven trends from Thoughtworks Technology Radar Vol. 33. Covers AI prototyping, spec-driven development, AG-UI protocol, intelligent testing, and modern tooling for intermediate and senior frontend engineers.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Staying updated in tech is like keeping pace with the seasons. Ignore it for a while and suddenly you look like the one person still writing jQuery in 2025. Among the handful of reliable sources that consistently deliver high-quality, expert insights, the Thoughtworks Technology Radar stands tall. Volume 33, in particular, has a rich collection of signals that map perfectly to modern frontend engineering. Here are the trends that caught my eye—my unofficial "Adopt" list for any intermediate or above frontend engineer.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="ai-enhanced-prototyping-and-design">AI-Enhanced Prototyping and Design<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#ai-enhanced-prototyping-and-design" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to AI-Enhanced Prototyping and Design" title="Direct link to AI-Enhanced Prototyping and Design" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Designers today have superpowers. Tools like <strong>UX Pilot</strong> and <strong>AI Design Reviewer</strong> act like always-available collaborators, helping generate everything from wireframes to pixel-perfect mockups. These tools also offer automated design audits, giving early warnings before a design becomes a future engineering migraine.</p>
<p>On the developer side, tools like <strong>V0</strong> and <strong>Bolt</strong> allow text-based prototyping. Instead of waiting for finalized Figma files, developers can spin out interactive, throwaway prototypes in minutes. This fuels a new workflow where teams iterate rapidly on UI concepts before committing to the real build. Think of it as whiteboarding with a compiler.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="spec-driven-development-comes-of-age">Spec-Driven Development Comes of Age<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#spec-driven-development-comes-of-age" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Spec-Driven Development Comes of Age" title="Direct link to Spec-Driven Development Comes of Age" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Spec-driven development is moving from “cool experiment” to “serious workflow.” The idea is simple: treat requirements as a versioned artifact, similar to code. Tools such as <strong>GitHub Spec Kit</strong> enforce this by introducing a structured flow—requirements, design, and task breakdown—each backed by richer orchestration and prompts. It also introduces a “constitution,” a set of rules the AI helpers must always obey. When specs become first-class citizens, onboarding and collaboration get smoother, and ambiguity drops dramatically.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="agents-need-documentation-too-enter-agentsmd">Agents Need Documentation Too: Enter <em>Agents.md</em><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#agents-need-documentation-too-enter-agentsmd" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to agents-need-documentation-too-enter-agentsmd" title="Direct link to agents-need-documentation-too-enter-agentsmd" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Software engineers long accepted README files as the source of truth. Agents are now getting the same treatment. An <strong>Agents.md</strong> file acts like a behavioural guidebook for AI agents, explaining their capabilities, constraints, assumptions, and intended usage. It’s a simple idea but powerful for reducing unpredictability. It also improves collaboration when multiple teams depend on the same agent logic.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="shared-instructions-with-slash-commands-and-chat-modes">Shared Instructions with Slash Commands and Chat Modes<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#shared-instructions-with-slash-commands-and-chat-modes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Shared Instructions with Slash Commands and Chat Modes" title="Direct link to Shared Instructions with Slash Commands and Chat Modes" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Teams are increasingly using shared shortcuts inside their AI workflows. Slash commands like <code>/refactor</code>, <code>/review</code>, or <code>/prototype</code> help create predictable collaboration patterns. Paired with custom chat modes, teams end up with a common vocabulary for interacting with AI tools. This reduces the “AI did something weird” factor and introduces repeatable, deterministic workflows.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="testing-faster-loops-and-smarter-bots">Testing: Faster Loops and Smarter Bots<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#testing-faster-loops-and-smarter-bots" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Testing: Faster Loops and Smarter Bots" title="Direct link to Testing: Faster Loops and Smarter Bots" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The <strong>Test &amp;&amp; Commit || Revert</strong> workflow is resurfacing as a productive pattern. The idea is brutal and effective: write code, run tests, commit only if everything passes, and automatically revert if something breaks. Tools like <strong>Nx</strong> make this workflow practical by running only relevant tests instead of the entire suite. Without that, you’re staring at the screen waiting for tests longer than waiting for a Bangalore–Hosur bus on a rainy day.</p>
<p>AI-powered UI testing is also evolving. Playwright and Selenium now integrate with MCP-based agents that automatically author test cases, heal flaky selectors, and update broken assertions. UI tests finally feel less fragile and more self-repairing—a welcome relief for any frontend engineer who has fought with a stubborn CSS selector at 2 AM.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="real-time-humanagent-collaboration-ag-ui-protocol">Real-Time Human–Agent Collaboration: AG-UI Protocol<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#real-time-humanagent-collaboration-ag-ui-protocol" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Real-Time Human–Agent Collaboration: AG-UI Protocol" title="Direct link to Real-Time Human–Agent Collaboration: AG-UI Protocol" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The <strong>AG-UI Protocol</strong> is an open standard aimed at structuring communication between frontends and agents. It defines how UI components and backend agents exchange state, collaborate in real time, and suggest actions to users. As agent-driven apps become mainstream, standards like this will keep architectures from devolving into random RPC chaos.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="keeping-llms-on-the-same-version-context7">Keeping LLMs on the Same Version: Context7<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#keeping-llms-on-the-same-version-context7" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Keeping LLMs on the Same Version: Context7" title="Direct link to Keeping LLMs on the Same Version: Context7" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>LLMs often hallucinate outdated API calls because their training data is stale. <strong>Context7</strong> solves this by feeding models fresh, version-specific code directly from your source. This dramatically reduces the “React stopped supporting this in 2023” type of errors. For fast-moving ecosystems like Next.js or Angular, this is a significant advantage.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="feature-flags-and-productivity-tools">Feature Flags and Productivity Tools<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#feature-flags-and-productivity-tools" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Feature Flags and Productivity Tools" title="Direct link to Feature Flags and Productivity Tools" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Feature flags are a necessary evil, but managing them across multiple runtimes is messy. <strong>OpenFeature</strong> brings a standard to how flags are defined and consumed across languages, frameworks, and platforms. It simplifies rollout strategies and makes flag management consistent.</p>
<p>On the tooling front, <strong>pnpm</strong> continues to prove it’s the package manager npm wishes it had become. Disk usage drops, install times improve, and monorepo workflows become smoother.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="tools-worth-paying-attention-to">Tools Worth Paying Attention To<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#tools-worth-paying-attention-to" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Tools Worth Paying Attention To" title="Direct link to Tools Worth Paying Attention To" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The Radar also spotlights a number of tools that feel highly relevant for frontend engineers:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Fastify</strong> brings high-performance Node servers with a pleasant TypeScript story.</li>
<li class=""><strong>LangGraph</strong> pushes agent orchestration forward with graph-based logic flows.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Nuxt</strong> continues to mature as Vue’s equivalent to Next.js, now also backed by Vercel.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Tauri</strong> lets you build desktop apps using web technologies without the Electron weight class.</li>
<li class=""><strong>ADK</strong> (Agent Development Kit) standardizes how agents are built and deployed.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Assistant UI</strong> simplifies building apps around AI assistants.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Drizzle</strong> and <strong>Prisma</strong> keep evolving as the most ergonomic TypeScript ORMs.</li>
<li class=""><strong>OpenInference</strong> adds observability standards for AI pipelines.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Valibot</strong> provides lightweight schema validation with tight type inference.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Vercel AI SDK</strong> is becoming the go-to for building AI-driven frontend apps.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-picks-from-thoughtworks-radar-vol-33#closing-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Closing Thoughts" title="Direct link to Closing Thoughts" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Thoughtworks Radar Vol. 33 makes one thing clear: the frontend world is shifting toward AI-augmented workflows, spec-driven development, and structured protocols for human–agent interaction. Frontends are no longer static presentation layers—they’re turning into dynamic negotiation tables where users and agents collaborate in real time.</p>
<p>Ignoring these trends will leave teams struggling to catch up later. Embracing them early gives developers the advantage of speed, clarity, and leverage. The next wave of frontend innovation is already forming around standards like AG-UI and tools like Context7, and the exciting part is that we’re still at the beginning of this transformation.</p>
<p>More experiments soon, especially hands-on explorations with agent-driven UIs and AI-aligned development workflows.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>frontend</category>
            <category>thoughtworks-radar</category>
            <category>engineering-trends</category>
            <category>ai-tools</category>
            <category>ui-engineering</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Best New Books October 2025: Must-Read Releases Across Fiction and Non-Fiction]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/best-new-books-october-2025-reviews-recommendations</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/best-new-books-october-2025-reviews-recommendations</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Discover October 2025’s standout books — from Steven Pinker’s cognitive science masterpiece to Indian folklore and sports memoirs. Curated reviews and recommendations from Your Update Officer.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="New book releases October 2025 displayed on wooden shelf" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/non-fiction-reads-oct-week4-2025-1b1a0a3b2f759734427c93d9f9372e9f.webp" width="1024" height="1024" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>October 2025 has turned out to be an extraordinary month for readers. From deep dives into human cognition to folklore-inspired storytelling and bold rethinks of India’s economy — this lineup reflects what <em>Your Update Officer</em> stands for: <strong>curated intelligence that keeps you ahead of the curve.</strong></p>
<p>Below are five standout titles chosen not for hype, but for the <strong>clarity and curiosity they spark.</strong></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-when-everyone-knows-that-everyone-knows--steven-pinker">1. When Everyone Knows That Everyone Knows – <em>Steven Pinker</em><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/best-new-books-october-2025-reviews-recommendations#1-when-everyone-knows-that-everyone-knows--steven-pinker" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1-when-everyone-knows-that-everyone-knows--steven-pinker" title="Direct link to 1-when-everyone-knows-that-everyone-knows--steven-pinker" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The master of mind and language returns with a study on “common knowledge” — how shared awareness shapes trust, cooperation, and civilization itself. A must-read in an era where everyone <em>thinks</em> they know, but few understand what that means.</p>
<p><strong>Genre:</strong> Cognitive Science, Social Psychology<br>
<strong>Read if you’re:</strong> A leader, strategist, or simply curious about how collective understanding fuels progress.<br>
<!-- -->👉 <a href="https://www.amazon.in/When-Everyone-Knows-That-Knowledge/dp/1668011573" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">View on Amazon India</a></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-when-birds-talked--neha-negi">2. When Birds Talked – <em>Neha Negi</em><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/best-new-books-october-2025-reviews-recommendations#2-when-birds-talked--neha-negi" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2-when-birds-talked--neha-negi" title="Direct link to 2-when-birds-talked--neha-negi" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>A lyrical, illustrated collection that revives Himalayan bird myths — stories where nature speaks in metaphors. Rarely does folklore meet such graceful storytelling and visual poetry.</p>
<p><strong>Genre:</strong> Folklore, Nature, Illustrated Mythology<br>
<strong>Read if you’re:</strong> A dreamer drawn to stories that connect humanity and nature.<br>
<!-- -->👉 <a href="https://www.amazon.in/When-Birds-Talked-Folklore-Hills/dp/0143476564" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">View on Amazon India</a></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-reimagining-indias-economy--arun-maira">3. Reimagining India’s Economy – <em>Arun Maira</em><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/best-new-books-october-2025-reviews-recommendations#3-reimagining-indias-economy--arun-maira" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3-reimagining-indias-economy--arun-maira" title="Direct link to 3-reimagining-indias-economy--arun-maira" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The former Planning Commission member invites readers to challenge GDP obsessions and rediscover inclusive, purpose-driven growth. A timely reflection for those who believe India’s story deserves a more humane script.</p>
<p><strong>Genre:</strong> Economic Critique, Public Policy<br>
<strong>Read if you’re:</strong> A policymaker, founder, or citizen invested in the nation’s long-term well-being.<br>
<!-- -->👉 <a href="https://www.amazon.in/Reimagining-Indias-Economy-Equitable-Society/dp/9363360512" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">View on Amazon India</a></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="4-the-caste-con-census--anand-teltumbde">4. The Caste Con Census – <em>Anand Teltumbde</em><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/best-new-books-october-2025-reviews-recommendations#4-the-caste-con-census--anand-teltumbde" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4-the-caste-con-census--anand-teltumbde" title="Direct link to 4-the-caste-con-census--anand-teltumbde" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>An unflinching critique of the caste census narrative — exploring whether data empowers reform or reinforces division. A sharp, necessary read in India’s evolving social debate.</p>
<p><strong>Genre:</strong> Sociology, Politics, Indian Society<br>
<strong>Read if you’re:</strong> A critical thinker who prefers nuance over noise.<br>
<!-- -->👉 <a href="https://www.amazon.in/Caste-Census-Anand-Teltumbde/dp/B0FSF41V2V" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">View on Amazon India</a></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="5-heartbeats-a-memoir--björn-borg">5. Heartbeats: A Memoir – <em>Björn Borg</em><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/best-new-books-october-2025-reviews-recommendations#5-heartbeats-a-memoir--bj%C3%B6rn-borg" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5-heartbeats-a-memoir--björn-borg" title="Direct link to 5-heartbeats-a-memoir--björn-borg" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Beyond the ice-cool legend lies a man wrestling with pressure, fame, and solitude. Borg’s memoir humanizes greatness — a rare confession from tennis’s original enigma.</p>
<p><strong>Genre:</strong> Sports Memoir<br>
<strong>Read if you’re:</strong> A sports lover or anyone curious about the cost of chasing perfection.<br>
<!-- -->👉 <a href="https://www.amazon.in/Heartbeats-Memoir-Bj%C3%B6rn-Borg-ebook/dp/B0F6KCH18D" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">View on Amazon India</a></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="closing-note">Closing Note<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/best-new-books-october-2025-reviews-recommendations#closing-note" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Closing Note" title="Direct link to Closing Note" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Every book in this month’s list reflects a <strong>different dimension of intelligence</strong> — analytical, cultural, economic, and emotional. That balance is precisely what <em>Your Update Officer</em> curates: not more noise, but the <strong>right updates that move you forward.</strong></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Next up: <em>Finance and AI Picks for November 2025.</em><br>
<!-- -->Stay tuned at <a href="https://yourupdateofficer.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">yourupdateofficer.com</a></p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>book reviews</category>
            <category>new book releases 2025</category>
            <category>best books to read</category>
            <category>Indian authors</category>
            <category>international bestsellers</category>
            <category>book recommendations</category>
            <category>reading list</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Consumer vs Business PCs: Why Enterprises Still Pay a Premium]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A technical deep-dive into why business PCs outlast and outperform consumer laptops, with a 2025 update on NPUs, AI integration, and enterprise-grade hardware.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/business-laptop-vs-consumer-laptop-5f2539f3c91d64cdff61aed54db98196.png" width="1536" height="1024" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>My journey with computers has been… vivid.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Started with an assembled PC which broke in 2 years</li>
<li class="">Tried a netbook which looked like a toy in hindsight, broke in 2 years</li>
<li class="">Switched to a refurbished Dell CPU from an unreliable shop which lasted 6 months, abandoned at the repair shop</li>
<li class="">Bought a Dell Inspiron (used) which surprisingly served 9 years (10 years total age)</li>
<li class="">Worked with at least 10+ managed devices given by employers</li>
<li class="">Today<!-- -->
<ul>
<li class="">running a Dell Precision (11th gen CPU) for coding, content creation and local LLMs</li>
<li class="">running a Dell Inspiron (4th gen CPU) for browsing and on the move</li>
<li class="">M1 mac managed by employer</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>TLDR: Consumer printers vs business printers. Consumer cars vs taxis. Consumer PCs vs business PCs. The business-grade version always outlives the shiny consumer one.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here’s why business PCs dominate both new and used markets.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="business-laptops-usp">Business laptops USP<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#business-laptops-usp" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Business laptops USP" title="Direct link to Business laptops USP" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-reliability-out-of-the-box">1. Reliability Out of the Box<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#1-reliability-out-of-the-box" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. Reliability Out of the Box" title="Direct link to 1. Reliability Out of the Box" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Consumer laptops are built for light use, good on a store shelf. Stress them and you’ll see broken hinges, dead keyboards, flimsy motherboards, and underpowered chargers.</p>
<p>Business laptops look boring, but they are engineered for 5–7 years of daily grind. Hinges, chargers, and keyboards are higher grade. Battery management is smarter and avoids overcharging when docked all day.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-trusted-platform-module-tpm">2. Trusted Platform Module (TPM)<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#2-trusted-platform-module-tpm" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Trusted Platform Module (TPM)" title="Direct link to 2. Trusted Platform Module (TPM)" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>A dedicated security chip that stores BitLocker keys, passwords, and certificates.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Provides transparent disk encryption: your PC boots normally, but if the drive is moved to another machine, it’s unreadable.</li>
<li class="">Caveat: if the motherboard dies, recovery requires a backup of the bitlocker keys.</li>
<li class="">You may need Windows 11 or 10 Pro license to get the most of this feature.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-intel-vpro--amd-pro">3. Intel vPro / AMD PRO<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#3-intel-vpro--amd-pro" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Intel vPro / AMD PRO" title="Direct link to 3. Intel vPro / AMD PRO" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Not just a CPU feature. It enables remote management at the firmware level.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">IT admins can wake, patch, or wipe a laptop remotely—even if powered off.</li>
<li class="">This is why enterprises never ship Windows Home on corporate machines.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="4-neural-processing-unit-npu">4. Neural Processing Unit (NPU)<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#4-neural-processing-unit-npu" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4. Neural Processing Unit (NPU)" title="Direct link to 4. Neural Processing Unit (NPU)" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>The latest upgrade in 2025 laptops (Intel Core Ultra, AMD Ryzen AI, Qualcomm Snapdragon X) also known as AI PCs lineup.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">NPUs accelerate on-device AI such as Teams background blur, Copilot, and real-time translation.</li>
<li class="">Offloads work from CPU/GPU and improves battery life.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="5-ecc-ram-error-correcting-code">5. ECC RAM (Error-Correcting Code)<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#5-ecc-ram-error-correcting-code" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5. ECC RAM (Error-Correcting Code)" title="Direct link to 5. ECC RAM (Error-Correcting Code)" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Detects and fixes bit flips, crucial for finance, engineering, and scientific workloads.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Common in workstations such as Dell Precision, Lenovo ThinkPad P-series, and HP ZBook.</li>
<li class="">Developers today find 32 GB as a sweet spot. Workstations can scale to 64–128 GB if needed.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="6-smart-card-readers-and-biometrics">6. Smart Card Readers and Biometrics<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#6-smart-card-readers-and-biometrics" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 6. Smart Card Readers and Biometrics" title="Direct link to 6. Smart Card Readers and Biometrics" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Frequent logins add friction. Business PCs integrate:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Smart card slots</li>
<li class="">Fingerprint sensors</li>
<li class="">IR cameras with Windows Hello</li>
</ul>
<p>Hardware-based authentication is both secure and fast.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="7-physical-locks">7. Physical Locks<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#7-physical-locks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 7. Physical Locks" title="Direct link to 7. Physical Locks" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>The Kensington lock slot still exists. Rarely used at home but still standard in ThinkPads, Latitudes, and EliteBooks.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="8-workload-testing-and-certification">8. Workload Testing and Certification<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#8-workload-testing-and-certification" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 8. Workload Testing and Certification" title="Direct link to 8. Workload Testing and Certification" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Business lines undergo validation for CAD, video editing, and financial modeling.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Dell Precision and Lenovo ThinkPad P-series are ISV certified for tools like AutoCAD, SolidWorks, and Adobe Premiere.</li>
<li class="">Ensures stability under heat and sustained load.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="9-ports-that-still-matter">9. Ports That Still Matter<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#9-ports-that-still-matter" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 9. Ports That Still Matter" title="Direct link to 9. Ports That Still Matter" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Unlike Macs, business laptops keep Ethernet, HDMI, multiple USB-A, C ports, and docking connectors.</p>
<p>Legacy ports survive because enterprises still run projectors, wired keyboards, and VPN boxes.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="10-serviceability-and-spares">10. Serviceability and Spares<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#10-serviceability-and-spares" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 10. Serviceability and Spares" title="Direct link to 10. Serviceability and Spares" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Easy to swap RAM, SSD, and batteries.</li>
<li class="">Huge second-hand parts market due to enterprise refresh cycles.</li>
<li class="">Dell, Lenovo, and HP provide 5+ years of driver and firmware support.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="11-nvidia-or-not">11. NVIDIA or Not?<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#11-nvidia-or-not" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 11. NVIDIA or Not?" title="Direct link to 11. NVIDIA or Not?" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Most business laptops use integrated graphics only.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">If workloads demand it (CAD, AI, 3D design), NVIDIA RTX or A-series workstation GPUs are offered.</li>
<li class="">Certified drivers ensure stability, unlike gaming GPUs.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="12-conservative-storage-options">12. Conservative Storage Options<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#12-conservative-storage-options" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 12. Conservative Storage Options" title="Direct link to 12. Conservative Storage Options" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Standard configuration is 512 GB NVMe SSD.<br>
<!-- -->IT-managed fleets prefer predictable configurations and controlled upgrades.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="13-thermal-engineering">13. Thermal Engineering<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#13-thermal-engineering" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 13. Thermal Engineering" title="Direct link to 13. Thermal Engineering" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Fans and vents are designed for cooling, not aesthetics.<br>
<!-- -->Consumer ultrabooks overheat under load, while business laptops throttle less.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="14-displays-and-media">14. Displays and Media<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#14-displays-and-media" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 14. Displays and Media" title="Direct link to 14. Displays and Media" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Standard = 14-inch, FHD, anti-glare panels.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Panels are tuned for battery life and productivity, not entertainment.</li>
<li class="">Webcam, mic, and speakers are optimized for meetings, not binge-watching.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="15-fast-charging-bricks">15. Fast Charging Bricks<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#15-fast-charging-bricks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 15. Fast Charging Bricks" title="Direct link to 15. Fast Charging Bricks" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Business chargers are 90W–130W, larger but faster.<br>
<!-- -->A quick lunch break can give you 50–60% recharge.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="16-wireless-audio-headsets-with-mic">16. Wireless Audio Headsets with Mic<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#16-wireless-audio-headsets-with-mic" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 16. Wireless Audio Headsets with Mic" title="Direct link to 16. Wireless Audio Headsets with Mic" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Microsoft Teams has revolutionized the market for audio devices. With Teams-certified devices becoming the default, wireless headsets with mics are now standard issue.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Depend on USB-C charging.</li>
<li class="">Last 2 days of moderate meetings and music.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="state-of-business-pcs-in-2025">State of Business PCs in 2025<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#state-of-business-pcs-in-2025" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to State of Business PCs in 2025" title="Direct link to State of Business PCs in 2025" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Business laptops have started embracing AI as a first-class feature:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">NPUs are now standard in Intel Core Ultra, AMD Ryzen AI, and Qualcomm Snapdragon X series, powering on-device AI tasks without draining the GPU.</li>
<li class="">Windows 11 Pro integrates deeply with hardware security, making TPM and vPro more relevant than ever.</li>
<li class="">Enterprise models increasingly offer <strong>Wi-Fi 7</strong> and <strong>5G modules</strong> for field work.</li>
<li class="">Battery tech has improved, with some models offering <strong>65Wh–97Wh packs</strong> plus rapid charge, making them all-day machines.</li>
<li class="">Docking stations have gone fully USB-C/Thunderbolt, retiring mechanical docks but preserving enterprise workflows.</li>
<li class="">Eco-conscious designs are rising: modular parts, recycled materials, and longer official support lifecycles.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="enterprise-hardware-watchlist-august-2025">Enterprise Hardware Watchlist: August 2025<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#enterprise-hardware-watchlist-august-2025" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Enterprise Hardware Watchlist: August 2025" title="Direct link to Enterprise Hardware Watchlist: August 2025" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>From an IT admin’s desk, here’s what business owners should track before refreshing their fleets.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="cpu">CPU<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#cpu" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to CPU" title="Direct link to CPU" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Intel Core Ultra (Meteor Lake / Lunar Lake)</strong>: Common in Dell Latitude, HP EliteBook, Lenovo ThinkPad. Strong balance of efficiency + AI.</li>
<li class=""><strong>AMD Ryzen AI 300 series</strong>: Multi-core leaders, shipping with NPUs, used in ThinkPads and HP ProBooks.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Qualcomm Snapdragon X</strong>: ARM-based, efficient, integrated 5G, driving Microsoft Surface and select Lenovo/HP.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="memory">Memory<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#memory" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Memory" title="Direct link to Memory" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>16 GB LPDDR5x</strong> is baseline, <strong>32 GB+ DDR5/ECC</strong> in workstations.</li>
<li class="">Soldered RAM in ultrabooks, modular SO-DIMMs in workstation-class devices.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="graphics--gpu">Graphics / GPU<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#graphics--gpu" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Graphics / GPU" title="Direct link to Graphics / GPU" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Integrated (Intel Xe, AMD Radeon, Qualcomm Adreno) good enough for most tasks.</li>
<li class="">NVIDIA RTX A-series still essential for CAD, 3D, ML training at the edge.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="npu">NPU<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#npu" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to NPU" title="Direct link to NPU" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Intel AI Boost, AMD Ryzen AI, Qualcomm Hexagon: 30–50 TOPS on-device AI.</li>
<li class="">By 2025, NPUs are standard across enterprise laptops.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="display">Display<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#display" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Display" title="Direct link to Display" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">14–15.6 inch FHD+ IPS panels dominate.</li>
<li class="">Touchscreen and convertible form factors (HP x360, ThinkPad Yoga) gaining ground.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="storage">Storage<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#storage" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Storage" title="Direct link to Storage" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Default: 256–512 GB PCIe Gen 4 NVMe SSD.</li>
<li class="">Workstations: 1–2 TB PCIe Gen 5 SSDs, sometimes with RAID.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="webcam">Webcam<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#webcam" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Webcam" title="Direct link to Webcam" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">720p still lingers, but 1080p IR cameras are becoming default in premium models.</li>
<li class="">AI-assisted autoframing and background blur now run on NPUs.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="connectivity">Connectivity<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#connectivity" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Connectivity" title="Direct link to Connectivity" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">USB-C/Thunderbolt 4 or 5 for docks, still keeping some USB-A and HDMI.</li>
<li class="">Ethernet ports survive in larger T-series/Latitude machines.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="networking">Networking<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#networking" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Networking" title="Direct link to Networking" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Wi-Fi 7</strong> standard in new 2025 refreshes.</li>
<li class="">Optional 5G/LTE modems in rugged and field-oriented models.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="biometrics">Biometrics<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#biometrics" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Biometrics" title="Direct link to Biometrics" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Fingerprint sensors standard.</li>
<li class="">IR cameras with Windows Hello face unlock becoming common.</li>
<li class="">Smart card readers still present in compliance-heavy industries.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="battery">Battery<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#battery" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Battery" title="Direct link to Battery" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">50–65 Wh packs for thin-and-light.</li>
<li class="">86–97 Wh for mobile workstations.</li>
<li class="">Fast charging (50% in 30 minutes) across Dell, Lenovo, HP.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="color--material">Color &amp; Material:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#color--material" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Color &amp; Material:" title="Direct link to Color &amp; Material:" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Business PCs lean towards black, grey, or navy blue matte finishes — less flashy, more professional.</li>
<li class="">Materials: magnesium alloy (light + strong), aluminum chassis (premium feel, good thermals), and carbon fiber composites (lightweight + durable for ThinkPads).</li>
<li class="">Plastic-only builds are almost gone from premium lines, reserved for entry-level.</li>
<li class="">Fingerprint resistance coatings and MIL-STD-810H certifications are selling points for enterprise fleets.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="total-cost-of-ownership-and-buying-decision">Total Cost of Ownership and Buying Decision<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#total-cost-of-ownership-and-buying-decision" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Total Cost of Ownership and Buying Decision" title="Direct link to Total Cost of Ownership and Buying Decision" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="why-pay-a-premium">Why Pay a Premium?<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#why-pay-a-premium" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why Pay a Premium?" title="Direct link to Why Pay a Premium?" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Business PCs almost always come with higher upfront costs, but TCO—the sum of purchase, support, downtime, and productivity—strongly favors business-grade hardware[3][4][10].</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Studies estimate the TCO for a well-managed business laptop to range from $4,600 to $9,793 over three years, with most savings coming from reduced downtime and support costs[4].</li>
<li class="">A device with a 1% failure rate versus 5% can save a company over $330,000 annually per 1,000 laptops, primarily through reduced productivity loss and support expenses[4].</li>
<li class="">Extended warranty, sled deployment, multi-year OS support, and modular parts drive long-term value.</li>
<li class="">IT operations costs (OPEX) and user downtime can exceed capital costs for hardware—lowering failures, easier service, and scalable deployment lead to major ROI[1][3][4].</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="how-should-business-owners-decide">How Should Business Owners Decide?<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#how-should-business-owners-decide" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How Should Business Owners Decide?" title="Direct link to How Should Business Owners Decide?" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Match hardware to intended use:</strong> Office tasks, fieldwork, or production workloads need corresponding device durability and support.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Balance upgrade cycles and productivity:</strong> Short cycles add complexity and expense; longer lifecycles (5+ years) minimize disruptions.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Consider indirect costs:</strong> Support, downtime, security breaches, compliance, and device failures are more expensive than the purchase price.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Plan for the future:</strong> Invest in modular, repairable hardware with warranty and vendor support. Evaluate AI features, but monitor real-world impact before heavy adoption.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Engage IT and end-users:</strong> Gather feedback from IT on manageability and from users on workflow bottlenecks.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="final-word">Final Word<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/features-found-only-in-business-pc#final-word" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Final Word" title="Direct link to Final Word" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Consumer PCs are designed to look good.<br>
<!-- -->Business PCs are designed to last, secure, and serve.</p>
<p>If you are a heavy user who hates downtime, a business PC—new or used—is still the smarter investment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Business PCs</category>
            <category>Enterprise Laptops</category>
            <category>PC Hardware</category>
            <category>NPUs</category>
            <category>Workstations</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My Role as Felicitation Chair at the Area D5 Joint Meeting]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[At a prestigious joint Toastmasters event featuring clubs from Hosur, Vellore, and beyond, I took the mic as Felicitation Chair. Here’s what went down, how I prepared, and why this underestimated role deserves more credit.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/felicitation-ceremony-15ad2dedcbcd2cd40bd2bd3c2abdb177.png" width="1536" height="1024" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<iframe title="The Art of Felicitation: A Toastmasters Tale" allowtransparency="true" height="300" width="100%" style="border:none;min-width:min(100%, 430px);height:175px;margin-bottom:20px" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&amp;i=6aki4-193504b-pb&amp;square=1&amp;share=1&amp;download=1&amp;fonts=Arial&amp;skin=1&amp;font-color=auto&amp;rtl=0&amp;logo_link=episode_page&amp;btn-skin=3ab278&amp;size=300" loading="lazy" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<blockquote>
<p><em>"The best section of Toastmasters sessions? The one where the winners are announced and felicitated."</em><br>
<!-- -->— Me, after surviving the Felicitation Chair role.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="a-meeting-of-minds">A Meeting of Minds<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience#a-meeting-of-minds" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A Meeting of Minds" title="Direct link to A Meeting of Minds" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>This wasn’t just another club meeting.</p>
<p>It was a <strong>cross-border alliance of wit, wisdom, and wow-moments</strong> — a <strong>joint meeting of Area A5 clubs</strong>, featuring powerhouses from <strong>Vellore, Hosur</strong>, mind blowing education session speakers and beyond.</p>
<p>And right at the tail end of this prestigious gathering, I was handed a mic and a mission: to felicitate, celebrate, and wrap up sessions like a pro — all in <strong>under 45 seconds per role taker</strong>.</p>
<p>Here’s what the felicitation ceremony looked like:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">20 people to be felicitated</li>
<li class="">3 dignitaries on stage</li>
<li class="">Me giving light-hearted appreciation</li>
<li class="">Person comes on stage, collects the gift</li>
<li class="">Photographer gives a thumbs up after the click</li>
<li class="">I call the next person</li>
</ul>
<p>Smooth, right? Almost.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="my-preparation">My Preparation<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience#my-preparation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to My Preparation" title="Direct link to My Preparation" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The official Toastmasters website had <em>hardly any information</em> on the felicitation role.</p>
<p>Later, in a discussion with my <strong>mentee-turned-DTM</strong>, I learned that this role is the <strong>brainchild of the Conference Chair</strong> — someone who truly believes in the “division of labour”... or should I say, <em>division of roles</em>.</p>
<p>Though the plan was to have two people share the felicitation duties, the universe decided that one person — me — was a perfect (and only) fit.</p>
<p>Special shoutout to <strong>TM Monica, CA</strong>, whose calm, coaching-style leadership helped me manage the logistics and statistics required to perform this role without chaos.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-script-i-used-as-felicitation-chair">The Script I Used as Felicitation Chair<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience#the-script-i-used-as-felicitation-chair" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Script I Used as Felicitation Chair" title="Direct link to The Script I Used as Felicitation Chair" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="tm-style-opening-hook">TM-style Opening Hook<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience#tm-style-opening-hook" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to TM-style Opening Hook" title="Direct link to TM-style Opening Hook" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<blockquote>
<p>On a Sunday, if I start my bike before 9 AM, it knows exactly where to go — straight to the farmers’ market, where I shop mindfully without worrying about GST.<br>
<!-- -->But today isn’t an ordinary Sunday.<br>
<!-- -->A Toastmasters conference in my sleepy little town, <strong>Hosur</strong>, with members from <strong>District 120 and beyond</strong> converging at <strong>Advaith School</strong> — now <em>that</em> deserves a chapter in history.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For making this happen, everyone in this room deserves to be felicitated.</p>
<p>The felicitation ceremony had <strong>two parts</strong>:<br>
<strong>Part 1</strong> – Role players<br>
<strong>Part 2</strong> – Honouring the <em>crust above the rest</em></p>
<hr>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="part-1--felicitating-the-role-takers">Part 1 – Felicitating the Role Takers<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience#part-1--felicitating-the-role-takers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Part 1 – Felicitating the Role Takers" title="Direct link to Part 1 – Felicitating the Role Takers" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>I invited the following dignitaries to the stage:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Division A Director <strong>TM Pratheepa Sukumar</strong></li>
<li class="">Area D5 Director <strong>TM Bharat Nandhagopal</strong></li>
<li class="">Conference Chair <strong>TM Caroline Padankatti</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Let the show begin:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p><em>“From gathering registrations on AllEvents to reminding us to carry water bottles, pens, and sharing every crucial detail — welcome on stage, Registration Chair <strong>TM Samuel</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“The silent force of Hosur Toastmasters, from co-registration to backend updates — welcome, Co-registration Chair <strong>TM Saravanan</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“From informative posters to nostalgic TV-box reels and timely reminders — welcome, PR Chair <strong>TM Vani Ugin</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“From backstage coffee to guest care — you were everywhere! Welcome, Hospitality Chair and mighty president of Hosur TM, <strong>TM Gary Michael Henderson</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“Your voice carried confidence and set the morning tempo — Emcee Morning, <strong>TM Abidha Shah</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“Professional, composed, and to the point — Timer, <strong>TM Priyadharshini</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“Post-lunch slump didn’t stand a chance — Emcee Afternoon, <strong>TM Nandini</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“Solid stage presence and seamless coordination — <strong>TM Ramesh</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“Every great event runs on time, and every second counts — Timer, <strong>TM Saranya</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“Delivering precise timing reports — Timer, <strong>TM Abinaya Kannan</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>“She set the venue, ran behind mics, and now she’s at center stage handing over gifts — our SAA, <strong>TM Monica</strong>!”</em></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><em>And of course, <strong>TM Balaji</strong> – myself, multitasking through all of this with a grin.</em></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I did go off-script occasionally to inject humor — the energy in the room had started dipping post-lunch, and quite a few attendees had already <em>vanished</em> for their afternoon nap.</p>
<hr>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="part-2--felicitating-the-bosses-of-tm">Part 2 – Felicitating the Bosses of TM<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience#part-2--felicitating-the-bosses-of-tm" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Part 2 – Felicitating the Bosses of TM" title="Direct link to Part 2 – Felicitating the Bosses of TM" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Next, I invited the <em>District Trio</em> — a term I learned just a week earlier:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>District Director, DTM Parthasarathy</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Club Growth Director, DTM Anirudh</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Program Quality Director, TM Vinoth Kumar</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Also invited, in the same sequence:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Division A Director, TM Pratheepa Sukumar</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Area D5 Director, TM Bharat Nandhagopal</strong> – effortlessly cool</li>
<li class=""><strong>TM Caroline Padankatti</strong> – the power behind the stage who stayed composed even during 9 PM Google Meet marathons</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="my-self-evaluation">My Self-Evaluation<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience#my-self-evaluation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to My Self-Evaluation" title="Direct link to My Self-Evaluation" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>I'd rate myself <strong>4 out of 5</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">I came prepared</li>
<li class="">I added personal flair</li>
<li class="">I adjusted in real time</li>
</ul>
<p>One thing I would do differently: I should have <strong>orchestrated stage movements better</strong>, such as having the first set of dignitaries return to their seats before inviting the next batch.</p>
<p>Other than that, the show went smoothly.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="what-is-the-felicitation-chair">What <em>is</em> the Felicitation Chair?<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience#what-is-the-felicitation-chair" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-is-the-felicitation-chair" title="Direct link to what-is-the-felicitation-chair" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class="">It's the segment where the audience starts <strong>scanning for snacks</strong> (pun intended)</li>
<li class="">Role takers and dignitaries expect a <strong>professional wrap-up</strong>, not a duct-tape script</li>
<li class="">You’ll have <strong>last-minute add-ons</strong> whispered to you in front of 50 people while you’re holding a mic and pretending everything’s under control</li>
<li class="">You must remain <strong>calm, composed, and ready to improvise</strong></li>
<li class="">Carrying notes isn't optional — it’s a <strong>survival tool</strong></li>
<li class="">Yes, you do get felicitated in the same ceremony (just don’t expect a standing ovation)</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="final-words">Final Words<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/applause-to-roasts-my-felicitation-chair-experience#final-words" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Final Words" title="Direct link to Final Words" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>If you're ever asked to be the <strong>Felicitation Chair</strong> at your club or area event — don’t hesitate.</p>
<p>Say yes.<br>
<!-- -->Bring your A-game.<br>
<!-- -->And remember:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Claps fade.<br>
<!-- -->But well-worded praise? That sticks.</strong></p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>toastmasters</category>
            <category>leadership</category>
            <category>public-speaking</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[React Nexus 2025 in 25 Points]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/react-nexus-2025-3-day-summary-in-25-points</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/react-nexus-2025-3-day-summary-in-25-points</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A dry, nerdy summary from a lead frontend dev’s second visit to React Nexus. Includes speaker highlights, sponsor buzz, and a gentle roast of conference clichés.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="react-nexus-2025-react-harder">React Nexus 2025: React Harder<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/react-nexus-2025-3-day-summary-in-25-points#react-nexus-2025-react-harder" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to React Nexus 2025: React Harder" title="Direct link to React Nexus 2025: React Harder" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/React-Nexus-25-29e86cb60ebeff1b87f9657959151cdd.jpg" width="1000" height="1333" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Second time at React Nexus. Bigger venue, bigger sponsors, same old dev jokes. Held at Tata Auditorium, IISC – beautiful place if you like trees and long walks to the nearest metro.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="what-went-down-other-than-my-battery">What Went Down (Other Than My Battery)<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/react-nexus-2025-3-day-summary-in-25-points#what-went-down-other-than-my-battery" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What Went Down (Other Than My Battery)" title="Direct link to What Went Down (Other Than My Battery)" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Logistics</strong>:
One sticker. One tee. One meal per day. That’s the deal. Cab-friendly, metro-unfriendly.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Sponsors</strong>:
Took the stage like Bollywood villains. Some reruns from 2024. Gemini &amp; Copilot aced the quizzes more than the attendees did.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/sponsors-44ad1423ee2098555ff050f07af75a4e.jpg" width="1000" height="750" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>ImageKit.io</strong>:
Indie builder CEO handing out stickers = 🫶
Who knew images + GenAI + AWS could be a profitable cocktail?</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>GoDaddy</strong>:
Still selling domains like flash sales. Bought one. Page still says “Hello World.” Now with GenAI, <em>they</em> add the hello page for you. Still pushing Outlook 365 like it’s going out of stock.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Vonage</strong>:
Zoom-ish APIs. Most colorful booth. Least understood by crowd. They were hiring.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>WSO2 Asgardeo</strong>:
Auth-as-a-service. Repeat speaker, repeat stickers. Still no buy-in from bosses.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Zoho Catalyst</strong>:
“Run everything with us (on free tier).” Indie energy, real. Good for side projects, enterprise signup after sales men raids. Might convert prompt to SaaS if you squint hard enough.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Code of Conduct Slide</strong>:
The usual “don’t harass women” clause. But honestly, dev conferences now look like HR onboarding. 50/50 gender ratio. Welcome change.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>React 19 + NextJS</strong>:
Headliners. React Actions API opened the show. Time to un-dust the docs.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Audience Engagement</strong>:
Peak Bangalore moment: guy hacked, built, and launched a product on New Year’s Eve. 🙌</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>React Compiler</strong>:
Still a mystery box. Used in 3D video gen demo—hit and miss.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Best Speaker?</strong>
Wadad Parker. Tackled React Context with stand-up energy. Put Toastmasters to shame.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>GoDaddy Talk on Microfrontends</strong>:
Enlightening. But no tools, just “vibes.”</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Tech Company vs Software Company vs Vibe-Coded Startup</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Tech company = builds tech</li>
<li class="">Software company = builds from packages</li>
<li class="">Vibe-coded = builds vibes, nothing else</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Zoho Catalyst (again)</strong>:
Their domain setup is easier than your weekend plans.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Lighthouse Talk (again)</strong>:
Same speaker. Same slides. Different year. Look at <code>web.dev</code> if you need filler content, apparently.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Monitoring &amp; Observability</strong>:
Not the same. One alerts, one explains. Both are friends now.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Frontend QA</strong>:
Smoke tests &gt; Nothing.
Playwright &gt; Hope.
Monitoring &gt; Late-night debugging.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Telemetry 101</strong>:
Metrics, logs, traces... add them to your design system if you want to sound senior.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>AI Tools</strong>:
Cursor’s @web, @docs, @diff = DevGPT mode unlocked.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>MCP (Magic Component Platform)</strong>:
Figma → Code without tears.
Everyone's happy. Until you self-host it online and leak your keys.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>React Dev Joke Moment</strong>:
“Lazy loading is like buying 10 chips, eating one at a time.”
Me: “Bro that’s throttling. Lazy loading = frequent runs to the shop.”</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>React Native</strong>:
Few talks. Fewer fans. Still exists.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Browser-LLMs</strong>:
Local LLMs in your browser soon. Because why not.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong>:
React is evolving, audiences are engaging, and conferences are quietly becoming better. React Nexus 2025 felt more like a community summit than a sponsor expo—despite the sponsor overload. Chennai devs showed up in droves. Peaceful vibes. Good chai. No one shipped to production from the venue, which is a win.</p>
<p><strong>P.S.</strong> I still haven’t deployed that domain I bought.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/react-nexus-attendance-86e8b36ea7f2d988f360281ccbf59457.jpg" width="1000" height="750" class="img_jvCJ"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>react</category>
            <category>react-conferences</category>
            <category>frontend</category>
            <category>developer-events</category>
            <category>tech-humor</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[14 Years in Tech, 7 Years with One Company: Notes from the Edge of Impermanence]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 10:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[After 14 years in tech—including 7 years with one company—this is not a celebration post. It’s a reality check on jobs, layoffs, AI, and the myths we silently carry in the modern workplace.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/7-years-86bf28f3dd62c427602a255a33456fdb.png" width="1536" height="1024" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>After 14 years in tech — including 7 years at my current company — this isn't a celebration post. It's a reflection.</p>
<p>A career this long doesn’t just give you experience. It gives you patterns. You start noticing what stays, what fades, and what was never real to begin with.</p>
<p>This post isn’t about growth charts, anniversaries, or achievements. It’s a reality check. Especially for those who entered the workforce with dreams shaped by college lectures, parental expectations, or HR onboarding decks.</p>
<p>Bookmark it. Revisit it. Especially when the winds change.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="jobs-are-forever--the-myth-we-bought">Jobs Are Forever — The Myth We Bought<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer#jobs-are-forever--the-myth-we-bought" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Jobs Are Forever — The Myth We Bought" title="Direct link to Jobs Are Forever — The Myth We Bought" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>We were told a job is a destination. Land one, and you’re safe. Study hard, get placed, follow the system, and one day retire in peace. That illusion didn’t survive its first encounter with real-world volatility. For many of us, it collapsed not in our first job, but in the uncertainty of the second or third, where layoffs weren’t just newspaper headlines — they were personal. I vividly remember 2012 — hearing the word <em>layoff</em> not in a company-wide announcement, but in hushed conversations. Someone had run a SQL script to revoke access for 2,000 employees. That one line of code unraveled years of effort in milliseconds.</p>
<p>Like Abhimanyu in the Mahabharata’s chakra vyuha — we were trained to enter the maze, but never taught how to exit with dignity or direction.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="trainings-will-save-you--another-false-promise">Trainings Will Save You — Another False Promise<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer#trainings-will-save-you--another-false-promise" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Trainings Will Save You — Another False Promise" title="Direct link to Trainings Will Save You — Another False Promise" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Every new tool promises salvation. There's always a 10-hour video, a certification badge, or a learning week calendar invite. But knowledge ≠ transformation. You can’t train your way out of stagnation if you never practice. I’ve seen folks with "12 years of experience" who’ve actually repeated the same year twelve times.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, younger teammates with fewer years and sharper instincts bulldoze ahead because they build, break, and ship things. That edge doesn’t come from upskilling videos — it comes from showing up, making calls, failing fast, and bouncing back faster.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="hold-virtual-ownership--but-dont-drown-in-it">Hold Virtual Ownership — But Don’t Drown in It<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer#hold-virtual-ownership--but-dont-drown-in-it" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Hold Virtual Ownership — But Don’t Drown in It" title="Direct link to Hold Virtual Ownership — But Don’t Drown in It" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>"Take ownership" is on every job description and manager’s checklist. But what does it actually mean in a workplace where ownership is distributed so thinly that no one has true decision power? We all know how “too many cooks” ends. At some point, everyone owns everything and yet nothing gets done. Developer productivity becomes a metric sport, while the product itself has no paying users. Market validation? Not my department. We just sprint. It feels like a rush-hour metro ride — packed, sweaty, and no one is willing to adjust for the person next to them. Everyone's pushing, no one knows where the train is heading.</p>
<p>Virtual ownership without real influence breeds burnout. Masked as initiative, rewarded with more tasks. And if your work isn’t directly influencing product adoption or revenue?  <strong>Better believe someone’s already rewriting your goodbye message.</strong></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="your-worth--a-number">Your Worth = A Number<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer#your-worth--a-number" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Your Worth = A Number" title="Direct link to Your Worth = A Number" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Whether you’re a fresher or a VP, you are a number in a dashboard:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">CGPA</li>
<li class="">Leetcode percentile</li>
<li class="">Story points delivered</li>
<li class="">Uptime maintained</li>
<li class="">Revenue influenced</li>
<li class="">Cost avoided</li>
</ul>
<p>If your work can’t be quantified, it’s sidelined. Worse — you start internalizing the idea that you’re not contributing enough, even if you’re the glue holding teams together. I learned this late: Emotional intelligence, long-term thinking, culture-building — these don’t show up in slides. But the system demands that even these be justified with metrics. If not, you risk being seen as "nice to have" when it's time to downsize.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="layoffs-are-normalised--and-thats-not-going-away">Layoffs Are Normalised — And That’s Not Going Away<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer#layoffs-are-normalised--and-thats-not-going-away" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Layoffs Are Normalised — And That’s Not Going Away" title="Direct link to Layoffs Are Normalised — And That’s Not Going Away" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Layoffs are no longer the stuff of boardroom whispers. They're livestream events. Scripted, staged, and delivered over Zoom.</p>
<p>From Big Tech to startups, workforce cuts are no longer a reaction — they're a strategy.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">It’s not personal.</li>
<li class="">It’s not fair.</li>
<li class="">It’s just business.</li>
</ul>
<p>At the time of writing this post, TCS a prestigious Indian company where several employees stayed loyal to Tata Group where put on the line called "first ever 2% workforce reduction". Illustrating the fact, no company is layoff proof. You are only as secure as the revenue forecast or funding runway. You could be the highest performer and still be asked to go because your role didn’t “align with priorities.”</p>
<p>Every job now feels like a stock pick. You invest time, hope, and weekends into a bet that may or may not pay off. You rise and fall with the market mood.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="ai-the-elephant-in-every-meeting-room">AI: The Elephant in Every Meeting Room<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer#ai-the-elephant-in-every-meeting-room" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to AI: The Elephant in Every Meeting Room" title="Direct link to AI: The Elephant in Every Meeting Room" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>AI is the most discussed guest in the room — invited to every conversation, understood by very few.</p>
<p>In meetings, “Let’s bring in AI” is thrown around like a magical fix. But when asked what exactly it should do, silence follows. Truth is, <strong>AI is today what cloud was in 2012</strong> — full of promise, stuck in pitch decks. By 2030, AI will face its own audit. The novelty will wear off. Leaders will stop using it for press releases and start using it for results. And developers will stop fearing AI — not because it’s weak, but because they'll finally understand what it can and can't do.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="mental-health-is-a-joke">Mental Health Is a Joke<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer#mental-health-is-a-joke" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Mental Health Is a Joke" title="Direct link to Mental Health Is a Joke" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>It’s easy to preach balance when you’re a spiritual leader with a lake-view campus and loyal donors. But when you’re an employee living month-to-month, <strong>“balance” sounds like a luxury.</strong> When townhall invites trigger dread. When one reorg wipes out months of planning. When even good work ends with a “however” in the appraisal form. No wellness app will fix the anxiety of seeing colleagues disappear from Slack and payroll overnight.</p>
<p>Today, every employee has at least two AI tools watching their work, recording patterns, nudging suggestions — <strong>training to replace them</strong> more than to support them. It’s no longer fiction to imagine a future where brain-implanted AI boosts “efficiency.” Because hey, it’s more important to track keyboard strokes than to turn off the energy-guzzling TVs still looping yesterday’s metrics in an empty office bay.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="final-thought">Final Thought<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/7-years-with-one-employer#final-thought" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Final Thought" title="Direct link to Final Thought" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Work is no longer a straight line. It’s a loop.<br>
<strong>Learn → Build → Make money → Exit → Repeat</strong></p>
<p>14 years in tech. 7 years in one company. This milestone isn’t a victory lap. It’s a checkpoint. A reminder to stay <strong>adaptable</strong>, <strong>humble</strong>, and <strong>detached</strong>. Because in this industry, one truth reigns above all:</p>
<p><strong>Impermanence isn’t a bug — it’s the default setting.</strong></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>career</category>
            <category>tech-industry</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Discipline 2.0: Mesh Networks, NextDNS, and the Ongoing Battle Against YouTube]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/new-dad-network-safety-part-2</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/new-dad-network-safety-part-2</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 01:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A nerd-dad’s ongoing quest to baby-proof not just the furniture—but the family’s Wi-Fi and screens. NextDNS, mesh routers, and the practical realities of keeping YouTube out of reach without a SaaS subscription nightmare.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/new-tp-link-router-ad8c3f7d9dd46505c863d7daea414242.png" width="994" height="548" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="quick-recap">Quick Recap<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/new-dad-network-safety-part-2#quick-recap" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Quick Recap" title="Direct link to Quick Recap" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>We took our first swing at digital hygiene: <strong>NextDNS configured on a non-ISP router, mobile Private DNS set, the whole house subtly steering away from distractions.</strong> Our battle star? The never-ending chase to block YouTube.com for good.</p>
<p>But as always, the story gets more interesting.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-parental-control-problem--isp-routers-just-dont-cut-it">The Parental Control Problem — ISP Routers Just Don’t Cut It<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/new-dad-network-safety-part-2#the-parental-control-problem--isp-routers-just-dont-cut-it" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Parental Control Problem — ISP Routers Just Don’t Cut It" title="Direct link to The Parental Control Problem — ISP Routers Just Don’t Cut It" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The so-called “parental controls” on most ISP-supplied hardware are a masquerade. The DNS fields are locked down; your hands are tied. For real filtering, the only way out is to move to your own hardware so I picked up a <strong>TP-Link mesh router</strong> supporting true mesh networking.</p>
<p>Mesh brings coverage, flexibility, and—crucially—three distinct SSIDs:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Default</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Guest</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Smart Devices</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Now, with <strong>NextDNS</strong> set at the router level, everything in the house bows to centralized rules.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="nextdns-profiles-access-levels-like-iam-for-humans">NextDNS Profiles: Access Levels Like IAM for Humans<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/new-dad-network-safety-part-2#nextdns-profiles-access-levels-like-iam-for-humans" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to NextDNS Profiles: Access Levels Like IAM for Humans" title="Direct link to NextDNS Profiles: Access Levels Like IAM for Humans" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>One genius detail about NextDNS is its profile-based filtering, think of it like authorization groups in IAM. Here’s how my rules stack up:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Default:</strong> YouTube is blocked everywhere, the good citizens’ network.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Elders:</strong> YouTube allowed (but only when the baby’s not around).</li>
<li class=""><strong>Dev Mode:</strong> Everything permitted—for me, when it’s time to break things or fix them.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Side effect:</em> some analytics break, and anyone with the Tor app can waltz past the controls. It’s not bulletproof, but it’s pretty resilient.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="saas-fatigue-and-the-diy-fix">SaaS Fatigue and the DIY Fix<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/new-dad-network-safety-part-2#saas-fatigue-and-the-diy-fix" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to SaaS Fatigue and the DIY Fix" title="Direct link to SaaS Fatigue and the DIY Fix" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Here’s the catch: <strong>NextDNS’s free plan caps at 30,000 DNS requests/month</strong>. That’s enough for one or two users, but add a full house and you’ll hit the wall. The fear: getting locked into yet another SaaS subscription for every single filter.</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><em>Temporary solution:</em> Careful rationing, multiple profiles, and possibly automating some extra DNS protection. Still, I have DIY plans brewing to avoid lifelong lock-in.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-result-under-control-for-now">The Result: Under Control… For Now<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/new-dad-network-safety-part-2#the-result-under-control-for-now" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Result: Under Control… For Now" title="Direct link to The Result: Under Control… For Now" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>With distinct SSIDs, granular DNS filtering, and profile-based controls, the home network feels far more intentional and secure. The only wildcard? Human factors, will elders and guests play along or look for loopholes?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I personally save nearly 2 hours a day with no youtube, thats 30 days saved per year.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But for now, digital discipline is stronger than ever. Parenthood is chaos; your network doesn’t have to be.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>To fellow parents: tweaking your network takes patience, but the peace of mind is worth it. On to the next frontier…</em></p>
<p>[1] <a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>children</category>
            <category>computer-networks</category>
            <category>parental-controls</category>
            <category>nextdns</category>
            <category>mesh-routers</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[From Tragedy to Triumph: My New Laptop Specs]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-monsoon-laptop-saga</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-monsoon-laptop-saga</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[After eight years, my trusted Dell Inspiron met an untimely demise during the monsoon. This is the emotional journey of loss, recovery, and the search for a refurbished warrior to rebuild my creative momentum.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/dell-7620-desk-027e93728fc19d9f27c2585cdd32deb4.jpg" width="750" height="1000" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>It began as most heartbreaks do, not with a warning, but with a moment. Eight years of companionship, memories etched into plastic keys and flickering screens. This was not just a laptop; it was a cherished confidant, a silent witness to late-night hustles, travels, and the fragile trust between creator and machine.</p>
<p>But even strong bonds can snap. On a monsoon-drenched evening, fate delivered a blow. The Dell service center greeted me somberly, where a sticker cheerily warned about “monsoon laptop care”—advice, in my case, a little too late. The diagnosis: my beloved Dell Inspiron, dead on arrival. There were no heroic rescues, just a silent mourning and the slow ache that follows a familiar loss.</p>
<p>The fallout was immediate. Backlogs grew like weeds. Blogs languished in drafts as an interim Dell Vostro—salvaged from the garage and coaxed to life with Debian—struggled beneath the weight of creative ambition. The void left by the Inspiron haunted every click. Sooner or later, I knew: it was time to let go and move on.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-pursuit-of-power-and-value">The Pursuit of Power And Value<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-monsoon-laptop-saga#the-pursuit-of-power-and-value" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Pursuit of Power And Value" title="Direct link to The Pursuit of Power And Value" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>I dreamt, briefly, of a desktop—a machine built on ChatGPT-powered advice, futuristic and mighty. But reality grinned: a 3–5 lakh rupee price tag. It felt absurd, the cost outweighing the gains, with the grey cloud of warranty uncertainty looming. Dell’s tower PCs were impossible to “add to cart” without wading through conversations with bots; the tempting A51 desktop was a crush at first sight, quickly doomed by its price—well above ₹5 lakhs.</p>
<p>The configurations under Dell’s “Workstation” banner cost more than a new Ather Pro scooter. Disheartened, I wandered into the wilds of OLX, mentorless but hopeful.</p>
<p>On OLX, the market teemed with budget laptops—plentiful at 25k, but the beasts I needed lurked rarely, cloaked behind search filters: “Dell i7”, “50k and above”. And yet, despite Apple’s siren song and options aplenty, my heart stayed loyal to Dell—perhaps from habit, perhaps nostalgia.</p>
<p>On OLX, two sellers emerged: individuals hoping for a fair price, and seasoned shopkeepers flipping out-of-warranty stock. Caution prevailed; I chose the latter. Stranger meets in unknown places—money flashing on UPI—felt like a recipe for disaster. I wanted reliability, not adventure.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-resurrection-enter-dell-7620">The Resurrection: Enter Dell 7620<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-monsoon-laptop-saga#the-resurrection-enter-dell-7620" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Resurrection: Enter Dell 7620" title="Direct link to The Resurrection: Enter Dell 7620" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://www.rgcomputers.in/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">RG Computer, Belandur</a> was unassuming—a small shop, a friendly shopkeeper, and an attentive assistant. There, among reclaimed silicon, sat my contender: the Dell 7560. (Specs to come.) The inspection ritual began:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Checked the Dell service tag, verified the model’s lineage.</li>
<li class="">Scanned for scars—deep or faint—from previous lives.</li>
<li class="">BIOS revealed battery health and year of manufacture (both scrutinized).</li>
<li class="">Booted and rebooted, measuring patience.</li>
<li class="">Ran HW Info, checked SSD specs—ensuring no deceit hid beneath the surface.</li>
</ul>
<p>The shopkeeper walked me through their refurbishing process—old NVMe swapped for a fresh NVMe, a subtle upsell attempt gracefully declined. After two hours, I still forgot to check every key, but luck favored me; all were functional.</p>
<p>Armed with a bill and three months of shop-backed warranty, I walked out—lighter in heart, heavier in hand. The workstation is, in a word, solid. I do not recommend carrying it around on your back, its indeed heavy. I use my Dell Vostro for light work on the move.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="meet-the-beast-dell-7620">Meet the Beast: Dell 7620<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-monsoon-laptop-saga#meet-the-beast-dell-7620" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Meet the Beast: Dell 7620" title="Direct link to Meet the Beast: Dell 7620" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Intel i7, 11th Gen, 8 cores @2.50GHz</li>
<li class="">32GB DDR4 RAM</li>
<li class="">512GB healthy NVMe storage</li>
<li class="">Nvidia 6GB graphics</li>
<li class="">Windows 11 Pro</li>
</ul>
<p>Things I Don’t Understand Yet</p>
<ul>
<li class="">The 180W charger—why such a power-hungry beast for this machine?</li>
<li class="">The air vents, reminiscent of a car radiator, puzzling me with their design and purpose.</li>
<li class="">The CPU core temperatures, often hovering at 50°C and above—stable or stealth warning?</li>
</ul>
<p>Red Flags? Of course:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Out of Dell warranty, over four years old</li>
<li class="">Noticeable signs of prior use</li>
<li class="">Fingerprint sensor, more gimmick than guardian</li>
</ul>
<p>But for ₹55k? In my urgency, the deal felt fair. Back at the desk, it stood firm—two USB-Cs, two USBs, HDMI, and a DP port. It powers two monitors, a cooling pad, and more. The webcam is decent (bonus: a privacy slider).</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="epilogue-grief-growth-gratitude">Epilogue: Grief, Growth, Gratitude<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/my-monsoon-laptop-saga#epilogue-grief-growth-gratitude" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Epilogue: Grief, Growth, Gratitude" title="Direct link to Epilogue: Grief, Growth, Gratitude" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Three weeks in, I’m surprised by the stability. I’m building again—products, content, momentum. The wound from the monsoon disaster remains, but it’s fading, replaced by a story of resilience and renewal.</p>
<p><strong>Overall rating: 4.5/5.</strong> For a refurbished warrior and a rekindled creator’s journey.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>technology</category>
            <category>refurbished-laptops</category>
            <category>personal-story</category>
            <category>monsoon</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Baby on Board, Firewalls Up: A New Dad’s Guide to Internet Hygiene at Home]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[How to baby-proof your home network and devices for your child’s safety. A nerdy dad’s guide to computer networks, digital discipline, and practical security.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="A dad and child using a laptop, symbolizing safe computer networks at home." src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/dad-child-internet-a76b989daf6aa0f315fec8f4638d36fa.png" title="A dad and child using a laptop, symbolizing safe computer networks at home." width="1536" height="1024" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Expecting a baby? You’ve probably baby-proofed your furniture, but what about your Wi-Fi and devices? In today’s world, computer networks are as important as cribs and car seats. Here’s how I—a nerdy new dad—secured my digital den for my family’s safety and sanity.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="step-1-understand-your-home-network-like-a-responsible-adult">Step 1: Understand Your Home Network Like a Responsible Adult<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#step-1-understand-your-home-network-like-a-responsible-adult" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 1: Understand Your Home Network Like a Responsible Adult" title="Direct link to Step 1: Understand Your Home Network Like a Responsible Adult" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Most homes today have more than one way to get online, even if you don’t realize it. <strong>Computer networks</strong> are everywhere—broadband, mobile data, and hotspots.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="count-the-networks">Count the Networks<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#count-the-networks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Count the Networks" title="Direct link to Count the Networks" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Total Networks at home =</strong> 1 broadband + each phone with an active mobile data plan</p>
<p>That means your child’s screen time could sneak in through any of these entry points. First step: identify and isolate them.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="basic-network-topology-before-changes">Basic Network Topology (Before Changes)<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#basic-network-topology-before-changes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Basic Network Topology (Before Changes)" title="Direct link to Basic Network Topology (Before Changes)" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Internet → ISP Router (Wi-Fi &amp; LAN) → All Devices → your child</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This gives the ISP’s router full control over DNS, firewall rules, and device access. Not ideal for a security-conscious parent.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Smart phones + data packs → your child</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Data packs by carrier don’t give any parental control tools.</p>
<p>We need to target the network-level filtering, which is generally good enough to block ads, parked domains, and time wasters.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="step-2-fix-the-manhole--lock-down-your-broadband">Step 2: Fix the Manhole — Lock Down Your Broadband<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#step-2-fix-the-manhole--lock-down-your-broadband" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 2: Fix the Manhole — Lock Down Your Broadband" title="Direct link to Step 2: Fix the Manhole — Lock Down Your Broadband" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="why-isp-routers-are-a-problem">Why ISP Routers Are a Problem<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#why-isp-routers-are-a-problem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why ISP Routers Are a Problem" title="Direct link to Why ISP Routers Are a Problem" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Most ISP routers are locked down—DNS settings greyed out</li>
<li class="">Firmware is often outdated and insecure</li>
<li class="">Limited or no parental control features</li>
<li class="">No custom firewall or VLAN options</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="what-i-did-instead">What I Did Instead<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#what-i-did-instead" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I Did Instead" title="Direct link to What I Did Instead" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li class=""><strong>Disabled Wi-Fi on the ISP router</strong><br>
<!-- -->Let it act as a basic modem or Layer 2 switch.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Introduced My Own Router (Netgear)</strong><br>
<!-- -->Plugged into the ISP box via Ethernet (LAN to WAN). This separates my internal LAN from the ISP’s network.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Enabled NAT, DHCP, and DNS on My Router</strong><br>
<!-- -->Configured to issue private IPs (e.g., <code>192.168.1.x</code>) and point all DNS queries to <strong>OpenDNS</strong> servers:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li class=""><code>208.67.222.222</code></li>
<li class=""><code>208.67.220.220</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class=""><strong>Registered with OpenDNS</strong><br>
<!-- -->Created a free account, added my dynamic IP, and enabled category-level filtering. You can block:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li class="">Social networks</li>
<li class="">Video sharing</li>
<li class="">Adult content</li>
<li class="">Gaming, shopping, forums—up to you</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class=""><strong>Tested the Setup</strong><br>
<!-- -->Verified DNS override by visiting:<br>
<a href="https://welcome.opendns.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">https://welcome.opendns.com</a></li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="updated-network-topology">Updated Network Topology<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#updated-network-topology" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Updated Network Topology" title="Direct link to Updated Network Topology" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>All devices now talk to the internet via <strong>my firewall + DNS filters</strong>, not the ISP’s.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="step-3-taming-the-phonesespecially-the-ones-with-data-packs">Step 3: Taming the Phones—Especially the Ones With Data Packs<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#step-3-taming-the-phonesespecially-the-ones-with-data-packs" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 3: Taming the Phones—Especially the Ones With Data Packs" title="Direct link to Step 3: Taming the Phones—Especially the Ones With Data Packs" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Broadband is fixed, but what about <strong>mobile data</strong> on phones? These are the real backdoors in your computer networks.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="simple-but-effective-plan">Simple But Effective Plan<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#simple-but-effective-plan" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Simple But Effective Plan" title="Direct link to Simple But Effective Plan" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Recharge only when needed (no monthly auto-renewal of data-heavy packs)</li>
<li class="">Use mobile data only for OTPs, emergency maps, and short bursts</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-engineers-setup">The Engineer’s Setup<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#the-engineers-setup" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Engineer’s Setup" title="Direct link to The Engineer’s Setup" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>I needed something <strong>robust and centrally managed</strong>.</p>
<ol>
<li class=""><strong>For Broadband Devices</strong> – I use <strong>OpenDNS</strong> via the router.</li>
<li class=""><strong>For Mobile Data (4G/5G) Devices</strong> – I use <strong>NextDNS</strong> via Android/iPhone’s Private DNS feature.</li>
</ol>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="why-nextdns">Why NextDNS?<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#why-nextdns" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why NextDNS?" title="Direct link to Why NextDNS?" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<ul>
<li class="">Supports DNS-over-TLS (DoT) and DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH)</li>
<li class="">Per-device logs, analytics, and block rules</li>
<li class="">Works even over mobile data, friends’ hotspot</li>
<li class="">One profile can be shared across multiple devices</li>
<li class="">For entire family, basic plan is worth it. Free plan is limited.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="how-to-set-it-up-on-android">How to Set It Up on Android<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#how-to-set-it-up-on-android" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How to Set It Up on Android" title="Direct link to How to Set It Up on Android" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Go to: <code>Settings &gt; Network &amp; Internet &gt; Private DNS</code></li>
<li class="">Choose: <code>Private DNS provider hostname</code></li>
<li class="">Enter: <code>your-profile-id.dns.nextdns.io</code> (from nextdns.io dashboard)</li>
<li class="">Save and test at: <a href="https://test.nextdns.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">https://test.nextdns.io</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Now even on 4G, your DNS traffic is encrypted and filtered.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-bigger-motive-family-wide-digital-discipline">The Bigger Motive: Family-Wide Digital Discipline<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#the-bigger-motive-family-wide-digital-discipline" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Bigger Motive: Family-Wide Digital Discipline" title="Direct link to The Bigger Motive: Family-Wide Digital Discipline" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>This isn’t just about protecting a newborn. It’s about reprogramming how <strong>we</strong> use computer networks and the internet—so that the baby doesn’t see everyone glued to screens 24/7.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="what-were-trying-to-do">What We’re Trying to Do<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#what-were-trying-to-do" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What We’re Trying to Do" title="Direct link to What We’re Trying to Do" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Remove addictive triggers from devices</li>
<li class="">Encourage meaningful use of tech</li>
<li class="">Create consistency across screens</li>
<li class="">Lead by example</li>
</ul>
<p>This is not a one-man battle. It’s a full-stack family-level architecture decision.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="problems-faced">Problems Faced<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#problems-faced" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Problems Faced" title="Direct link to Problems Faced" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="technical">Technical<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#technical" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Technical" title="Direct link to Technical" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Changing DNS is straightforward if you’re used to router admin pages.</li>
<li class="">Most modern routers support this out of the box.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="psychological">Psychological<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#psychological" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Psychological" title="Direct link to Psychological" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Asking aging parents to give up binge-watching YouTube is like asking them to skip tea.</li>
<li class="">You’ll hear:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li class="">“What’s wrong with watching one or two reels?”</li>
<li class="">“It’s just a recipe video...?”</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">Prepare for mini mutinies, emotional blackmail, and silent resistance.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="financial">Financial<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#financial" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Financial" title="Direct link to Financial" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Another subscription added, hopefully Netflix &amp; Prime go away</li>
</ul>
<p>But if you stick to it, it gets easier.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="advanced-nerd-notes">Advanced Nerd Notes<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#advanced-nerd-notes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Advanced Nerd Notes" title="Direct link to Advanced Nerd Notes" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>DNS Leak Protection</strong>: Use firewall rules to block outbound port 53 and redirect to OpenDNS.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Split VLANs</strong>: For homes with smart TVs and IoT devices, separate them into guest VLANs.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Device MAC Tracking</strong>: Some routers let you assign policies per MAC address (for kids vs adults).</li>
<li class=""><strong>Dynamic DNS</strong>: If your IP changes often, configure DDNS and bind it to OpenDNS/NextDNS updates.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Logs &amp; Analytics</strong>: Use Pi-hole or Netflow on a Raspberry Pi to monitor domain requests for forensic insights.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="disclaimer">Disclaimer<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#disclaimer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Disclaimer" title="Direct link to Disclaimer" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>I’m not selling any tool here. This blog is about the <strong>mindset shift</strong> required to raise children in the age of digital dopamine.</p>
<p>Use any tool you prefer. The idea is to build a <strong>secure, distraction-minimal environment</strong> where children grow up watching their parents being intentional—not just entertained.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="final-words-from-a-nerdy-new-dad">Final Words from a Nerdy New Dad<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/preparing-home-network-before-first-child#final-words-from-a-nerdy-new-dad" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Final Words from a Nerdy New Dad" title="Direct link to Final Words from a Nerdy New Dad" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Failing to plan is planning to fail. We’ve baby-proofed our furniture. Now let’s baby-proof our Wi-Fi and computer networks.</p>
<p>Because the real "parental control" isn’t in a router setting—it’s the decision to take control in the first place. What are your strategies? Did you deny lending your phone? Share your tips below!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>children</category>
            <category>computer-networks</category>
            <category>internet-safety</category>
            <category>parenting</category>
            <category>home-network</category>
            <category>security</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Trifles You’ll Spot in Every Tech Team Even In The Age of AI]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/common-it-industry-triffles</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/common-it-industry-triffles</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 15:30:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Break your writer’s slump with this cheeky take on the classic struggles within tech teams – from the senior-junior conundrum and cost-cutting debates to the never-ending outsourcing squeeze. If you’ve been in tech for even a minute, you’ll relate.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes you just need to break the writer’s slump, and what better way than to air some tech community laundry/gossips. Here are <strong>3 classic struggles</strong> that keep popping up, no matter how fast the AI world moves.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/senior-junior-51f87aea32a9ab85308c84886b9621b6.webp" width="1024" height="1024" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-senior-vs-junior-conundrum--the-banyan-tree-effect"><strong>1. Senior vs. Junior Conundrum – The Banyan Tree Effect</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/common-it-industry-triffles#1-senior-vs-junior-conundrum--the-banyan-tree-effect" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1-senior-vs-junior-conundrum--the-banyan-tree-effect" title="Direct link to 1-senior-vs-junior-conundrum--the-banyan-tree-effect" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Juniors often feel like they’re <strong>growing in the shadow</strong> of their seniors – those <strong>strong, wide-spread banyan trees</strong> that <strong>block opportunities</strong> and stunt their growth. This isn’t just a theory – data shows that <strong>nearly 30% of techies</strong> with <strong>less than 3 years of experience</strong> switch jobs, looking for <strong>more sunlight and fresh air</strong>.</p>
<p>For juniors, the challenge isn’t just the learning curve but <strong>finding their voice</strong> in a team where the seniors have already taken the best seats. It’s like trying to grow a startup in a market dominated by FAANG.</p>
<p>While seniors are busy debating the <strong>best design pattern for a microservice</strong>, juniors are trying to get their <strong>first pull request merged</strong> without being roasted on the code review thread. It’s a constant game of <strong>"How many comments will this PR get before it’s finally approved?"</strong>, <strong>"Will anyone mentor me honestly about all corners of the long career ahead?"</strong>, etc.</p>
<p>Seniors, on the other hand, see juniors as a <strong>potential threat</strong> – the fresh minds who come in armed with <strong>JavaScript, Python, and React</strong> and casually throw around terms like <strong>LLMs</strong>, <strong>prompt engineering</strong>, <strong>hackathons</strong> and <strong>vector databases</strong>. Meanwhile, the seniors are still perfecting the art of <strong>Spring Boot</strong> and <strong>JPA</strong>, occasionally grumbling about how <strong>Java 8</strong> was the last “real” upgrade.</p>
<p>It’s not just about skills – it’s about <strong>mindset</strong>. The seniors have survived <strong>production outages at 3 AM</strong>, managed <strong>political office battles</strong>, and <strong>honestly mentored</strong> a generation of developers who now run startups.</p>
<p>Juniors, on the other hand, are still fresh, living out of <strong>PG rooms</strong>, debugging their code on <strong>15-inch laptops</strong>, and pushing code on a <strong>5G hotspot</strong> while dodging their roommate’s PUBG screams. They may lack experience, but they have the raw <strong>hustle, curiosity, and caffeine tolerance</strong> that seniors often lose along the way.</p>
<p>And if you want a real generational gap, just bring up <strong>Agile vs. Waterfall</strong> in a meeting. The seniors will reminisce about the days when <strong>project plans were thicker than the SRS document</strong>, while the juniors wonder if they should include <strong>Agile Scrum</strong> in their LinkedIn profile.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-employee-vs-management--the-cost-cutting-showdown"><strong>2. Employee vs. Management – The Cost-Cutting Showdown</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/common-it-industry-triffles#2-employee-vs-management--the-cost-cutting-showdown" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2-employee-vs-management--the-cost-cutting-showdown" title="Direct link to 2-employee-vs-management--the-cost-cutting-showdown" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>When it comes to cutting costs, <strong>management</strong> often takes the path of least resistance – <strong>reduce headcount</strong>. Performance, age, location, experience – all fair game when trimming the payroll. This is the <strong>"high-impact, low-cost"</strong> strategy that features in every MBA case study.</p>
<p>From the management perspective, it’s all about <strong>"optimizing the org chart"</strong> and <strong>"maximizing shareholder value"</strong> – fancy phrases that essentially mean <strong>fewer people, more profit</strong>. The logic is simple: cutting the bottom 10% might save the company <strong>millions</strong> without the <strong>PR disaster</strong> of reducing executive perks.</p>
<p>But employees see it differently. To them, the real savings lie in <strong>cutting the fat at the top</strong>. After all, the <strong>CEO earning 100x</strong> the average developer’s salary, <strong>VPs</strong> flying business class, and middle managers enjoying plush perks attending meetings.</p>
<p>And then there’s the <strong>perks debate</strong>. Employees argue that cutting <strong>free food, and fancy offices</strong> in favor of <strong>WFH (Work From Home)</strong> could save millions. After all, those ping-pong tables and <strong>bean bags</strong> aren’t exactly mission-critical. And let’s be real – the only people who truly use the office gym are the same ones who have the time for <strong>marathon LinkedIn posts</strong>.</p>
<p>This is especially stark in India, where <strong>C-level executives</strong> at top tech firms earn <strong>crores per annum</strong>, while a fresh developer might make <strong>7-15 LPA</strong>. The disparity is not just in the paychecks but also in the <strong>power to decide the fate of others</strong>.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-the-outsourcing-squeeze--a-tale-of-two-realities"><strong>3. The Outsourcing Squeeze – A Tale of Two Realities</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/common-it-industry-triffles#3-the-outsourcing-squeeze--a-tale-of-two-realities" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3-the-outsourcing-squeeze--a-tale-of-two-realities" title="Direct link to 3-the-outsourcing-squeeze--a-tale-of-two-realities" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Outsourcing is a simple idea – move work to a cheaper location and <strong>save big</strong>. India, with its massive pool of <strong>highly skilled engineers</strong>, is a top destination for this. In 2024 alone, India’s <strong>IT exports</strong> were estimated at over <strong>$250 billion</strong>, with <strong>GCCs (Global Capability Centers)</strong> in Bangalore, Hyderabad, and Chennai leading the charge.</p>
<p>But this efficiency comes with a human cost. For every American worker laid off, there’s likely a replacement in Bangalore, Manila, or Chengdu doing the same work at a fraction of the cost. It’s the <strong>"rob Peter to pay Paul"</strong> strategy of the corporate world.</p>
<p>But it’s not a bed of roses for the outsourcers either. They’re often stuck in <strong>corporate jungles</strong> – the GCCs of India – doing the same work for <strong>3x-5x less pay</strong> than their Western counterparts, with fewer perks, <strong>less vacation</strong>, and the constant <strong>contract renewal threats</strong>.</p>
<p>And to add to their woes, the <strong>entry-level salaries</strong> at these GCCs have barely moved in the past <strong>15 years</strong>, despite inflation and the rising cost of living. It’s like getting a <strong>static variable</strong> in a <strong>dynamic world</strong>.</p>
<p>Plus, they have to <strong>sync up at 11 PM</strong> for calls with <strong>PST</strong> time zone clients who think that <strong>IST</strong> stands for <strong>"I’ll Slack Tomorrow."</strong></p>
<hr>
<p>This post is a simple <strong>rant for the slump</strong> – not to be taken seriously. There are many more battles in tech, like <strong>open source vs. closed source</strong>, <strong>cloud vs. on-prem</strong>, and <strong>Windows vs. Mac</strong>. I’ll tackle those when the next writer’s block hits. 😉</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>work-life</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bridging the Gap: CAP Theorem for Senior React Developers]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 15:30:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Learn CAP Theorem using Git and real-time React apps. A must-read bridge post for frontend engineers to understand distributed systems like software architects.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/cap-theorom-git-explained-ff26ca84a5fc10ba511287079503c346.webp" width="1024" height="1024" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p><strong>Why this post?</strong> As frontend engineers, we often focus narrowly on frameworks and tooling—primarily JavaScript, React, and UI libraries. But many of us hit a career plateau because we lack exposure to core software engineering principles.</p>
<p>This post is part of a growing genre I call <strong>“Bridge Posts”</strong>—connecting frontend development to foundational software architecture concepts. The goal is to help frontend engineers think like system designers, not just component builders.</p>
<p>Today, we explore the <strong>CAP Theorem</strong>, a classic principle in distributed systems, and map it to familiar frontend scenarios—such as Git workflows, real-time collaborative UIs, and offline-friendly apps.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="understanding-the-cap-theorem">Understanding the CAP Theorem<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#understanding-the-cap-theorem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understanding the CAP Theorem" title="Direct link to Understanding the CAP Theorem" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>In distributed systems, the <strong>CAP Theorem</strong> states that during a network partition (i.e., some parts of the system can’t communicate), you can only guarantee <strong>two of the following three</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Consistency (C):</strong> All nodes see the same data at the same time.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Availability (A):</strong> Every request receives a response—regardless of the freshness of the data.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Partition Tolerance (P):</strong> The system continues to operate even when parts of it can’t communicate.</li>
</ul>
<p>In practice, <strong>partition tolerance</strong> is non-negotiable in any distributed system. Therefore, systems must choose between consistency and availability when partitions occur.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="git-analogy-you-already-use-cap">Git Analogy: You Already Use CAP<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#git-analogy-you-already-use-cap" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Git Analogy: You Already Use CAP" title="Direct link to Git Analogy: You Already Use CAP" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Let’s start with Git—a tool every developer knows.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">When you commit locally on a plane, you’re in a <strong>partitioned state</strong>.</li>
<li class="">You can continue working (<strong>Availability</strong>), even though your code may diverge from your teammate’s (<strong>Consistency</strong> is compromised).</li>
<li class="">Once reconnected, you <strong>merge</strong> changes to restore consistency.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Git is an AP (Available + Partition-Tolerant) system</strong>. It tolerates partitions and lets you work offline but eventually requires reconciliation.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="react-use-case-real-time-collaborative-forms">React Use Case: Real-Time Collaborative Forms<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#react-use-case-real-time-collaborative-forms" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to React Use Case: Real-Time Collaborative Forms" title="Direct link to React Use Case: Real-Time Collaborative Forms" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Now imagine you’re building a collaborative form in React. Multiple users edit the same form in real-time. Updates are synchronized via WebSockets or polling.</p>
<p>How does CAP play out here?</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-cp--consistent--partition-tolerant">1. <strong>CP – Consistent &amp; Partition-Tolerant</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#1-cp--consistent--partition-tolerant" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1-cp--consistent--partition-tolerant" title="Direct link to 1-cp--consistent--partition-tolerant" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">If a user loses network connectivity, editing is disabled.</li>
<li class="">This ensures everyone always sees the latest state.</li>
<li class="">However, the application becomes unavailable for offline or disconnected users.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Use cases:</strong> Healthcare apps, finance platforms—where data integrity is paramount.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-ap--available--partition-tolerant">2. <strong>AP – Available &amp; Partition-Tolerant</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#2-ap--available--partition-tolerant" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2-ap--available--partition-tolerant" title="Direct link to 2-ap--available--partition-tolerant" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Users can continue editing offline.</li>
<li class="">Changes are stored locally and synced later.</li>
<li class="">This may lead to <strong>conflicting edits</strong>, requiring merge strategies.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Use cases:</strong> Note-taking apps, chat applications—where user flow matters more than perfect sync.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-ca--consistent--available-no-partition-tolerance">3. <strong>CA – Consistent &amp; Available (No Partition Tolerance)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#3-ca--consistent--available-no-partition-tolerance" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3-ca--consistent--available-no-partition-tolerance" title="Direct link to 3-ca--consistent--available-no-partition-tolerance" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Works as expected under perfect network conditions.</li>
<li class="">Any partition causes the system to fail or block.</li>
<li class="">While theoretically ideal, <strong>this model is impractical in real-world distributed systems</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-designing-for-partition-tolerance">🌐 Designing for Partition Tolerance<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#-designing-for-partition-tolerance" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🌐 Designing for Partition Tolerance" title="Direct link to 🌐 Designing for Partition Tolerance" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>A <strong>network partition</strong> occurs when different components of a distributed system—clients, services, or databases—cannot communicate due to a temporary network failure. Each component may still be operational, but they're isolated like islands without bridges.</p>
<p>In frontend development, this is surprisingly common:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">A user loses internet connectivity mid-session.</li>
<li class="">A mobile app hits a dead spot with no signal.</li>
<li class="">The frontend can reach a CDN or cache but not the main API server.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Designing for Partition Tolerance</strong> means your app should continue functioning as gracefully as possible, even during such disconnects.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="as-a-react-developer-this-involves">As a React developer, this involves:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#as-a-react-developer-this-involves" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to As a React developer, this involves:" title="Direct link to As a React developer, this involves:" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<ul>
<li class="">Storing user actions locally (memory, localStorage, IndexedDB).</li>
<li class="">Queuing mutations and syncing later (e.g., Service Workers, Apollo cache, Redux middleware).</li>
<li class="">Providing clear UI cues: “You’re offline, changes will sync later.”</li>
<li class="">Implementing conflict resolution logic, if needed.</li>
</ul>
<p>Real-world examples:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Figma</strong> continues rendering and recording user edits during disconnects.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Notion</strong> lets you type offline and syncs the block tree later.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Gmail</strong> stores draft emails offline and sends them once reconnected.</li>
</ul>
<p>These applications <strong>opt for Partition Tolerance</strong>, ensuring the app remains usable—even if consistency is delayed or temporarily broken.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Designing for Partition Tolerance doesn’t mean ignoring consistency—it means accepting that consistency might be <em>eventual</em>, not immediate.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In distributed systems, <strong>network failures are not rare edge cases—they're expected events.</strong> As frontend engineers, acknowledging and designing for them elevates your thinking from component trees to system-level resilience.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="mapping-cap-to-frontend-patterns">Mapping CAP to Frontend Patterns<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#mapping-cap-to-frontend-patterns" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Mapping CAP to Frontend Patterns" title="Direct link to Mapping CAP to Frontend Patterns" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<table><thead><tr><th>Frontend Pattern</th><th>CAP Tradeoff</th><th>Notes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>React Query (stale-while-revalidate)</td><td>AP</td><td>Shows stale cache first, fetches fresh data.</td></tr><tr><td>Optimistic UI (e.g., message send)</td><td>AP</td><td>Assumes success and syncs with the server later.</td></tr><tr><td>Disabling forms on lost connection</td><td>CP</td><td>Prevents stale writes by enforcing consistency.</td></tr><tr><td>Service Workers / Offline-First PWA</td><td>AP</td><td>Operates offline and reconciles post-reconnect.</td></tr><tr><td>Live collaboration (e.g., Figma, Google Docs)</td><td>AP + conflict resolution</td><td>Resolves sync issues with operational transforms.</td></tr></tbody></table>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="what-this-means-for-frontend-developers">What This Means for Frontend Developers<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#what-this-means-for-frontend-developers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What This Means for Frontend Developers" title="Direct link to What This Means for Frontend Developers" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>You don’t have to be building a distributed database to care about CAP. If your application:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Caches remote data</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Lets users work offline</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Supports multi-user collaboration</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Relies on eventual consistency</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>…then you’re actively navigating CAP trade-offs.</p>
<p>Ask yourself:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Can users work with stale data? → Choose <strong>Availability</strong>.</li>
<li class="">Must every write be accurate and conflict-free? → Prioritize <strong>Consistency</strong>.</li>
<li class="">Should the app always respond—even during outages? → Design for <strong>Partition Tolerance</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="closing-thoughts-frontend-as-a-distributed-system">Closing Thoughts: Frontend as a Distributed System<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/explaining-cap-dvcs-multi-user-for-frontends#closing-thoughts-frontend-as-a-distributed-system" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Closing Thoughts: Frontend as a Distributed System" title="Direct link to Closing Thoughts: Frontend as a Distributed System" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>“CAP isn’t just a backend concern—it manifests in every interactive, networked UI you build.”</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Whether you’re building a rich client with React Query, crafting optimistic updates, or designing for offline-first usage, you’re constantly making trade-offs. Understanding CAP helps you make them consciously.</p>
<p>This post was part of a broader mission to elevate frontend engineers into system thinkers—developers who don’t just build buttons, but design resilient user experiences.</p>
<p>Let’s not be cookie-cutter React developers. Let’s bridge the gap.</p>
<hr>
<p>Would you like me to help you turn this into a blog-ready Markdown + SEO-friendly format?</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>frontend</category>
            <category>bridge-posts</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Back to stage, My Comeback to Toastmasters and First Visit to Hosur Toastmasters Club]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 15:30:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Discover the Hosur Toastmasters Club through the eyes of a seasoned Toastmaster! In this blog, dhbalaji shares his comeback experience, key takeaways, meeting highlights, and why joining Toastmasters in Hosur is a smart move for personal and professional growth. Perfect for public speaking enthusiasts, professionals, and new members in Tamil Nadu.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What happens when a <strong>frontend architect meets a podium</strong> after years? You get a mix of <code>console.log("confidence")</code> and some seriously good speeches.</p>
<p>I'm <strong>dhbalaji</strong> — Lead Frontend Engineer by day, Toastmaster since 2012, and collector of certificates like <a class="" href="https://dhbalaji.dev/docs/certifications/toastmasters/acb"><strong>CC</strong>, <strong>CL</strong>, and <strong>ACB</strong></a>. After taking a break to focus to master sorcerous Javascript. But when I heard there’s a <strong>Toastmasters Club right here in Hosur</strong>, my curiosity wanted me to do a little mic check.</p>
<p>So I walked in. Here's what happened.</p>
<hr>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Hosur Toastmasters Meeting Invite" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/hosur-toastmasters-meeting-invite-1683e41acdd8e0b577aa37f54996d209.jpg" width="853" height="1280" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-where-it-happened">📍 Where It Happened<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-where-it-happened" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 📍 Where It Happened" title="Direct link to 📍 Where It Happened" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>When:</strong> Every <strong>Sunday</strong>, 10:00 AM – 11:30 AM</li>
<li class=""><strong>Where:</strong> 2nd Floor, Finance Academy, <strong>ASTC HUDCO</strong>, Hosur</li>
<li class=""><strong>Parking:</strong> Loads of space — park like a boss</li>
<li class=""><strong>Setup:</strong> Cosy room with a ~30 person capacity</li>
<li class=""><strong>Hybrid Mode:</strong> Online guests can join via Microsoft Teams</li>
</ul>
<p>🗺️ <em>If you're Googling "Toastmasters club near me in Hosur" — this is it!</em> <a href="https://toastmasters.org/Find-a-Club/07757477-hosur-toastmasters-club" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Hosur Toastmasters club permalink</a></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-first-impressions">👀 First Impressions<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-first-impressions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👀 First Impressions" title="Direct link to 👀 First Impressions" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Having attended clubs with bells, whistles, and near-TED levels of polish, <strong>Hosur Toastmasters</strong> felt refreshingly raw. Think: garage band with talent, waiting to hit Spotify.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-what-worked">✅ What Worked:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-what-worked" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ✅ What Worked:" title="Direct link to ✅ What Worked:" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Diverse Professionals:</strong> Engineers, finance folks, HR pros — all under one roof</li>
<li class=""><strong>Mature Audience:</strong> 30s+ crowd added depth and real-life stories</li>
<li class=""><strong>Warm Vibes:</strong> Received a formal invite ahead of time (yay structure!)</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="️-what-could-be-better">⚠️ What Could Be Better:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#%EF%B8%8F-what-could-be-better" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ⚠️ What Could Be Better:" title="Direct link to ⚠️ What Could Be Better:" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Sunday morning?</strong> Great for early birds, rough for Netflix-bingers</li>
<li class=""><strong>Limited networking:</strong> Hybrid format made hallway chats tough</li>
<li class=""><strong>Retention Blues:</strong> Noticed some churn — fresh energy needed</li>
</ul>
<p>The session I attended was a <strong>joint meeting with Proficient Toastmasters Club</strong>, with quite a few tuning in online. Felt like an office teams meeting — but with better grammar.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-meeting-highlights">🌟 Meeting Highlights<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-meeting-highlights" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🌟 Meeting Highlights" title="Direct link to 🌟 Meeting Highlights" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>I won’t pretend I was the General Evaluator, but here’s what stuck with me:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Theme:</strong> <em>“Voices of Nature”</em> — poetic, calming, not a weather report</li>
<li class=""><strong>Word of the Day:</strong> “<strong>Cacophony</strong>” — ironically, the meeting room fan was anything <em>but</em></li>
<li class=""><strong>Prepared Speeches:</strong> Delivered with confidence — definitely mentor material</li>
<li class=""><strong>Table Topics:</strong> Real-time adrenaline for guests. I spoke. I survived.</li>
<li class=""><strong>TAG Team:</strong> Tracked <strong>Time</strong>, <strong>Ah-counter</strong>, and <strong>Grammar</strong> like ninjas with excel sheets, yes someone ended up sharing screen on teams</li>
<li class=""><strong>Evaluations &amp; Awards:</strong> Encouragement with a touch of pageantry and photos</li>
<li class=""><strong>Post-Meeting Chats:</strong> Surprisingly rich — could have been better</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-what-could-level-up-the-experience">🤔 What Could Level-Up the Experience<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-what-could-level-up-the-experience" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🤔 What Could Level-Up the Experience" title="Direct link to 🤔 What Could Level-Up the Experience" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Here’s my candid guest audit (no PowerPoint, promise):</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Introduce guests early — helps with context and connection</li>
<li class="">Bigger in-person crowd = more energy</li>
<li class="">Meeting decorum — a little polish goes a long way</li>
<li class="">Tighter meeting flow — less lag between segments</li>
<li class=""><strong>Record &amp; upload speeches</strong> — boost visibility and speaker growth</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-people-who-inspired-me">💬 People Who Inspired Me<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-people-who-inspired-me" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 💬 People Who Inspired Me" title="Direct link to 💬 People Who Inspired Me" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>This was the deal-sealer.</p>
<p>Where else do <strong>frontend developers, sales pros, finance strategists, and HR veterans</strong> talk about communication, confidence, and community — all in the same room?</p>
<p>Special shoutout to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/muthuk-kalimuthu" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class=""><strong>TM Muthu Kalimuthu</strong></a>, the Club President. His hospitality and thoughtful questions before the meeting made me feel like I was already part of the team.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-takeaways-from-hosur-toastmasters-club">🧠 Takeaways from Hosur Toastmasters Club<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-takeaways-from-hosur-toastmasters-club" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🧠 Takeaways from Hosur Toastmasters Club" title="Direct link to 🧠 Takeaways from Hosur Toastmasters Club" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class="">Hosur isn’t just about factories anymore. We’ve got <strong>IIT training centres, shopping malls... and now, Toastmasters.</strong></li>
<li class="">The club may not be in full bloom yet, but the seeds are solid. Leadership can make it shine.</li>
<li class="">English fluency can be a barrier in this region — <strong>this club is a bridge</strong>, not just a stage.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-should-you-join-hosur-toastmasters">👍 Should You Join Hosur Toastmasters?<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-should-you-join-hosur-toastmasters" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 👍 Should You Join Hosur Toastmasters?" title="Direct link to 👍 Should You Join Hosur Toastmasters?" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Yes, yes, a thousand times yes — especially if you:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Want to improve your <strong>public speaking and leadership skills</strong></li>
<li class="">Are looking for <strong>community engagement in Hosur</strong></li>
<li class="">Enjoy learning from people outside your industry bubble</li>
</ul>
<p>Here’s how I imagine the club’s golden mix:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>33%</strong> – Students and early-career folks</li>
<li class=""><strong>33%</strong> – Regulars actively participating and giving speeches</li>
<li class=""><strong>33%</strong> – Mentors and seasoned Toastmasters offering wisdom from the backbenches</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-fun-goof-of-the-day">😆 Fun Goof of the Day<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-fun-goof-of-the-day" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 😆 Fun Goof of the Day" title="Direct link to 😆 Fun Goof of the Day" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Speaker (with full confidence): “And then I heard the <strong>birds slurping</strong>...” instead of "<strong>birds chirrping</strong>"</p>
<p>Audience: <em>blink blink</em>
Grammarian: Noted</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-final-thoughts">💬 Final Thoughts<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/hosur-toastmasters-journey-to-confidence-starts-here#-final-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 💬 Final Thoughts" title="Direct link to 💬 Final Thoughts" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>I didn’t just walk into a meeting. I walked into <strong>a reboot</strong>.</p>
<p>So if you’re searching for:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">“<strong>Hosur Toastmasters Club timings</strong>”</li>
<li class="">“<strong>Toastmasters near ASTC HUDCO</strong>”</li>
<li class="">“<strong>How to improve public speaking in Hosur</strong>”</li>
</ul>
<p>You’ve found your place.</p>
<p>🎤 Come for the speeches. Stay for the people. Rediscover your voice.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>toastmasters</category>
            <category>public-speaking</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Understanding How LLMs Work with a Doctor's Clinic Analogy]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 15:30:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Break down the inner workings of Large Language Models (LLMs) using an easy-to-follow analogy of a doctor's clinic. Learn about tokenization, embeddings, transformer architecture, and more.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/doctor-patient-ai-illustration-01ba81e9b1cfc24251a3212175a35e3d.webp" width="1000" height="666" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Large Language Models (LLMs) are revolutionizing the way we build intelligent applications—especially in frontend development. From ChatGPT to custom AI copilots, LLMs are everywhere. But have you ever wondered <strong>how LLMs actually work</strong> under the hood?</p>
<p>The theory behind LLMs can be complex—terms like <em>embeddings</em>, <em>transformers</em>, <em>tokenization</em>, and <em>vector space</em> often feel overwhelming. That’s why I’m using a familiar analogy: a visit to a <strong>local doctor’s clinic</strong>.</p>
<p>This blog post breaks down <strong>the internal architecture of LLMs</strong> using a real-world story that’s easy to visualize and remember. Whether you're a developer exploring AI integration, an engineer curious about embeddings, or someone building chat interfaces, this analogy-driven explanation will help you understand:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">What tokenization really means</li>
<li class="">Why vectors and embeddings are essential</li>
<li class="">How transformers "think" using attention</li>
<li class="">Why temperature affects LLM creativity</li>
<li class="">How memory and context shape outputs</li>
</ul>
<p>Let’s walk into the clinic. 🚶‍♂️💊</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="characters-in-the-community-clinic-example">Characters in the Community Clinic Example<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#characters-in-the-community-clinic-example" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Characters in the Community Clinic Example" title="Direct link to Characters in the Community Clinic Example" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>User</strong> – A person interacting with the LLM (the patient)</li>
<li class=""><strong>LLM</strong> – The large language model (the doctor)</li>
<li class=""><strong>Internals</strong> – Sequence of steps the model uses to generate a response (diagnostic workflow)</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="step-1-patient-describes-the-issue-to-doctor">Step 1: Patient Describes the Issue to Doctor<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#step-1-patient-describes-the-issue-to-doctor" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 1: Patient Describes the Issue to Doctor" title="Direct link to Step 1: Patient Describes the Issue to Doctor" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Scene:</strong><br>
<!-- -->The patient walks into the clinic.</p>
<p><strong>Conversation:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Doctor: Hi, please sit down.</li>
<li class="">Patient: Thank you.</li>
<li class="">Doctor: Tell me.</li>
<li class="">Patient: I got back from my friend’s wedding 2 days back. Since yesterday, I feel cold and have body pains.</li>
<li class="">Doctor: (listening) hmm.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>LLM Analogy:</strong><br>
<!-- -->This step is like <strong>tokenization</strong> — breaking the input sentence into smaller units (tokens) that the machine can understand.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Step 1 - Tokenizer:</strong><br>
<!-- -->Converts input from human language to machine-readable tokens.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Input:</strong> Plain text / story</li>
<li class=""><strong>Output:</strong> Word tokens (e.g., "wedding", "cold", "pains")</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="step-2-doctor-comprehends-the-patient-problem">Step 2: Doctor Comprehends the Patient Problem<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#step-2-doctor-comprehends-the-patient-problem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 2: Doctor Comprehends the Patient Problem" title="Direct link to Step 2: Doctor Comprehends the Patient Problem" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The doctor interprets the patient’s words and thinks in terms of temperature, symptoms, etc. They may even order diagnostic tests for more data.</p>
<p><strong>LLM Analogy:</strong><br>
<!-- -->This is like the <strong>embedding layer</strong>, where word tokens are turned into number arrays (vectors) that hold semantic meaning.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Step 2 - Embedding Layer:</strong><br>
<!-- -->Converts tokens into vector form for semantic understanding.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Input:</strong> Word tokens</li>
<li class=""><strong>Output:</strong> Vectors that represent meaning (like symptoms turned into medical data)</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="step-3-doctor-runs-diagnosis-internally">Step 3: Doctor Runs Diagnosis Internally<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#step-3-doctor-runs-diagnosis-internally" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 3: Doctor Runs Diagnosis Internally" title="Direct link to Step 3: Doctor Runs Diagnosis Internally" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The doctor thinks through the problem using experience and logic—checking symptoms against patterns they’ve seen before.</p>
<p><strong>LLM Analogy:</strong><br>
<!-- -->This is the <strong>transformer architecture</strong>—especially self-attention layers, which compare words across the sentence to extract meaning and decide what matters most.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Step 3 - Transformer Layers:</strong><br>
<!-- -->Deep learning steps like self-attention and feedforward networks.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Input:</strong> Vectors</li>
<li class=""><strong>Output:</strong> Context-aware vectors based on internal learned patterns</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="step-4-doctor-considers-constraints-like-budget">Step 4: Doctor Considers Constraints (like budget)<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#step-4-doctor-considers-constraints-like-budget" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 4: Doctor Considers Constraints (like budget)" title="Direct link to Step 4: Doctor Considers Constraints (like budget)" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Doctors don’t always prescribe expensive tests—patient affordability, practicality, and history all affect decisions.</p>
<p><strong>LLM Analogy:</strong><br>
<!-- -->This step is like <strong>positional encoding</strong>—ensuring the model understands the order and structure of the sentence.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Step 4 - Positional Encoding:</strong><br>
<!-- -->Adds position-related meaning to vectors.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Input:</strong> Related vector tokens</li>
<li class=""><strong>Output:</strong> Ordered vector tokens based on sentence position</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="step-5-doctor-writes-a-prescription">Step 5: Doctor Writes a Prescription<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#step-5-doctor-writes-a-prescription" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 5: Doctor Writes a Prescription" title="Direct link to Step 5: Doctor Writes a Prescription" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The doctor now documents the diagnosis and treatment. It’s a direct result of structured thinking and patient input.</p>
<p><strong>LLM Analogy:</strong><br>
<!-- -->This is where the model <strong>decodes</strong> the internal vector into a predicted sequence of tokens.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Step 5 - Decoder:</strong><br>
<!-- -->Generates output tokens based on model’s confidence and logic.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Input:</strong> Positional vectors</li>
<li class=""><strong>Output:</strong> Probable tokens in correct context</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="step-6-doctor-shares-the-prescription-with-the-patient">Step 6: Doctor Shares the Prescription with the Patient<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#step-6-doctor-shares-the-prescription-with-the-patient" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 6: Doctor Shares the Prescription with the Patient" title="Direct link to Step 6: Doctor Shares the Prescription with the Patient" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The final interaction. If the patient is nervous, doctor might tweak the recommendation. This is where human nuance enters.</p>
<p><strong>LLM Analogy:</strong><br>
<!-- -->The LLM now converts tokens back into human-readable words. Here, <strong>temperature</strong> plays a role in how creative or safe the response is.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Step 6 - Output Layer:</strong><br>
<!-- -->Converts final vector into output text based on temperature setting.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Input:</strong> Final vector</li>
<li class=""><strong>Output:</strong> Natural language sentence</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="bonus-step-the-doctor-remembers-your-previous-visit">Bonus Step: The Doctor Remembers Your Previous Visit<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#bonus-step-the-doctor-remembers-your-previous-visit" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bonus Step: The Doctor Remembers Your Previous Visit" title="Direct link to Bonus Step: The Doctor Remembers Your Previous Visit" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>LLMs with <strong>memory or context windows</strong> can remember prior conversations, like a doctor recognizing returning patients. This helps give better, contextual responses in multi-turn dialogues.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="summary">Summary<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#summary" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Summary" title="Direct link to Summary" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Just like a good doctor doesn’t Google your symptoms in front of you, a well-trained LLM doesn’t "think" in real-time. It applies complex math on pre-learned data to predict and autocomplete responses.</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Words → Tokens → Vectors → Patterns → Tokens → Words</strong></li>
<li class="">Everything happens in <strong>vector space</strong>, not in "language" as humans know it.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you’re building with tools like <strong>LangChain</strong>, <strong>OpenAI</strong>, or <strong>embedding-powered RAG applications</strong>, understanding these LLM fundamentals gives you a huge advantage.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>🧠 "A well-trained LLM is just a super-fast autocomplete that has read the entire internet."</p>
</blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="-takeaways-for-developers">✨ Takeaways for Developers<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2025/understanding-llm-with-hospital-example#-takeaways-for-developers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ✨ Takeaways for Developers" title="Direct link to ✨ Takeaways for Developers" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class="">Tokenization = Parsing human input</li>
<li class="">Embedding = Understanding meaning</li>
<li class="">Transformer = Core logic engine / Deep learning</li>
<li class="">Positional Encoding = Sentence structure</li>
<li class="">Decoding = Constructing a response</li>
<li class="">Temperature = Tuning creativity</li>
<li class="">Context = Remembering past interactions</li>
</ul>
<p>LLMs don’t reason like humans—but they recognize patterns with superhuman speed. Now you can too. If you like this story, share it on social media.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>AI-for-frontends</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[5 Things I am Letting Go of in 2025 - Building a Not-To-Do List]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/5-things-not-to-do-in-2025</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/5-things-not-to-do-in-2025</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 13:30:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[As tech enthusiasts, we often talk about to-do lists to stay productive. But have you ever considered the power of a not-to-do list? It's about consciously identifying habits or activities that no longer serve your goals and removing them. Here's my not-to-do list for 2025, crafted with the intent to stay focused, efficient, and aligned with my evolving priorities.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As tech enthusiasts, we often talk about <strong>to-do lists</strong> to stay productive. But have you ever considered the power of a <strong>not-to-do list</strong>? It's about consciously identifying habits or activities that no longer serve your goals and removing them. Here's my not-to-do list for 2025, crafted with the intent to stay focused, efficient, and aligned with my evolving priorities.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-no-more-public-github-repos">1. No More Public GitHub Repos<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/5-things-not-to-do-in-2025#1-no-more-public-github-repos" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. No More Public GitHub Repos" title="Direct link to 1. No More Public GitHub Repos" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Open-source contribution has been a cornerstone of the tech world, and I’ve had my share of excitement from it. But with the rise of AI tools, the landscape is changing. Unless you’re a core maintainer of a prominent library, the recognition that once came from showcasing code has diminished.</p>
<p>In 2025, I’ll shift my energy toward <strong>building meaningful products and functionalities</strong> rather than maintaining a public code showcase. The focus will be on solving problems and creating impact—where the real value lies.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-no-social-media-overload">2. No Social Media Overload<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/5-things-not-to-do-in-2025#2-no-social-media-overload" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. No Social Media Overload" title="Direct link to 2. No Social Media Overload" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Social media can be a double-edged sword. It’s a goldmine for networking, but it’s also a time sink designed for immersion and doomscrolling. With AI tools providing quick insights (even without sitting through a 40-minute video), my reliance on these platforms will be minimal.</p>
<p>Here’s my plan: <strong>Engage with social media just once a week for an hour</strong>, in the following order:</p>
<ol>
<li class=""><strong>Facebook</strong> for personal updates.</li>
<li class=""><strong>LinkedIn</strong> for professional networking.</li>
<li class=""><strong>GitHub Feed</strong> to track industry trends.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Twitter/X</strong> for niche topics and hot takes.</li>
<li class=""><strong>YouTube Subscriptions</strong> for targeted learning.</li>
</ol>
<p>Additionally, I’ll curate a list of websites to stay updated instead of depending on algorithm-driven feeds.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-no-two-visits-per-week-to-office">3. No Two Visits Per Week To Office<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/5-things-not-to-do-in-2025#3-no-two-visits-per-week-to-office" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. No Two Visits Per Week To Office" title="Direct link to 3. No Two Visits Per Week To Office" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Working from the office puts you into a routine which is a supporting stick for those who lack self discipline of waking up early, switching subjects under work naturally. Thats why I am against working from office on select days of the week.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="4-no-more-reading-goals">4. No More Reading Goals<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/5-things-not-to-do-in-2025#4-no-more-reading-goals" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4. No More Reading Goals" title="Direct link to 4. No More Reading Goals" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>I used to pride myself on being a voracious reader, devouring two books a week. But life evolves, and so do habits. For two consecutive years, I failed to hit my reading goals—and that’s okay.</p>
<p>In 2025, I’ll stop setting rigid reading goals. Instead, I’ll use mobile apps that provide <strong>daily book summaries</strong> to stay updated with the latest titles. Physical books will still have a place in my collection, but the pressure to meet arbitrary goals will be a thing of the past.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="5-no-more-video-courses-unless-ive-tried-and-failed">5. No More Video Courses Unless I’ve Tried and Failed<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/5-things-not-to-do-in-2025#5-no-more-video-courses-unless-ive-tried-and-failed" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5. No More Video Courses Unless I’ve Tried and Failed" title="Direct link to 5. No More Video Courses Unless I’ve Tried and Failed" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Video courses are everywhere—just one click away. But they often require hours of commitment, and many simply repackage information available in documentation or books.</p>
<p>Moving forward, I’ll treat video courses as a <strong>last resort</strong>. I’ll prioritize <strong>reading documentation</strong>, <strong>experimenting</strong>, and leveraging AI for quick answers. If I still hit roadblocks, only then will I invest time in a course. The same logic applies to interviews or tutorials—AI can summarize key insights faster than a 60-minute watch.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-overall-theme-build-ship-and-upskill">The Overall Theme: Build, Ship, and Upskill<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/5-things-not-to-do-in-2025#the-overall-theme-build-ship-and-upskill" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Overall Theme: Build, Ship, and Upskill" title="Direct link to The Overall Theme: Build, Ship, and Upskill" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>2025 is about <strong>action over abstraction</strong>. Instead of endlessly documenting best practices or creating small libraries, I’ll focus on:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Building real applications</strong> for my portfolio.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Leveraging AI for 5x upskilling</strong>.</li>
<li class="">Prioritizing <strong>actual product development</strong> over pre/post-work content.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s time to let go of distractions and double down on meaningful work. Here’s to a focused and fulfilling year ahead!</p>
<p>What’s on your <strong>not-to-do list</strong> for 2025? Share in the comments—I’d love to hear your thoughts!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>goals</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Journey of Learning and Growth with Youtube in 2024]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/things-learnt-from-youtube-2024</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/things-learnt-from-youtube-2024</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 13:30:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[YouTube has become an indispensable part of our daily lives. From entertainment to education, it’s a treasure trove of information waiting to be tapped. However, like any tool, its impact depends on how we use it. By channeling our time on YouTube towards productive endeavors, we can unlock immense value. Here are three transformative lessons I’ve learned from YouTube in 2024, which have reshaped my perspective and enriched my life.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/youtube-learning-2024-c9adf410489294cabdcf4ae6168e7d89.webp" width="1024" height="1024" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>YouTube has become an indispensable part of our daily lives. From entertainment to education, it’s a treasure trove of information waiting to be tapped. However, like any tool, its impact depends on how we use it. By channeling our time on YouTube towards productive endeavors, we can unlock immense value. Here are three transformative lessons I’ve learned from YouTube in 2024, which have reshaped my perspective and enriched my life.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-diy-laptop-and-motorcycle-repairs-empower-yourself">1. DIY Laptop and Motorcycle Repairs: Empower Yourself<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/things-learnt-from-youtube-2024#1-diy-laptop-and-motorcycle-repairs-empower-yourself" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. DIY Laptop and Motorcycle Repairs: Empower Yourself" title="Direct link to 1. DIY Laptop and Motorcycle Repairs: Empower Yourself" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Nothing is more frustrating than being technically inclined yet unable to handle minor repairs. For many, minor fixes—whether it’s a laptop issue or a motorcycle—are often overlooked by mechanics or seen as unworthy of their time. Insurance companies don’t cover such small mishaps, and for the owner, they’re just time-wasters. But learning to perform these tasks yourself is a game-changer.</p>
<p>Through YouTube, I’ve gained the confidence to tackle these challenges. DIY repair videos have become my go-to resource before making any major purchases. For instance:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Most business-grade laptops have detailed repair tutorials available.</li>
<li class="">Popular vehicles, like Maruti cars, also have a wealth of content explaining common issues and fixes.</li>
</ul>
<p>This newfound skill has transformed how I make purchase decisions. DIY repairability is now a core factor in my selection framework. The ability to fix things with my own hands not only saves money but also fosters a sense of independence and ownership.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Pro Tip:</strong> Before buying any big or expensive item, check if it is DIY repair-friendly. It can save you a lot of hassle down the line.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-financial-frameworks-for-life-learn-from-real-stories">2. Financial Frameworks for Life: Learn from Real Stories<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/things-learnt-from-youtube-2024#2-financial-frameworks-for-life-learn-from-real-stories" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Financial Frameworks for Life: Learn from Real Stories" title="Direct link to 2. Financial Frameworks for Life: Learn from Real Stories" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Conversations around finance often revolve around trades, insurance, or IPOs, but rarely delve into overarching financial frameworks or strategies for building wealth. Thanks to YouTube, we can now access diverse perspectives and stories from people at different stages of their financial journey.</p>
<p>Just today, I watched two fascinating videos:</p>
<ol>
<li class="">A story about a betting addict burdened by debt—a cautionary tale of financial mismanagement.</li>
<li class="">The inspiring journey of a top-level executive who retired early to live sustainably on a farm. Their financial strategy included years of disciplined saving and investments, supplemented by income from startups. Here’s their asset allocation:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li class="">40% in real estate, including their farm.</li>
<li class="">40% in equities and mutual funds.</li>
<li class="">10% in gold.</li>
<li class="">10% in liquid funds for emergencies.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>These narratives offer invaluable insights and practical frameworks for managing personal finances.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Key Takeaway:</strong> Before you quit your job, ensure you have a solid financial runway. Asset allocation is crucial for long-term stability.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-tech-events-live-stay-ahead-of-the-curve">3. Tech Events Live: Stay Ahead of the Curve<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/things-learnt-from-youtube-2024#3-tech-events-live-stay-ahead-of-the-curve" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Tech Events Live: Stay Ahead of the Curve" title="Direct link to 3. Tech Events Live: Stay Ahead of the Curve" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>For developers and tech enthusiasts, attending global conferences like Next.js Conf or Google I/O often seems like a distant dream. Enter YouTube, the ultimate equalizer. With live streams and recorded sessions, anyone, anywhere, can stay updated on the latest trends and technologies.</p>
<p>This year, I tuned into multiple tech events that would have been impossible to attend in person. These events not only kept me informed but also inspired me to stay ahead in my career. The ability to access these resources at your convenience is a game-changer for lifelong learning.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Actionable Insight:</strong> Don’t miss out on tech trends—attend virtual events and conferences through YouTube.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="summary-guardrails-for-growth">Summary: Guardrails for Growth<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/things-learnt-from-youtube-2024#summary-guardrails-for-growth" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Summary: Guardrails for Growth" title="Direct link to Summary: Guardrails for Growth" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>YouTube is undoubtedly a powerful platform for learning and growth. However, navigating it effectively requires discipline. The abundance of content can quickly lead to doom-scrolling and distractions if we’re not careful. By setting guardrails and focusing on purposeful content, we can turn YouTube into a tool for self-improvement.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/things-learnt-from-youtube-2024#final-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Final Thoughts" title="Direct link to Final Thoughts" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>The key to harnessing YouTube’s potential lies in intentionality. Whether it’s mastering DIY repairs, building financial acumen, or staying updated with industry trends, the platform offers endless opportunities. Use it wisely, and you’ll find yourself growing in ways you never imagined.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>learning</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Warranty claims explained as HTTP Requests, a developer’s analogy]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 13:30:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Warranty claims in India can feel like navigating the internet with a shaky connection. Sometimes you get a swift 200 OK, and other times you're stuck in an endless loop of 408 Request Timeout or redirected to 303 See Other Agency for Warranty. As a tech blogger and frontend developer, I thought it’d be fun to break down this often frustrating yet essential consumer process using HTTP status codes as a metaphor.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/warranty-claim-http-codes-b0fed17c608e2a44a4879e1396a860df.webp" width="1024" height="1024" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Warranty claims in India can feel like navigating the internet with a shaky connection. Sometimes you get a swift <strong>200 OK</strong>, and other times you're stuck in an endless loop of <strong>408 Request Timeout</strong> or redirected to <strong>303 See Other Agency for Warranty</strong>. As a tech blogger and frontend developer, I thought it’d be fun to break down this often frustrating yet essential consumer process using HTTP status codes as a metaphor.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="what-the-heck-is-a-warranty">What the Heck is a Warranty?<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#what-the-heck-is-a-warranty" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What the Heck is a Warranty?" title="Direct link to What the Heck is a Warranty?" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Before diving in, let's understand the basics. Warranty is a form of consumer protection where a company promises to replace or repair a product if it malfunctions within a specified period. Think of it as a service-level agreement between you and the brand, like <strong>12 months of uptime guarantee</strong> for your shiny new "Bonda" mobile charger.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="but-its-not-always-a-200-ok">But It’s Not Always a <strong>200 OK</strong>...<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#but-its-not-always-a-200-ok" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to but-its-not-always-a-200-ok" title="Direct link to but-its-not-always-a-200-ok" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>If companies approved every warranty claim without scrutiny, they'd be out of business. So, they create hurdles to ensure only genuine claims get through. For us consumers, this means our warranty experience can range from seamless to outright bizarre.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-http-status-code-guide-to-warranty-claims">The HTTP Status Code Guide to Warranty Claims<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#the-http-status-code-guide-to-warranty-claims" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The HTTP Status Code Guide to Warranty Claims" title="Direct link to The HTTP Status Code Guide to Warranty Claims" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="200-ok-positive-case"><strong>200 OK</strong>: Positive Case<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#200-ok-positive-case" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 200-ok-positive-case" title="Direct link to 200-ok-positive-case" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>The consumer submits a claim with a valid invoice, and the company processes it smoothly.<br>
<!-- -->For example, my experience with a Transcend pen drive's lifetime warranty was flawless. I handed in the old one at their warehouse and walked out with a replacement. <strong>No drama, just resolution.</strong> I wish every claim was like this!</p>
<hr>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="negative-cases-300-400-and-500-errors"><strong>Negative Cases: 300, 400, and 500 Errors</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#negative-cases-300-400-and-500-errors" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to negative-cases-300-400-and-500-errors" title="Direct link to negative-cases-300-400-and-500-errors" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="303-see-other-agency-for-warranty-outsourced"><strong>303 See Other Agency for Warranty (Outsourced)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#303-see-other-agency-for-warranty-outsourced" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 303-see-other-agency-for-warranty-outsourced" title="Direct link to 303-see-other-agency-for-warranty-outsourced" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Instead of resolving your issue directly, the brand redirects you to a third-party service center. This often happens with products bought online. Hello, Amazon warranty maze!</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="304-untouched-were-looking-into-it"><strong>304 Untouched (We’re Looking Into It)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#304-untouched-were-looking-into-it" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 304-untouched-were-looking-into-it" title="Direct link to 304-untouched-were-looking-into-it" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>You’ve submitted your claim, but the company keeps responding with, “Our team will get back to you soon.” Weeks pass, but nothing changes. Classic cached response with no updates.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="305-use-proxy-only-the-first-owner-gets-warranty"><strong>305 Use Proxy (Only the First Owner Gets Warranty)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#305-use-proxy-only-the-first-owner-gets-warranty" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 305-use-proxy-only-the-first-owner-gets-warranty" title="Direct link to 305-use-proxy-only-the-first-owner-gets-warranty" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Some motorcycle companies require warranty claims to be made by the original owner. If you’ve bought the motorcycle second-hand, tough luck finding the first owner or kiss the warranty goodbye.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="400-bad-request-invalid-warranty-claim"><strong>400 Bad Request (Invalid Warranty Claim)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#400-bad-request-invalid-warranty-claim" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 400-bad-request-invalid-warranty-claim" title="Direct link to 400-bad-request-invalid-warranty-claim" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Misplaced your receipt? No original box? Missing serial number? Your claim is denied.<br>
<!-- -->Pro tip: Keep the computer generated bill of your purchases and warranty details in your locker.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="401-unauthorized-you-bought-it-online"><strong>401 Unauthorized (You Bought It Online)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#401-unauthorized-you-bought-it-online" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 401-unauthorized-you-bought-it-online" title="Direct link to 401-unauthorized-you-bought-it-online" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Some brands deny warranty for products bought on open-market platforms or unauthorized dealers. It's their way of saying, <em>“You didn’t play by our rules.”</em></p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="402-payment-required-hidden-costs"><strong>402 Payment Required (Hidden Costs)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#402-payment-required-hidden-costs" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 402-payment-required-hidden-costs" title="Direct link to 402-payment-required-hidden-costs" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>While the product part might be under warranty, labor or transportation costs aren’t. Parcel charges for small items like chargers can sometimes exceed the product’s value. Talk about irony!</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="403-forbidden-out-of-warranty-period"><strong>403 Forbidden (Out of Warranty Period)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#403-forbidden-out-of-warranty-period" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 403-forbidden-out-of-warranty-period" title="Direct link to 403-forbidden-out-of-warranty-period" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Your claim is automatically rejected because you missed the warranty window. Companies rarely extend grace periods, so you're on your own now.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="404-not-found-company-disappeared"><strong>404 Not Found (Company Disappeared)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#404-not-found-company-disappeared" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 404-not-found-company-disappeared" title="Direct link to 404-not-found-company-disappeared" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Online brands often vanish faster than seasonal discounts. By the time your product fails, the company’s customer support or even the brand itself is nowhere to be found.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="406-not-acceptable-customer-induced-damage"><strong>406 Not Acceptable (Customer-Induced Damage)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#406-not-acceptable-customer-induced-damage" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 406-not-acceptable-customer-induced-damage" title="Direct link to 406-not-acceptable-customer-induced-damage" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Warranty claims for damage caused by misuse are promptly denied. Spilled coffee on your laptop? Dropped your phone? The terms and conditions were crystal clear. This one's on you.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="408-request-timeout-no-response-from-company"><strong>408 Request Timeout (No Response from Company)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#408-request-timeout-no-response-from-company" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 408-request-timeout-no-response-from-company" title="Direct link to 408-request-timeout-no-response-from-company" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Even with valid documents, some claims are met with silence. Eventually, you lose patience and move on.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="415-unsupported-media-type-proof-required-in-specific-formats"><strong>415 Unsupported Media Type (Proof Required in Specific Formats)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#415-unsupported-media-type-proof-required-in-specific-formats" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 415-unsupported-media-type-proof-required-in-specific-formats" title="Direct link to 415-unsupported-media-type-proof-required-in-specific-formats" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Some companies require you to upload videos or images of the defect, often in specific formats. If you can’t reproduce the issue on camera, your claim is stuck.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="426-upgrade-required-let-me-upsell-you"><strong>426 Upgrade Required (Let Me Upsell You)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#426-upgrade-required-let-me-upsell-you" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 426-upgrade-required-let-me-upsell-you" title="Direct link to 426-upgrade-required-let-me-upsell-you" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Instead of resolving your claim, companies push you to buy a newer model. It's like saying, “Why fix your old phone when you can upgrade to this shiny new one?”</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="500-internal-server-error-technicians-are-hopeless"><strong>500 Internal Server Error (Technicians Are Hopeless)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#500-internal-server-error-technicians-are-hopeless" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 500-internal-server-error-technicians-are-hopeless" title="Direct link to 500-internal-server-error-technicians-are-hopeless" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Sometimes, even well-meaning customer support can’t save the day because technicians are either incompetent or lack resources.</p>
<h4 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="504-gateway-timeout-service-center-delay"><strong>504 Gateway Timeout (Service Center Delay)</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#504-gateway-timeout-service-center-delay" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 504-gateway-timeout-service-center-delay" title="Direct link to 504-gateway-timeout-service-center-delay" translate="no">​</a></h4>
<p>Ever had a product sit in a service center for months? Delays pile up, and eventually, you're left chasing your own tail.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="tips-to-avoid-warranty-dramas">Tips to Avoid Warranty Dramas<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#tips-to-avoid-warranty-dramas" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Tips to Avoid Warranty Dramas" title="Direct link to Tips to Avoid Warranty Dramas" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-buy-smart">1. <strong>Buy Smart</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#1-buy-smart" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1-buy-smart" title="Direct link to 1-buy-smart" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Think of product purchases as software development. Match your environment and reliability needs before you hit "Proceed to Payment". Check reviews and avoid flashy influencers who rave about products shortly after launch.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-copy-success">2. <strong>Copy Success</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#2-copy-success" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2-copy-success" title="Direct link to 2-copy-success" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>If your friend swears by their Maruti or Dell, consider following suit. Proven track records often mean smoother post-purchase experiences.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-stay-organized">3. <strong>Stay Organized</strong><a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#3-stay-organized" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3-stay-organized" title="Direct link to 3-stay-organized" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Maintain a digital or physical record of invoices and warranty documents. Think of it as a git repository for your purchases.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/warranty-claim-request-response-cycle#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Claiming a warranty in India can be as unpredictable as an HTTP request to a flaky server. From <strong>200 OK</strong> to <strong>500 Internal Server Error</strong>, your experience depends on the brand, product, and sometimes sheer luck. But with a little preparation and a lot of patience, you can improve your odds.</p>
<p>Remember, warranty claims might not always bring you joy, but at least now you can laugh about them through the lens of HTTP status codes! Hope my article also clarifies if you need to buy extened warranty. That was a good tip if you read till the last line !!.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>products</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[10 takeaways from xconf 2024]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/10-takeaways-from-xconf-2024</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/10-takeaways-from-xconf-2024</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 13:30:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[XConf, the premier tech conference hosted by Thoughtworks, was held on November 22, 2024, at Marriott Whitefield, Bengaluru. The event was accessible through registration using a professional email at Thoughtworks XConf.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>XConf, the premier tech conference hosted by Thoughtworks, was held on <strong>November 22, 2024</strong>, at Marriott Whitefield, Bengaluru. The event was accessible through registration using a professional email at <a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/en-in/about-us/events/xconf/2024/India" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Thoughtworks XConf</a>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/xconf-vibe-check-1c4b3318df3c37f078a3e8b9a01c9bf5.webp" width="1200" height="900" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="event-highlights">Event Highlights<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/10-takeaways-from-xconf-2024#event-highlights" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Event Highlights" title="Direct link to Event Highlights" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Despite starting slightly behind schedule and facing time management challenges for speaker sessions, the event was vibrant and informative. Sponsored by <strong>AWS</strong> and <strong>CockroachDB</strong>, it featured five distinct booths:</p>
<ol>
<li class="">AWS</li>
<li class="">CockroachDB</li>
<li class="">Thoughtworks Careers</li>
<li class="">Thoughtworks Immersive Experiences in the Metaverse</li>
<li class="">Thoughtworks Publications</li>
</ol>
<p>The event was structured into three segments:</p>
<ol>
<li class=""><strong>Common Sessions</strong>: Keynotes and talks by AWS and other industry leaders.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Specialized Tracks</strong>: Focused sessions across specific themes.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Workshops</strong>: Exclusive, registration-based, hands-on workshops.</li>
</ol>
<p>The keynote speakers were particularly engaging, setting an inspiring tone for the day.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="themes-for-specialized-tracks">Themes for Specialized Tracks<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/10-takeaways-from-xconf-2024#themes-for-specialized-tracks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Themes for Specialized Tracks" title="Direct link to Themes for Specialized Tracks" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li class=""><strong>Machine Learning, Data, and AI</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Distributed Systems</strong></li>
<li class=""><strong>Emerging Technologies</strong>: Including SDV, XR, and Embedded Systems</li>
</ol>
<p>A standout moment was a fascinating talk by the Director of the Indian Astrophysics Department, highlighting the role of technology in space exploration. Interestingly, Thoughtworks has collaborated with the department for their software needs.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/10-takeaways-from-xconf-2024#key-takeaways" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Key Takeaways" title="Direct link to Key Takeaways" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Here are 10 notable insights from the conference:</p>
<ol>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Software Development as a Team Sport</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">AI assistants should enhance the entire software development lifecycle rather than support isolated coding efforts.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>From 10x Developers to 10x Teams</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">The aim of AI is to empower teams, fostering collaborative processes and tools for impactful delivery.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>AI Across the Software Development Lifecycle</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Beyond chatbots, AI is revolutionizing software processes, including research, planning, design, testing, deployment, and maintenance.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>AI Artifacts for Enhanced Productivity</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Sharing generative AI (GenAI) prompts across teams can significantly boost efficiency, supported by tools like Haiven Team Assistant.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Observability 2.0</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Innovations like canonical log lines are scaling observability practices while reducing network loads.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>GenAI for Legacy Code Understanding</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">GenAI facilitates reverse engineering legacy code, enabling seamless tech migrations.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Rethinking Codebase Documentation with GenAI</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">GenAI excels in generating documentation, capturing module links, and documenting architecture, epics, and stories.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>AI Tools for Diverse Problem-Solving</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Utilize GenAI prompts for code understanding, RAG (Retrieval-Augmented Generation) for problem-solving, and Graph + RAG for capability analysis in codebases.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Local-First Software Development</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">A paradigm emphasizing on-device computation for enhanced privacy, security, and real-time AI inferencing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Evaluating LLM Performance</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Techniques like "eval" and "vibe checking" are emerging for benchmarking LLMs, with both self-assessment and human validation improving model efficiency.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="additional-perks">Additional Perks<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/10-takeaways-from-xconf-2024#additional-perks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Additional Perks" title="Direct link to Additional Perks" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class="">Meet and interact with authors of Thoughtworks publications.</li>
<li class="">Opportunities for networking, paired with great coffee and exclusive goodies.</li>
<li class="">A focused event highlighting use cases in enterprise software.</li>
</ul>
<p>In conclusion, XConf 2024 provided a dynamic platform for exploring cutting-edge tech trends, fostering meaningful collaborations, and envisioning the future of enterprise software development.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>conferences</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Solar Water Heaters Pros, Cons, and Savings Calculations in 2024]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/3-reasons-not-to-buy-solar-water-heater-india</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/3-reasons-not-to-buy-solar-water-heater-india</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 13:30:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Solar water heaters have become a common sight in households, especially in southern India where the weather is ideal for harnessing solar energy. With over five years of experience dealing with solar heaters, both in my home and those of friends, I've gathered some insights on the advantages, disadvantages, and cost savings associated with these systems.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Solar water heaters have become a common sight in households, especially in southern India where the weather is ideal for harnessing solar energy. With over five years of experience dealing with solar heaters, both in my home and those of friends, I've gathered some insights on the advantages, disadvantages, and cost savings associated with these systems.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-advantages-of-having-a-solar-water-heater">3 Advantages of Having a Solar Water Heater<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/3-reasons-not-to-buy-solar-water-heater-india#3-advantages-of-having-a-solar-water-heater" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3 Advantages of Having a Solar Water Heater" title="Direct link to 3 Advantages of Having a Solar Water Heater" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p>Instant Hot Water No need to turn on the geyser and wait for it to heat up. For families with many members, this is a game-changer. My family has become accustomed to having instant hot water 24/7.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Reduced Electricity Bill Using solar energy means you save on electricity costs since you’re not using the electric geyser to heat water.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Efficient Use of Solar Energy Apart from drying clothes, it's a great way to utilize solar energy efficiently.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-downsides-of-having-a-solar-water-heater">3 Downsides of Having a Solar Water Heater<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/3-reasons-not-to-buy-solar-water-heater-india#3-downsides-of-having-a-solar-water-heater" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3 Downsides of Having a Solar Water Heater" title="Direct link to 3 Downsides of Having a Solar Water Heater" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Despite the benefits, there are notable challenges with continuous ownership:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p>Water Shortages During summer, water shortages are common. If your overhead tank runs dry, the solar tank can't cool down, leading to cracked or broken glass tubes. If a glass tube breaks, water gushes out, potentially damaging other tubes due to the solar tank being almost empty.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Vacation Planning When going on vacation, ensure your overhead tank is full. If it runs dry due to evaporation, leaks, or usage, your solar heater could be damaged. Issues like monkey problems, stones, or aerial firecrackers can also break the glass tubes.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Plumbing, Tank Quality, and Hard Water The long-term success of a solar water heater depends on these factors. Hard water requires periodic servicing, which can cost around ₹2500. Some solar tanks, made of steel alloys, can corrode and leak. The heat from the solar tank can deform pipes, so consult with plumbers about pipe quality. Hard water exacerbates these issues, damaging water-carrying devices.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="cost-of-investment-and-roi-worries">Cost of Investment and ROI Worries<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/3-reasons-not-to-buy-solar-water-heater-india#cost-of-investment-and-roi-worries" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Cost of Investment and ROI Worries" title="Direct link to Cost of Investment and ROI Worries" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Here are the numbers from my ownership, to help you with a cost-benefit analysis:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="expenses">Expenses<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/3-reasons-not-to-buy-solar-water-heater-india#expenses" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Expenses" title="Direct link to Expenses" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>2019:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p>Purchased Solar device: ₹25,000</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Solar piping and taps: ₹5,000</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Installation labor: ₹5,000</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>2023:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p>Glass tube replacement (1 tube): ₹2,000</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Service to remove salt every 2 years: ₹3,000</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Maintenance Costs:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p>Every 2 years: ₹4,000 for upkeep and salt removal</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Every 10 years: ₹20,000 for plumbing overhaul</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Additional expenses due to unexpected damage: ₹10,000</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Expected Product Life: 20 years</p>
<p>Issues faced in 5 years: Tank leak, broken glass tube, unfriendly service personnel, and uncooperative dealer.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="potential-savings">Potential Savings<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/3-reasons-not-to-buy-solar-water-heater-india#potential-savings" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Potential Savings" title="Direct link to Potential Savings" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Annual Electricity Bill Savings: ₹6,000 (₹500*12)</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="financial-summary">Financial Summary<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/3-reasons-not-to-buy-solar-water-heater-india#financial-summary" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Financial Summary" title="Direct link to Financial Summary" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p>Cost of Ownership in 20 years: ₹105,000 (approx.)</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Potential Savings: ₹120,000 (approx.)</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To recover the costs, avoid repairs due to water scarcity, monkey problems, etc.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="summary">Summary<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/3-reasons-not-to-buy-solar-water-heater-india#summary" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Summary" title="Direct link to Summary" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>While the pros and cons are nearly balanced, the convenience of having hot water readily available is a significant advantage. Purchase solar heaters from reputable dealers and ensure they provide good after-sales service. Many brands are local with informal dealer networks, so check their service commitment beforehand. For instance, a reputed brand might have only one service person for all of Bangalore and nearby districts.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>solar-heater</category>
            <category>house-owner</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google GenAI Developer Day Bangalore 2024 Learnings]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/google-genai-exchange-developer-day-2024-good-parts</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/google-genai-exchange-developer-day-2024-good-parts</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 08:30:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Gen AI Dev Day]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Gen AI Dev Day" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/genai-dev-day-28b75156cc7743775b8a327c63fc61b0.jpeg" width="4096" height="4096" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>This blog post summarizes key takeaways from the Google GenAI Developer Day in Bangalore, focusing on technical aspects relevant to  developers.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-genai-impact-and-demand">1. GenAI Impact and Demand<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/google-genai-exchange-developer-day-2024-good-parts#1-genai-impact-and-demand" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. GenAI Impact and Demand" title="Direct link to 1. GenAI Impact and Demand" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>While "AI" is often misused in marketing, the conference solidified the transformative power of Generative AI (GenAI) across personal, professional, and societal applications.  For businesses, GenAI tools enhance developer productivity by:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Auto-completion:</strong> Generating code snippets based on prompts.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Context-aware Test Generation:</strong> Automatically creating test cases.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Code Explanation and Review:</strong> Providing explanations and assisting with code reviews.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Multilingual Support:</strong> Supporting various programming languages and transpiling between them.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Full Codebase Awareness:</strong> Enriching analysis, refactoring, and optimization.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Efficient Code Generation:</strong> Capable of generating substantial code volumes (e.g., 100k lines)  from single prompts.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-code-enhancement-use-cases">2. Code Enhancement Use Cases<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/google-genai-exchange-developer-day-2024-good-parts#2-code-enhancement-use-cases" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Code Enhancement Use Cases" title="Direct link to 2. Code Enhancement Use Cases" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Live demonstrations showcased GenAI's capabilities. Notably, the creation of a shopping cart app with star ratings on both frontend and backend required only a few prompts.</p>
<p><strong>VS Gemini vs. Code Assist Addon</strong></p>
<p>While both tools generate code, Gemini offers a key advantage: it can learn and generate code for new or less common libraries on-the-fly, surpassing limitations of pre-trained languages.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-integration-with-popular-code-repositories">3. Integration with Popular Code Repositories<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/google-genai-exchange-developer-day-2024-good-parts#3-integration-with-popular-code-repositories" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Integration with Popular Code Repositories" title="Direct link to 3. Integration with Popular Code Repositories" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Google Code Assist seamlessly integrates with Github, GitLab, and Bitbucket, generating code for diverse use cases.  For enterprise security, models are trained on single-tenant private clouds, garnering trust from financial institutions.</p>
<p><strong>Developer Tools and Resources</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Vertex AI and Natural Language Integration:</strong> Enables log and crash analysis using natural language queries within GCP.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Code Assist Availability:</strong> Extends to various IDEs like Android Studio, GCP, and databases.</li>
<li class=""><strong>AI Practice Platforms:</strong> Google Colab for experimentation and Google Codelabs offering industry-leading examples.</li>
<li class=""><strong>GenAI Database Support:</strong> AlloyDB delivers high-performance, fully-managed database capabilities specifically suited for GenAI. Similar capabilities were showcased by MongoDB, Neo4j, and Elasticsearch.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Vertex AI Multimodal Exploration:</strong> Explore GenAI functionalities for various modalities within GCP via "Goto Vertex AI &gt; Multimodal &gt; Ask Prompt".</li>
<li class=""><strong>Google Cloud Functions Update:</strong> Google Cloud Functions are now rebranded as Google Cloud Run.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="4-foundational-concepts-for-genai-development">4. Foundational Concepts for GenAI Development<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/google-genai-exchange-developer-day-2024-good-parts#4-foundational-concepts-for-genai-development" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 4. Foundational Concepts for GenAI Development" title="Direct link to 4. Foundational Concepts for GenAI Development" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Developing GenAI applications requires:</p>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Training Data:</strong> To build robust models.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Context-Aware Responses:</strong> To generate relevant outputs based on natural language prompts.</li>
<li class=""><strong>Unified Data Handling:</strong> Images, videos, and text are treated as equally compatible data sources.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="5-retrieval-augmented-generation-rag">5. Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/google-genai-exchange-developer-day-2024-good-parts#5-retrieval-augmented-generation-rag" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 5. Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)" title="Direct link to 5. Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>While details weren't extensively covered, the session briefly introduced RAG as a technique for enhancing GenAI models.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="6-hackathon">6. Hackathon<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/google-genai-exchange-developer-day-2024-good-parts#6-hackathon" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 6. Hackathon" title="Direct link to 6. Hackathon" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>The concluding session featured a hackathon based on the <a href="https://codelabs.developers.google.com/patent-search-alloydb-gemini?hl=en#0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Codelabs</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="links">Links<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/google-genai-exchange-developer-day-2024-good-parts#links" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Links" title="Direct link to Links" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class="">Session Recording on Youtube - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/DqRHWq1IGgs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">https://www.youtube.com/live/DqRHWq1IGgs</a></li>
<li class="">Codelabs - <a href="https://codelabs.developers.google.com/patent-search-alloydb-gemini?hl=en#0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">https://codelabs.developers.google.com/patent-search-alloydb-gemini?hl=en#0</a></li>
<li class="">Related courses - <a href="https://www.cloudskillsboost.google/paths/118" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">https://www.cloudskillsboost.google/paths/118</a></li>
<li class="">Google cloud India - <a href="https://twitter.com/GoogleCloud_IN" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">https://twitter.com/GoogleCloud_IN</a></li>
<li class="">Webinars - <a href="https://cloudonair.withgoogle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">https://cloudonair.withgoogle.com/</a></li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>conferences</category>
            <category>GenAI</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[React Nexus 2024, Good Parts. A Consise Summary in 100 points.]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/react-nexus-2024-good-parts</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/react-nexus-2024-good-parts</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2024 17:30:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The objective of this post is to summarize the key points discussed in React Nexus 2024 conference in 100 points. I call them good parts of React Nexus 2024. I add my commentary along the way. Hope you like it and read all the way from good parts #1 to #100.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/react-nexus-62772fd5af5b45408910b16425d1bbba.jpg" width="1000" height="563" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>The objective of this post is to summarize the key points discussed in React Nexus 2024 conference in 100 points. I call them good parts of React Nexus 2024. I add my commentary along the way. Hope you like it and read all the way from good parts #1 to #100.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="good-parts">Good Parts<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/react-nexus-2024-good-parts#good-parts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Good Parts" title="Direct link to Good Parts" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="venue--arragements">Venue &amp; Arragements<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/react-nexus-2024-good-parts#venue--arragements" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Venue &amp; Arragements" title="Direct link to Venue &amp; Arragements" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li class="">
<p>The selection of <a href="https://reactnexus.com/#venue" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">React Nexus 2024 Venue</a> was Apt, not just easy for attendees but also in line with react nexus 2023 venue. Radison Blu Marathahalli is our 2 day adda (means a social gathering or hangout spot).</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The rockstars of the conference, the speakers were simply meritorious and profound. The full list along with their linkedin and X handles can be found on <a href="https://reactnexus.com/#speakers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">React Nexus Speakers Section</a></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The conference vibe was kindled by a giant screen resembling a movie theatre and JBL speakers playing <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DA-ChrNuyO0&amp;pp=ygUPZGVlcCBkb3BlIG11c2lj" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">deep dope beats</a>. Further momentum was added by <a href="https://reactnexus.com/#mcs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">charismatic emcees</a> who knew tech and humour.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The conference goodies included an name card tag, tshirt which is true to its size variant and few stickers. Minimalistic and useful.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The overall conference was jam packed with surprises like traditional yakshagana dance, activities which felt like cardio &amp; desk yoga, standup comedy, Bhangra dance which resembled flash mob, timely coffee and great food.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="day-1-of-react-nexus-2024">Day 1 of React Nexus 2024<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/react-nexus-2024-good-parts#day-1-of-react-nexus-2024" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Day 1 of React Nexus 2024" title="Direct link to Day 1 of React Nexus 2024" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ol start="6">
<li class="">
<p>The first speaker was Naman Goel, spoke about "Designing for design: API decisions for long-term success". Naman is a maintainer at <a href="https://stylexjs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">StyleX JS</a> at Meta. He spoke about the design decisions, importance of inspiration and lineage in developing libraries and quick demos of stylex.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Finish your side project to be successful. I do not think this needs any explaination. Simple advice yet profound.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>React was inspired by functional programming so hooks were inevitable and a natural progression. The same inspiration is a hidden force in stylex JS as well.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Evolution of ReactJS be like.. React create class --&gt; JSX --&gt; Real classes --&gt; Functional Components --&gt; hooks --&gt; React server components..</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Conference talk idea. "Algebraic effects". This is a react concept which is discussed on <a href="https://overreacted.io/algebraic-effects-for-the-rest-of-us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Dan Blog</a> and referenced in Naman Goel speech.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Trade offs help us to reach the sweet spot in design decisions. I cant agree more, without tradeoff programming would be simply hard for many.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>React fiber underwent a complete rewrite 8 years ago due to which we are able to add further enhancements to React like hooks, React Server Components (RSC), etc. Its always a good value add to hear directly from maintainers at Meta.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The second speaker Nurul Sundarani, spoke about "Beyond the Backend: The Rise of React Server Components". He gave a lightning introduction to React Server Components (RSC in short) and how we can use them with <a href="https://www.prisma.io/docs/getting-started" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Prisma</a>.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>In the era of RSC, every frontend developer will be a fullstack developer too. Tools like Prisma should help you with that transformation.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>RSC can directly talk to databases, render only on the server so they can have API keys, good for SEO as the HTML and CSS alone can add value to the web crawlers, make the website quick by avoiding render fetch, etc.. The list goes on. Bottomline learn RSC ASAP. Good for you and your business.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The third speaker Akash Hamirwasia, spoke about "Enhancing your Static Sites with React Server Components". Yes, RSC can be used on the static website. Sounds contrary? then read on.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><a href="https://akashhamirwasia.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Static websites</a> too run on a server and RSC can make use of the file server to do more. I was not able to find the code on Speaker Github but you need to know that its a possibility to do RSC on static websites.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>I was impressed with ease and confidence with which the relatively young speaker Akash was able to put his point across the room. While I was watching his speech, I was convinced without a doubt. Bottomline, the speaker had exceeding levels of communications skills and confidence. Sometimes you pick up a thing or two non tech skills in a tech conference.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The fourth speaker Stefinie Fernando spoke about "Building Secure React Apps with Choreo IDevP". The software Choreo had some similarity with GCP app engine. In choreo the role of the developer ends with commiting code and packaging app into a image. The rest is taken care by Choreo platform.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The Choreo platform boasts of complete software development cycle support ranging from CI/CD to deployment on a cluster. To playaround, visit <a href="https://wso2.com/choreo/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Choreo website</a>.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Next JS which is a react framework has good levels of RSC support. Other react frameworks like remix are not behind. Think RSC, think react frameworks. RSC have friends too, they are called React server actions. <code>use server</code> directive, heard of it?</p>
</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>If there were one word that was repeated a lot during react nexus 2024, it would be RSC</p>
</blockquote>
<ol start="22">
<li class="">
<p>The fourth speaker Vamshi Suram spoke about "Scalable mock data injection into Apollo (GraphQL) Client". Overall the speaker was confortable on stage talking about his open source project <a href="https://github.com/intuit/apollo-mock-http" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">apollo-mock-http</a> which helps us with data mocking even in enterprise level applications.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Mocking should be done away from application layer so that they can be toggled with a feature switch. This is not advice specific to apollo client but frontend in general. I like this application design pattern.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Good mocking should not hinder or interfere with UI rendering because you loose out on the UI interactivity and animation. This advice is given with the context of react components where devs set data to props directly to mock the data.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The fifth speaker Sweta Tanwar spoke about "Defensive Development: Testing Tactics for React Native Resilience". This was the first speech referencing React Native in React Nexus 2024. The content was actionable and could easily be blown up into a full book.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Defensive application development can be broken into 3 categories. Code practices, Testing and CI/CD automation. More details in the next thread.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Code practices include code quality checks, error handling with graceful degradation and error boundaries, component isolation before testing</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Testing practices include Unit testing with Jest, Integration testing with Enzyme and E2E testing with Detox/Appium. On react we are mostly talking about React testing with Vitest and playwright testing.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The pyramid visualization was used to show that an app needs more unit tests which are efficient and integration testing at the top of the pyramid which are comprehensive. The pyramid slide will be referenced in my future discussions with architects on why unit, e2e and integration.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>CI/CD automation of tests can be done to catch regression issues in a automated fashion. We can use tools like circle CI, Travis, etc.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The Sixth Speaker Rajat Vijay spoke about "Experiments with AI-Generated Tests". I see the testing theme, pre lunch to be a good idea. Good job organizers. I can sense that Rajat has seen good amount of tests in his career. He clearly outlined the problem with Copilot generated tests and how he intends to fix them.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Rajat mentioned a tool titled "auto guardian" which instructs AI tools about the expected quality and style of testing. It looks like a config file for AI testing. I feel this would bring uniformity in the AI testing.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Rajat spilled a few interview questions. userEvent vs fireEvent? Whats the difference and which is better. getByRole vs getByText. I will write a blog about these topics soon</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Rajat referenced <a href="https://www.promptingguide.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">https://www.promptingguide.ai/</a> to understand more about writing better prompts. I believe the future auto guardian would refer to these prompting standards.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The testing demo was fun to watch and clearly the quality of tests can be increased greatly. The link to github repo is broken. Rajat plz toggle the repo to public if its private.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The seventh speaker were from freshworks, spoke about "AI-Assisted Development: Harnessing the Freshworks Freddy Copilot Toolkit for App Development". The second sponsor speech on day 1. Its interested to see the no code movement gaining steam. Developers can build a full fledged application with a few apps and monetise on the platform. Thats insane.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The Freedy Copilot had lot of similarities with github copilot. It needed registration, installation on vs code, type your requirement on chat. Freedy can also deploy to their marketplace. Finally no code app generation is in reach / at times free to use.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The different stages from an idea to app. Requirements gathering, design, implemenation &amp; refactoring, testing can be handled by Freedy.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Freedy can also build UI for the developers based on the prompt. frontend engineers, gulp it down. Yes AI can build UI. Freedy relies on vision models for generating UI for freshworks marketplace.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The engineering behind Freedy copilot was also discussed by second presenter Nagaraj. All I could injest into my mind were LLM, AI and more of it. Finally Day 1 Lunch hour.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The post lunch first session featured a panel discussion comprising none other than the react core team from meta, how cool is that. We had Satya talk about the working on React compiler. Yes I heard it for the first time. I know only about React fiber but React compiler is a thing. True to its name, it compiles your react app into something sophisticated.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The react compiler could potentially free us from writing useMemo and useCallback as the compiler could do better code optimization compared to a normal developer. However if the compiler identifies a tricky code or hacky code, it will assume that developer is the best judge and shall not mess with it.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>In React 19, ref is a regular prop. I hope to miss forwardExoticComponentRef in my life.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>There was a short and sweet answer to breaking changes, if you had been following the modern standards of react development. Then there are no breaking changes that should bother you. So legacy app developers brace yourself, modern app developers rejoice and upgrade to react 19.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>eslint plugin for react is now updated and optimized for react compiler. However there are many bugs that could escape the eslint and get inferred by React compiler. Code better and do not just trust eslint for react.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>React Strict DOM (RSD) is an integration of React DOM and StyleX, aiming to streamline and standardize the development of styled React components for web and native targets. We had Stylex maintainer Naman Goel talk about the possibilities of RSD.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The conversation quickly moved towards RSC (React Server Components) best practices. Don't waste time hydrating components that are not read/used.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Render as you fetch or fetch as you render? An another interview question to note. The panel favoured Render as you fetch as mentioned this is how apps to be built be it RSC or RN</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>use operator is used for reading resources outside of the render. However it being a panel discussion, no demo or code was shown about the use operator. An another speech topic for potential speakers.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The road ahead for react team looks like this. Compilation improvements, eslint plugin updates, lot of tooling related work is expected. I remember panel mentioning NextJS, Remix, etc. The panel discussion felt short but Tapas (the moderator) was well prepared with sharp questions.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The eighth speaker Prateek Surana spoke about "Elevate your routing game with TanStack Router". Definitely I felt slightly outdated or an idiot for not use tanstack router after his demo. The power and relevance for enterprise use cases were amazing and would prevent developers from reinventing the wheel around routing.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Tanstack router is file based, which is easy to understand and relatively hard to scale. To me the most killer feature was auto filter param rename in runtime. Let us say if param was misspelled, tanstack query can correct it for us without breaking the application</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The overall tanstack tools are squarely built around scaled react usecases which is beyond a simple ecommerce use case. I recommend checking out other tanstack tools and I am also excited to see how the tanstack fullstack comes out to be.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The nineth speaker Palak Bansal spoke about "Mastering Image Optimization Techniques for Web Performance in React Applications". Let us face it, images can be hard to optimize and Addy osmani has written a book about it. Palak rightly hit the nail on the head by telling "Best practices keep changing which makes image optimization harder"</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Broadly there are 3 image optimization techniques that were discussed. They are lazy loading, responsive  images and image CDN.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Lazy loading can be done on the <img> tag with a attribute called lazy. The responsive images can be based on width of the client or pixel density of the client. Image cdn can be self managed or third party cdn which generate images on the fly specially for the client</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>If you are wondering if the talk around image optimization is not as comprehensive as <a href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2021/04/image-optimization-pre-release/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Addy Osmani</a> book, you are right. This is a small talk format, some speeches are smaller than others.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The tenth speaker Jerad Rutnam spoke about "Simplify React App Login". The reasons for having a login feature are access control and personalization. But having a solid authentication logic can be hard and there were the sponsor of the event pitched his humble React component which was part of <a href="https://wso2.com/asgardeo/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Asgardeo sdk</a></p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>As part of Asgardeo team, the recommendation from Jerad was to delegate complex parts of the app and focus on business logic implementation which could be your goto market strategy. Cannot deny if everyone had good budget, flexibility in the code and restrictions around data.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The eleventh speaker Apurv Khare spoke about "Flashpoint Performance". Is that even a thing or library or concept? Before I could stop wondering, the speaker was sprinting at the speed of flash with his speech. Lots of concepts discussed and I had tough time writing down the ideas from his speech. But the speaker knew his tools and he explained with confidence.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Measure performance first and optimize later. The speaker took us through different categories of performance metrics like Browser metrics, Core web vitals, Lab data &amp; Field data. The optimization techniques include compression techniques, optimizing JS, optimizing CSS, resource hints and optimized Largest Contentful Paint (LCP).</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The speaker idea was to give a crash course on measure performance and also optimizing the performance with some numbers/reports from the tools wherever required. But I do not think the speaker showed us any tool called flashpoint.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Browser metrics - Time To First Byte (TTFB), Speed Index. Core web vitals / User experience metrics - Largest Contentful Paint (LCP), Interaction to Next Paint (INP), First Input Delay (FID), Cumulative Latest Shift (CLS)</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Here are some of the tools to measure website performance. App run at lab condition / lab data - Lighthouse, webpage test. App run at field condition / field data - Chrome UX report (CrUX), Pagespeed insights</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The network waterfall was well discussed with webpageTest and web vitals were discussed. The important performance concept, Critical Rendering Path was discussed. Of course, the speaker mentioned how CSSOM is built and how its different from JS DOM.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Website performance testing on first load vs repeat load was interesting to me because we generally measure the first load only. Wherever flat text files or documents are served from server to client, we must enable one of the gzip, brottli or other compression techniques</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>For optimizing JS - Pause blocking JS, defer it as much as possible. For Optimizing CSS - download CSS ASAP on the device in one chunk so that CSSOM gets built and the user can see the content rendered. Use resource hints like rel, as to pre load the content before it gets used. When prefetching multiple resources, use fetch priority.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The day 1 post noon, performance speeches continue. The 12th speaker and last speaker of the day was Saurabh Daware and he spoke about "Debugging Performance Issues of Your Website". The previous speech was theoretical and this speech was practical to the best.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Performance issues are like any other bugs, for debugging performance issues just do not put a break point. The first place to look for is the network waterfall whenever we face an issue.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The speaker was running a static site featuring Razorpay landing page, he demonstrated First Contentful Paint and Last Contentful Paint. The speaker attempted to showcase perceived performance optimization and how his attempted interfered with other metrics like LCP.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The speaker showcased how he cleverly chose to improve the perceived performance by booting the webcontainer only when code gets focus, until that point he shows the static output which gives the user the perception of fast. Its kind of fake it until you make it logic.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="day-2-of-react-nexus-2024">Day 2 of React Nexus 2024<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/react-nexus-2024-good-parts#day-2-of-react-nexus-2024" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Day 2 of React Nexus 2024" title="Direct link to Day 2 of React Nexus 2024" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ol start="72">
<li class="">
<p>Day 2 felt somewhat slow to me as we did not waste time at registration desk. But things took a turn when we begun the day 2 with a lightening talk about Yoga. The speaker gave a mini talk focussed on breathing, expanding spine length and some posture correction tips. We need to take 10 minutes a day to see the difference.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The key exercises mentioned were neck stretches, breathing slow and deep, shoulder roll, cat cow pose while sitting. If you are yoga geek, then Tadasana and Garudasana were mentioned. If you feel stiff like wood, then remember range of motion increases with consistency.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 13th speaker Alex Lobera spoke about "Future-proofing state management at scale". He showcased the app he works on "Miro" and there is definitely lot of user state, sync state happening in the app. The app looks like scrum board and renders on canvas/webGL based on the client.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The author somehow connected the PHP era with RSC era. We were essentially connecting to DB and building UI all in one php file. We are doing the same in RSC. Just the server was not in the picture during SPA era and now its back. Congrats, everyone is now a full stack engineer.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Client can access server state but server cannot access client state. The server is coming back to the picture, this time its different. The server can help us build a state in RSC era. fyi day 2 had lot of speakers flying into India for the conference. Alex was from Portugal.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 14th speaker Tapas Adhikary spoke about "Do You Really Need React Query For Your Applications?". I was one of the user of React Query and I got hooked. The real threat to React Query was change in context due to RSC. Now the client can talk to DB directly. However for complex use cases we might still need tanstack query.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 15th speaker K Kamalakannan spoke about "Simplifying Complex Logic: Leveraging XState in React Development". I appreciate the state machine part, orchestration and visualization aspect of XState.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 16th speaker Ankit Tailor spoke about "How I built a Powerful Typed System?". He had worked on a design sytem called gluestack where he has authored CSS in JS which needs to be type safe. I could appreciate the use case for generic data types in designing type systems.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The speaker mentions different aspects of DX like linting, debugging tools, typescript type checks and he showcased a CLI diagnostic tool which could show the size of generated types file which is absolutely needed for performance reasons. npx tsc --diagnostics</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 16th and 17th speaker were Mike Grabowski &amp; Eric Vicenti speaking about a new paradigm "How you can Server-Render without Rendering on the Server". At the core we are trying to use web sockets to communicate with client UI on realtime to render changes. The use case was showcases interactively like a theatre play by 2 speaker on the stage with live coding.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The speakers showcased their npm component library which could react to our code listening via WS protocol. The links to the code or library cannot be found on google. Watch out for <a href="https://rise.tools/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">rise.tools</a>. Not just the rendering library, rise.tools also has a component library so that developers can quickly build apps along with a playground.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 18th speaker Sanket Sahu spoke about "Building Back-End Driven Universal Apps". Conceptually Sanket is attempting to solve the same problem as Mike &amp; Eric. Instead of too much code which looks like config. We have syntactically simpler code which can be generated by chatgpt to a very high level of accuracy. Thats in line with no code development of the future.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 19th speaker Shruti Arya spoke about "Measuring UI performance at scale". The talk was mostly about React native app on low end android devices. The github project was called component-profiler. Surprisingly I could not catch hold of the link to it. The goal was to prevent long re-renders so that there is no jankiness.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 20th speaker Santosh Yadav spoke about "Improve your Developer Experience with Nx". When the pain point that Nx tries to fill was lengthy build times on any machine, be it CI/CD or cloud or local. The NX tool intelligently creates a graph of the code and precisely knows the impact of the code change. Then runs the required build tasks instead of running every single build step on the entire code base.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 21st speaker Apoorv Taneja spoke about "Creating beautiful experiences with Framer-Motion on web". <a href="https://www.framer.com/motion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Framer motion</a> helps anyone without indepth css knowledge build animations. The speaker precisely showed us how to use framer to create interactivity on the UI components.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 22nd speaker Yashpreet Bathla spoke about "Avoid flickering user interfaces". The presentation deck resembled windows 95 and it was amazing. The speaker explained the concepts like call stack, micro task queue, macro task queue and render queue in detail. He also mentioned the need to maintain 60FPS, and one render in 16.6ms to have a jank free interface. He also showed how using useLayoutEffect helps in preventing jankiness when compared to useEffect</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 23rd speaker Mohit Kumar Toshniwal spoke about "Building XR applications using React Three Fiber". As speaker rightly said, the AR/VR usage has increased. Be it shopping on amazon or navigating with google maps. We can build AR/VR apps in react with react three fiber, drei, leva, react-xr etc</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Then a panel discussion follows but this time the theme is state of react native. Panelists mentioned that react native is yet to reach v1.0.0. The expo eco system is quite mature and visiting expo.new is the way to get started with React native.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 24th speaker Neha Sharma spoke about "Connecting Worlds: Enhancing Accessibility in React Native TV Applications". Her talk was more about building accessible react native apps for smart TVs. On the mobile, the accessible is missing unlike accessible semantic html. This calls for more empathy from react native developers. The attributes like accessible are must have to make app accessible on TVs. The speaker reiterated that accessiblity is hard, its not a requirement but a feature to have.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The 25th speaker Siddharth Kshetrapal spoke about Building accessible reusable react components. Having worked at primer.style, he is proficient in comprehending accessiblity issues and uses his tech speaker skills to make it interesting and understandable to audience. The speaker used 2 commonly used github widgets and tried to make them accessible.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Siddharth referenced the importance of <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/ARIA/apg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">APG</a> over WCAG in some use cases. he cleverly used the voice over to illustrate the pain, which the disabled people undergo due to our incorrect coding. I was thrilled and hooked to this speech, will certain share this speech to A11 enthusiasts.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="other-wonders-from-react-nexus-2024">Other wonders from React Nexus 2024<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/blog/2024/react-nexus-2024-good-parts#other-wonders-from-react-nexus-2024" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Other wonders from React Nexus 2024" title="Direct link to Other wonders from React Nexus 2024" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ol start="93">
<li class="">
<p>I watched the react documentary trailer for the first time and happy to see the people behind React and the collective team spirit. You should watch it too, I mean the full video on youtube titled <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8pDqJVdNa44" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">"How A Small Team of Developers Created React at Facebook | React.js: The Documentary"</a>.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The sponsors were unintrusive, I was not bored by their presence on the stage or at the booth. Both of them answered the questions earnestly. The Freedy developer, aka AI tool for freshworks marketplace developers booth at the conference was showering goodies to the successful quiz winners and they had a lucky draw too.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The Asgardio platform which is a simple managed Authentication platform for developers conducted a workshop post the day 1 session which I felt was a generous  offering for attendees. The choreo platform which was an another stall was a useful utility for individual developers and small teams who want to have managed backend service. I love their stickers and pens kept for visitors.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The audience were diverse in terms of demographics and their roots. Some of them were from students at Scalar academy, managers at Microsoft, founders of companies and in between. The Javascript community is quite strong like a giant multinational company having its subsidaries for their interests. We have JS Lovers, Chennai React, Delhi React, React Day Bangalore, team shiksha, etc</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Emcee Jobs are hardest and demands Charisma. Aakansha Doshi was simply bold and energetic. The cardio session to beat the sleep was a masterstroke by Aakansha.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>From timely humor to manager jokes, the second emcee Sahil Kalyani was equally charismatic on the stage. The third emcee Yashraj Nayak, whom I would remember for "how is the josh" was unique. He had deep connections with speakers and he was able to discuss some enjoyable anecdotes from his experience working with the speaker. Lastly "How is the Josh?"</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>The one last thing would be the presentation aids prepared by the tech speakers were spellbound. I would appeciate the amount of time, thought and content the speakers have put into the presentations aids / PPT material. I could not differentiate if its online editor or powerpoint tools or excalidraw or just 10x creative powers of the speakers who were frontend engineers.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Thats enough about react nexus and my commentary on React nexus 2024, have a good day.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>react-conferences</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>