<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>dhbalaji, lead design technologist at Sabre Blog</title>
        <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads</link>
        <description>dhbalaji, lead design technologist at Sabre Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 15:30:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Let's Talk Legacy A Financial Planner for Your Loved Ones by Monika Halan]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/20</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/20</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Book talk on Let's Talk Legacy A Financial Planner for Your Loved Ones by Monika Halan]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/lets-talk-money-2df39ae0270ae003b18dcf92d120468a.jpg" width="986" height="1500" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Here's a booktalk for "Let's Talk Legacy: A Financial Planner for Your Loved Ones" by Monika Halan.</p>
<p>2024 was an incredible year for my reading journey, especially in the realm of personal finance. Among the many books I read, one that truly stands out is "Let's Talk Legacy: A Financial Planner for Your Loved Ones" by Monika Halan. This book has become an essential addition to my financial library.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This is a work book which goes into bank locker and not your bookshelf</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Anticipation and Initial Reactions</strong></p>
<p>I eagerly followed this book from its pre-launch phase, but it initially left some young readers disappointed. They had certain expectations for a financial book, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">A clear algorithmic or logical process.</li>
<li class="">Over 225 pages of paperback content.</li>
<li class="">A Bollywood-style happy ending that makes you feel like you've achieved your Financial Independence, Retire Early (FIRE) goals.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What the Book Actually Offers</strong></p>
<p>However, "Let's Talk Legacy" offers something different:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Approximately 20 pages of insightful content and over 100 pages of practical worksheets.</li>
<li class="">A focus on planning for the inevitable, rather than achieving FIRE goals.</li>
<li class="">Encouraging active participation with pen and paper, rather than simply clicking a payment button.</li>
</ul>
<p>Despite facing early criticism and poor reviews, the book has reversed trend and earned its rightful place on the bookshelves.</p>
<p><strong>Who Should Read This Book?</strong></p>
<p>This book is a must-read for anyone who believes in the importance of insurance products. Let's break it down:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">We buy insurance to ensure our family's well-being during unforeseen events.</li>
<li class="">But what if our assets remain inaccessible?</li>
<li class="">What if we haven’t made a will, added relevant nominees, or even discussed insurance within the family?</li>
</ul>
<p>This book aims to help you get organized, making it easier for your loved ones to access your assets when you are no longer around.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-big-ideas-from-lets-talk-legacy">3 Big Ideas from Let's Talk Legacy<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/20#3-big-ideas-from-lets-talk-legacy" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3 Big Ideas from Let's Talk Legacy" title="Direct link to 3 Big Ideas from Let's Talk Legacy" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-use-a-simple-approach">1. Use a Simple Approach<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/20#1-use-a-simple-approach" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. Use a Simple Approach" title="Direct link to 1. Use a Simple Approach" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>We often overcomplicate security measures, password-protecting everything from phones to lockers. The author suggests a simpler method: write down all necessary details in the provided worksheets and store the book in a secure place or bank locker. When your nominees access the locker, they will find everything neatly laid out.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-list-all-assets">2. List All Assets<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/20#2-list-all-assets" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. List All Assets" title="Direct link to 2. List All Assets" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Create an inventory of all types of assets on the worksheets provided in the book with verbose details, including:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Bank accounts</li>
<li class="">Real estate</li>
<li class="">Stocks and securities</li>
<li class="">Collectibles</li>
<li class="">Government documents like passports</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-make-a-will-document">3. Make a Will Document<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/20#3-make-a-will-document" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Make a Will Document" title="Direct link to 3. Make a Will Document" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>A will is essential for anyone with assets and above the age of 18. It specifies how you want to distribute your assets after you pass away. The author provides a template for creating a will, making the process straightforward.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="summary">Summary<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/20#summary" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Summary" title="Direct link to Summary" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>This book isn't about making money through tactical or strategic methods. Instead, it's about ensuring your wealth is passed on smoothly to your loved ones. It's not a book for passive reading but an interactive guide that requires you to sit down with a pen and paper. Remember to update the worksheets regularly. This book's place is in your locker, not just on your bookshelf.</p>
<p>So, if you're looking for a practical and thoughtful guide to planning your financial legacy, <em>"Let's Talk Legacy"</em> is a must-read!</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Grit The Power of Passion and Perseverance by Angela Duckworth]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/19</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/19</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Book talk on Grit The Power of Passion and Perseverance by Angela Duckworth]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/grit-book-46138ba4cb5bd68cb6d2f9f141d9a13b.webp" width="1490" height="2348" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>“One of the lines I heard on the internet: Recreation is overrated.” That sentiment, while seemingly harsh, encapsulates how the top performers of any field approach life. They don’t fold under pressure, they don’t abandon their goals when the going gets tough, and they certainly don’t leave projects hanging when distractions show up on their phone. Angela Duckworth’s Grit: The Power of Passion and Perseverance is a profound reminder of what it takes to excel.</p>
<p>There are no shortcuts, quick strategies, or shiny tools sold here. This book is about one thing: putting in the work. And it makes you believe that consistent effort, not just talent, turns ordinary individuals into rock stars.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="who-should-read-this-book">Who should read this book?<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/19#who-should-read-this-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Who should read this book?" title="Direct link to Who should read this book?" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Are you feeling stuck? Perhaps it’s a slump at work, in your personal growth, or even in your favorite sport. Slumps are like quicksand—they pull you down slowly unless you fight back. This book is a lifeline for those moments.</p>
<p>Life often goes into autopilot mode, and we shift focus elsewhere, letting critical areas languish. Duckworth’s Grit serves as a wake-up call, a nudge to rekindle that fire and embrace a mindset that champions relentless effort. If you’re searching for a way out of stagnation, this book is for you.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="top-3-ideas">Top 3 ideas<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/19#top-3-ideas" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Top 3 ideas" title="Direct link to Top 3 ideas" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="talent-is-overrated">Talent is overrated<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/19#talent-is-overrated" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Talent is overrated" title="Direct link to Talent is overrated" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>How often do we hear the phrase, “They’re a natural”? Society is obsessed with the idea of talent, often crediting it for someone’s success while ignoring the years of effort behind the scenes. But Duckworth flips the script.</p>
<p>While talent is a good starting point, it’s hardly the full picture. True skill and achievement come from effort. She simplifies this idea with a powerful formula:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Talent × Effort = Skill
Skill × Effort = Achievement</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Effort counts twice! It turns raw ability into a developed skill and then transforms that skill into real-world results. Duckworth reminds us that even if talent gives someone a head start, consistent effort is what wins the race.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="how-to-develop-grit">How to develop grit<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/19#how-to-develop-grit" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How to develop grit" title="Direct link to How to develop grit" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Grit isn’t something you’re born with—it’s something you build. Duckworth identifies three essential ingredients that catalyze grit:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p>Interest: You can’t fake passion. To persevere, you need to genuinely enjoy what you’re doing. Finding something that excites you is the first step.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Purpose: Purpose goes beyond personal ambition. When your goals align with helping others or creating something meaningful, you’re far more likely to persevere. Purpose transforms grit into a mission.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Hope: Hope fuels resilience. It’s the belief that setbacks are temporary and challenges are surmountable. Duckworth emphasizes that maintaining optimism during tough times is key to staying the course.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="role-of-parenting">Role of parenting<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/19#role-of-parenting" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Role of parenting" title="Direct link to Role of parenting" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Parenting is pivotal in nurturing grit in children. The environment a child grows up in can either foster resilience or hinder it.</p>
<p>Duckworth advocates for a balanced approach: a combination of high standards (challenging children to push their limits) and unwavering support (providing a safe space to fail and try again). She highlights how early lessons in effort, persistence, and a growth mindset can create gritty adults who thrive under pressure.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="summary">Summary<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/19#summary" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Summary" title="Direct link to Summary" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Duckworth’s message is clear: success isn’t about luck, talent, or shortcuts. It’s about squeezing every ounce of effort from yourself, just as you would a lemon for its juice. Grit is about persevering when adversity strikes, and pushing forward when the path gets steep.</p>
<p>The beauty of Grit lies in its storytelling. Duckworth blends research, anecdotes, and actionable insights in a way that’s easy to read and deeply impactful. This isn’t a lecture—it’s an invitation to transform how you think about success.</p>
<p>So, do you have the grit to pick up this book? If you do, be prepared to see effort, perseverance, and passion in a whole new light. It might just change your life.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The 22 Immutable Laws Of Marketing by AI Ries & Jack Trout]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/18</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/18</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Book talk on the 22 Immutable Laws Of Marketing by AI Ries & Jack Trout]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/22-marketing-4eff83c093ce0ff20e598d994f25b663.jpg" width="652" height="1000" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="why-this-book">Why This Book?<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/18#why-this-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why This Book?" title="Direct link to Why This Book?" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>As a software engineer, I recognized that despite my proficiency with AI and technology tools, I lacked essential marketing skills. This deficiency was hindering my ability to effectively sell products online. In my quest to bridge this gap, I stumbled upon "The 22 Immutable Laws of Marketing" by Al Ries and Jack Trout. This book has been a revelation, offering deep insights into the principles of marketing. Here, I will share three significant concepts from the book for my reference and yours.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="big-ideas">Big Ideas<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/18#big-ideas" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Big Ideas" title="Direct link to Big Ideas" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-the-law-of-perception">1. The Law of Perception<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/18#1-the-law-of-perception" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. The Law of Perception" title="Direct link to 1. The Law of Perception" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>In India, Maruti Suzuki is a household name. However, it is perceived primarily as a mass-market brand, struggling to penetrate the premium segment. To address this, Maruti launched a new brand, Nexa, which has had some success in selling premium cars. Although it has a long way to go to compete with German brands, it is a step in the right direction.</p>
<p>Similarly, marketing is all about perception. It is not about having the best product but about being perceived as the best. The advertising, taglines, and positioning are all about embedding the brand name in the consumer's mind until it becomes the first choice. For example, Pepsi is perceived as youthful, while Coca-Cola is seen as old-school.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You may build a great product, but the buyer should perceive you as a great product.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-the-law-of-category">2. The Law of Category<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/18#2-the-law-of-category" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. The Law of Category" title="Direct link to 2. The Law of Category" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Have you ever wondered why Maruti produces so many car models even though their prices are often similar? The answer lies in categories. To become a market leader, companies position themselves by creating sub-categories. These sub-categories are further broken down into smaller niches.</p>
<p>Within these small categories, leaders emerge. For instance, Mahindra is the market leader in the SUV segment in India. As a developer, I fall into the sub-category of lead frontend engineers. If you cannot become the number one detergent seller, create a sub-category like liquid detergent and dominate it. This is what Godrej Consumer Care is doing with the liquid detergent market.</p>
<p>A sub category may not fully kill the parent category. For example kindle did not replace books completly.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Instead of building a "me-too" product, create a sub-category and be number one in that category.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-the-law-of-duality">3. The Law of Duality<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/18#3-the-law-of-duality" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. The Law of Duality" title="Direct link to 3. The Law of Duality" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>In the long run, every market is dominated by two major players. This phenomenon is inherent in market dynamics. For example, in India, the telecom market, now an essential commodity, is dominated by two giants: Jio and Airtel. The third player, Vodafone, and others continually lose market share to these leaders.</p>
<p>This pattern is evident in various categories:</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Premium Motorcycles: Royal Enfield and KTM</li>
<li class="">Soda: Coca-Cola and Pepsi</li>
<li class="">Premium Detergents: Surf Excel and Ariel</li>
<li class="">Search Engines: Google and Bing</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Once the market is polarized by two companies, people perceive them as superior and choose them repeatedly.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/18#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>This book has been an eye-opener, helping me understand the marketing dynamics around me. I now comprehend why the Indian telecom market is a duopoly between Jio and Airtel. As a developer, I realize the importance of choosing a sub-category and gaining market share there, rather than competing in the general segment.</p>
<p>While the book is highly informative and offers actionable ideas, it is not a manual that can be implemented in its entirety. It provides a foundation of marketing principles that one can adapt and build upon.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Developer experience by Addy Osmani]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/17</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/17</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Book talk on Developer experience by Addy Osmani]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="&amp;quot;Developer experience by Addy Osmani&amp;quot;" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/developer-exp-ba6aef2c3f7c4284390b4d9353b1ea24.png" width="1092" height="698" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Developer Experience (DX) is not just a buzzword tossed around at conferences; it's a crucial aspect of software development that significantly influences how developers author, maintain, and test software. Addy Osmani, a prominent figure in the development community, has recently penned a book on DX, providing valuable insights that can reshape how we approach software development. In this blog post, we'll delve into the key takeaways from the book and explore the principles, metrics, and strategies that contribute to a seamless DX.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="first-impressions">First Impressions<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/17#first-impressions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to First Impressions" title="Direct link to First Impressions" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Addy Osmani's book on DX is not only a compelling read but also freely accessible on the internet, making it a valuable resource for developers. With around one hundred pages, it offers succinct yet powerful insights that can be immediately applied in the enterprise software development landscape.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/17#key-takeaways" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Key Takeaways" title="Direct link to Key Takeaways" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Core of DX:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">DX revolves around how easily and effectively developers can accomplish tasks.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>DX vs. UX:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Good DX shares similarities with good User Experience (UX).</li>
<li class="">Components include understanding developer needs, designing intuitive tools, providing high-quality documentation, and fostering support and community engagement.</li>
<li class="">Success metrics involve surveys, quantitative metrics, and productivity gains.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Qualitative and Quantitative Metrics:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Metrics span usability, accessibility, findability, credibility, usefulness, value, and sentiment analysis.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>First Principles of DX:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Embrace principles like speed, minimal friction, incremental steps, hands-on learning, and prompt issue resolution.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Developer Tool Evaluation:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Developers assess tools based on APIs, documentation quality, development speed, production readiness, architectural understanding, ecosystem maturity, and debugging ease.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Quick Tips:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Prioritize error management.</li>
<li class="">Emphasize speed.</li>
<li class="">Market effectively.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Effective Error Messages:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Good error messages identify the problem, its cause, and the solution, unblocking developers in the process.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Real-time Feedback:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Provide feedback as developers type to preemptively address runtime or compilation errors.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>UX and First Impressions:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Positive experiences involve quick installation, rapid problem resolution, comprehensive APIs, and efficient information retrieval.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>DX Mindset:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Establish a DX vision and principles.</li>
<li class="">Measure DX success.</li>
<li class="">Implement DX in tools and journey maps.</li>
<li class="">Continuously refine and improve DX maturity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Implementation Strategies:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Focus on the first five minutes and the solid 100th day.</li>
<li class="">Aim for zero friction and high speed.</li>
<li class="">Leverage build automation and opinionated tooling.</li>
<li class="">Engage in understanding developer needs.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Developer Relations (DevRel):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Take DX to the community.</li>
<li class="">Act as the first customer to validate APIs and libraries.</li>
<li class="">Listen to community feedback and address questions.</li>
<li class="">Create comprehensive documentation, samples, and blog posts.</li>
<li class="">Manage local and online communities through active interactions.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>Types of Developer Journeys:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Frequent and important journeys.</li>
<li class="">Infrequent yet crucial journeys.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><strong>DX Journey Touchpoints:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="">Discover: Utilize social platforms, events, blogs, newsletters, and case studies.</li>
<li class="">Evaluate: Prioritize a well-designed docs landing page and FAQs.</li>
<li class="">Learn: Provide quick start guides, code samples, and tutorials.</li>
<li class="">Build: Offer sandboxes, reference guides, and change logs.</li>
<li class="">Scale: Focus on developer success and showcase implementations.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/17#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>In conclusion, Addy Osmani's concise book serves as a thought-provoking summary that ignites the discourse around DX. As the software development landscape continues to evolve, embracing a DX-focused mindset and implementing the strategies outlined in this book can pave the way for a more efficient and enjoyable development experience. The fire of DX has been lit, and it's poised to spread across the development community.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Learn to Win Arguments and Succeed 20 Powerful Techniques to Never Lose an Argument again, with Real Life Examples. A Life Skill for Everyone by Vishal Gupta]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/16</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/16</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Book talk on Learn to Win Arguments and Succeed 20 Powerful Techniques to Never Lose an Argument again, with Real Life Examples. A Life Skill for Everyone by Vishal Gupta]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="&amp;quot;Learn to Win Arguments and Succeed by Vishal Gupta&amp;quot;" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/win-arguments-cbfbbb2a3ff5cf8a8929b7e0483aa2b7.webp" width="400" height="618" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Arguments often have a bad reputation, associated with raised voices, negative emotions, and anger. We tend to avoid them, viewing them as something to be steered clear of. After all, arguments are typically reserved for courtrooms and formal debates, right? Well, not quite. Vishal Gupta, an engineer and a criminal side lawyer, believes that mastering the art of argumentation is a life skill that everyone should cultivate. In his book, "Learn to Win Arguments and Succeed," Gupta sheds light on how to engage in constructive, persuasive arguments that help you convey your viewpoint effectively.</p>
<p>Here are three valuable takeaways from the book that anyone can use to enhance their argumentative skills:</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="1-proverbs-less-is-more">1. Proverbs: Less is More<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/16#1-proverbs-less-is-more" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. Proverbs: Less is More" title="Direct link to 1. Proverbs: Less is More" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Proverbs have held a special place in our society for centuries. Instead of using a multitude of words to make your point, proverbs condense wisdom into succinct phrases. Take, for example, the timeless adage, "as you sow, so shall you reap." This simple proverb can be a powerful tool to persuade someone to take responsibility for their actions. By utilizing such wisdom, you can make your arguments more concise and compelling.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="2-repeat-repeat-repeat">2. Repeat, Repeat, Repeat<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/16#2-repeat-repeat-repeat" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Repeat, Repeat, Repeat" title="Direct link to 2. Repeat, Repeat, Repeat" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Some arguments can be grueling, particularly when the stakes are high. Picture a scenario where someone has damaged your motorcycle and is falsely accusing you of mistakes. Instead of getting lost in the chaos of defending yourself against every accusation, Gupta suggests a different approach: repetition. By consistently and calmly repeating your strong defense, you can guide the conversation toward a resolution. Repetition can help your opponent notice and, ultimately, accept their mistake.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="3-loaded-words-the-power-of-emotion">3. Loaded Words: The Power of Emotion<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/16#3-loaded-words-the-power-of-emotion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 3. Loaded Words: The Power of Emotion" title="Direct link to 3. Loaded Words: The Power of Emotion" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>In the art of persuasion, emotions play a crucial role. Loaded words, as Vishal Gupta explains, are terms or phrases that carry strong emotional connotations. These words are designed to sway opinions, evoke emotions, and manipulate the audience in various ways. For instance, instead of using plain language to accuse someone of their mistake, try employing loaded language to vividly illustrate their error. Words like "injustice" can evoke a profound sense of unfairness, making your argument more emotionally resonant.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="summary">Summary<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/16#summary" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Summary" title="Direct link to Summary" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>"Learn to Win Arguments and Succeed" is a must-read for anyone who encounters situations where persuasive skills matter, be it at work, in relationships, or elsewhere. The book offers a comprehensive set of techniques and strategies that can help you emerge victorious in debates while preserving respect and understanding in interpersonal relationships. Vishal Gupta's experience as an engineer and a lawyer makes him a credible source to guide readers through the art of argumentation. So, next time you hear someone say, "Don't argue with me," you'll be better equipped to navigate the discussion with finesse and persuasion. This book teaches you that arguments can be constructive, and mastering this skill is essential for everyone.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Making money in stocks - simplified by Aditya Shroff]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/15</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/15</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Book talk on making money in stocks - simplified by Aditya Shroff]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="&amp;quot;Making money in stocks - simplified by Aditya Shroff&amp;quot;" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/making-money-simplified-8aa3e8786e049579b6d7f7631ef206ad.jpg" width="326" height="500" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>We all have friends with different financial backgrounds. Some are already financially savvy, while others aspire to be. Aditya Shroff's book is tailored for the latter group, those who wish to elevate their financial literacy and carefully invest their hard-earned money.</p>
<p>Today, I want to introduce you to a book that bridges the gap between financial novices and seasoned investors, bringing the world of stocks closer to your fingertips. "Making Money in Stocks - Simplified" by Aditya Shroff is a treasure trove of financial wisdom.</p>
<p>Aditya Shroff, a seasoned Indian fund manager, is your guide in this journey. He takes you on a captivating exploration of the Indian stock market's highs and lows, offering insights in a conversational style that makes complex financial concepts feel accessible.</p>
<p>What sets this book apart is its ability to make financial concepts engaging. Through the conversations of three individuals, with one wise investor guiding the others, the content becomes a pleasure to read. The timeless investment strategies discussed within can be applied for many years to come.</p>
<p>A standout idea in the book is the "Identification of Economic Cycles." This advanced-level content helps investors build robust portfolios by understanding which sectors thrive during each phase of the economic cycle.</p>
<p>"Making Money in Stocks - Simplified" by Aditya Shroff is a must-have for your bookshelf. It's the perfect reference when you're analyzing stocks, making the world of finance more accessible and exciting. So, if you're looking to step up your financial game, this book is your essential guide. Happy investing!</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Stolen Focus - Why You Can't Pay Attention And How to Think Deeply Again by Johann Hari, self help genre]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/14</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/14</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2023 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on Why You Can't Pay Attention And How to Think Deeply Again by Johann Hari]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="&amp;quot;Stolen Focus Why You Can&amp;#39;t Pay Attention--And How to Think Deeply Again by Johann Hari&amp;quot;" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/stolen-focus-60db6522e3217130b651d8847fb62cdc.webp" width="329" height="499" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p><strong>Unlocking Creativity and Productivity: Insights from a Comprehensive Study on Focus</strong></p>
<p>In a substantial volume of 368 pages, an author of esteemed journalistic background delves into a subject of paramount significance for individuals of artistic inclinations - the art of focus. This book represents an impressive departure from the author's previous works which tackled weighty topics such as drugs, addiction, and depression. Meticulously researched, the book is an eloquent piece of literature that draws its insights from interviews with preeminent experts in the realm of memory management.</p>
<p>Within the pages of this enlightening work, three pivotal concepts stand out, offering readers invaluable insights into the realm of focus and its intricate interplay with various facets of modern life:</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-symbiotic-dance-between-the-author-and-the-web-a-discourse-on-the-significance-of-flow">The Symbiotic Dance Between the Author and the Web: A Discourse on the Significance of Flow<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/14#the-symbiotic-dance-between-the-author-and-the-web-a-discourse-on-the-significance-of-flow" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Symbiotic Dance Between the Author and the Web: A Discourse on the Significance of Flow" title="Direct link to The Symbiotic Dance Between the Author and the Web: A Discourse on the Significance of Flow" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The author expounds upon a personal transformation where he purposefully disentangles himself from the ensnaring tendrils of the web, mobile phones, and the internet at large, all in an earnest endeavor to enrich his focus and reclaim moments in a serene coastal town. By relinquishing the constant companionship of his phone and severing the digital umbilical cord, he experiences a profound transformation within himself. However, his epiphany lies in the realization that the absence of digital devices is not the sole catalyst for enhancing focus; rather, it is the pursuit of activities that facilitate a state of flow which emerges as the linchpin for heightened concentration.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="navigating-the-labyrinth-of-technical-distractions-unmasking-the-intricacies-of-surveillance-capitalism">Navigating the Labyrinth of Technical Distractions: Unmasking the Intricacies of Surveillance Capitalism<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/14#navigating-the-labyrinth-of-technical-distractions-unmasking-the-intricacies-of-surveillance-capitalism" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Navigating the Labyrinth of Technical Distractions: Unmasking the Intricacies of Surveillance Capitalism" title="Direct link to Navigating the Labyrinth of Technical Distractions: Unmasking the Intricacies of Surveillance Capitalism" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>As anticipated in a treatise devoted to the reinvigoration of focus, the discourse encompasses a contemplation on the role of applications and technology. The author astutely illuminates the strategies employed by these apps to captivate our attention, laying bare the intricate machinations of a phenomenon dubbed 'surveillance capitalism,' wherein the behemoths of commerce exploit our online presence to amass considerable fortunes. A countermeasure against this contemporary conundrum is proposed - a judicious utilization of the 'do not disturb' mode as a means to reclaim our cognitive space.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="unveiling-the-culprits-diet-pollution-and-pharmaceuticals">Unveiling the Culprits: Diet, Pollution, and Pharmaceuticals<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/14#unveiling-the-culprits-diet-pollution-and-pharmaceuticals" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Unveiling the Culprits: Diet, Pollution, and Pharmaceuticals" title="Direct link to Unveiling the Culprits: Diet, Pollution, and Pharmaceuticals" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The author, in his meticulous exploration, unearths an intriguing nexus between dietary habits, environmental factors, and pharmaceutical interventions, particularly as they relate to the burgeoning malady of hyperactivity disorders, notably ADHD. The narrative sheds light on the deleterious consequences of crash diets, elucidating how volatile fluctuations in blood sugar levels engender hyperactivity, ultimately precipitating the manifestation of Attention Disorder and Hyperactivity Disease. A trenchant observation regarding the use of certain additives in soft drinks, recognized culprits in inducing hyperactivity among children, is presented. The dichotomy between the regulatory stances of Europe and the United States on these additives is scrutinized, leaving the reader with much to ponder.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="concluding-reflections-fostering-a-focus-friendly-society">Concluding Reflections: Fostering a Focus-Friendly Society<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/14#concluding-reflections-fostering-a-focus-friendly-society" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Concluding Reflections: Fostering a Focus-Friendly Society" title="Direct link to Concluding Reflections: Fostering a Focus-Friendly Society" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>In synthesis, the book posits focus as an indispensable linchpin in the tapestry of achievement, an attribute transcending individual guilt and transmogrifying into a collective societal responsibility. The narrative underscores the imperative of shaping our technological infrastructure and urban landscapes to harmoniously coexist with our intrinsic need for focused contemplation. By shedding the mantle of self-reproach for moments of diverted attention, and instead orchestrating a collaborative endeavor to cultivate focus-conducive environments, we embark upon a journey toward the zenith of creativity and productivity.</p>
<p>In this thought-provoking volume, the interplay between the individual and the digital realm, the machinations of technology, and the intricate dance of external factors converge to furnish readers with a roadmap to unlock the potential of focus - a veritable treasure trove for creative souls seeking to navigate the labyrinth of modern distractions and harness the true essence of their cognitive prowess.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mindful Zen Habits by Mark Reklau, self help genre]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/13</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/13</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on Mindful Zen Habits by Mark Reklau]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="&amp;quot;Mindful Zen Habits by Mark Reklau&amp;quot;" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/mindful-zen-habits-c021b8abd06680116e5e291a50d475ed.webp" width="390" height="600" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>In the realm of non-fiction literature, the self-help genre stands as the most sought-after category. However, making a meaningful impact within this genre can be a challenging endeavor for authors. Mark Reklau's book, "Mindful Zen Habits," rises to this challenge, offering readers a formal and informative exploration of self-improvement principles.</p>
<p>Key Insights from the Book:</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="emphasizing-the-value-of-periodic-evaluation">Emphasizing the Value of Periodic Evaluation:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/13#emphasizing-the-value-of-periodic-evaluation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Emphasizing the Value of Periodic Evaluation:" title="Direct link to Emphasizing the Value of Periodic Evaluation:" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Reklau advocates the significance of setting specific key performance indicators (KPIs) for our goals and regularly assessing our progress toward them. By transforming aspirations into tangible written goals, the likelihood of attainment increases substantially, distinguishing a sincere commitment from mere wishful thinking.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="embracing-sadness-as-part-of-lifes-tapestry">Embracing Sadness as Part of Life's Tapestry:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/13#embracing-sadness-as-part-of-lifes-tapestry" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Embracing Sadness as Part of Life's Tapestry:" title="Direct link to Embracing Sadness as Part of Life's Tapestry:" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The author shines a light on the deceptive narrative propagated by consumerism, promoting an illusion of constant happiness. Reklau reminds readers that it is perfectly normal to experience moments of sadness which suppresses grief. By acknowledging and accepting sadness, individuals can navigate life's challenges with greater resilience.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="slowing-down-to-foster-intellectual-growth">Slowing Down to Foster Intellectual Growth:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/13#slowing-down-to-foster-intellectual-growth" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Slowing Down to Foster Intellectual Growth:" title="Direct link to Slowing Down to Foster Intellectual Growth:" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>In today's fast-paced world, a perpetual sense of hurry permeates our lives. Reklau cautions against the inherent risks of haste, urging us to take the time to truly listen to others. By refraining from rushing through tasks and instead adopting a systematic approach, we create space for intellectual growth and develop empathy for those around us.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="conclusion">Conclusion:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/13#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion:" title="Direct link to Conclusion:" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Mark Reklau's "Mindful Zen Habits" presents a refreshing perspective, free from cultural biases, and offers a treasure trove of transformative habits that can lead to a successful life. As the author wisely states, "Do not rely solely on self-discipline; instead, make positive habits a cornerstone of your journey." By incorporating the wisdom and practical insights shared within this book, readers can embark on a meaningful path of self-improvement, ultimately shaping a more purposeful and fulfilling existence</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Lets talk mutual funds by Monika Halan, personal finance genre]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/12</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/12</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2023 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on Lets talk mutual funds by Monika Halan]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="&amp;quot;Lets talk mutual fund by Monika Halan&amp;quot;" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/lets-talk-mutual-fund-6b8521c9edefe7faa2e89e4cf123b776.webp" width="450" height="800" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>In today's world, it has become commonplace for finance books to be authored by young influencers in their 20s. However, amid this trend, we witness the rare occurrence of true financial expertise in the form of Monika Halan, a seasoned finance professional. In her latest book, Monika delves into the realm of tried and tested mutual funds, following the success of her first book, "Let's Talk Money."</p>
<p>Highlighted Concepts:</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="unraveling-the-complexity-of-mutual-fund-categories-for-retail-investors">Unraveling the Complexity of Mutual Fund Categories for Retail Investors:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/12#unraveling-the-complexity-of-mutual-fund-categories-for-retail-investors" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Unraveling the Complexity of Mutual Fund Categories for Retail Investors:" title="Direct link to Unraveling the Complexity of Mutual Fund Categories for Retail Investors:" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Monika Halan adeptly navigates the intricate landscape of mutual funds, offering valuable insights to retail investors. With a focus on two primary categories, namely equity and debt funds, she systematically outlines the various subcategories that often bewilder investors. By demystifying options like large &amp; mid-cap funds, multi-cap funds, and tax saver funds within equity, as well as liquid funds and money market funds within debt, Halan empowers readers to make informed decisions. Moreover, she advocates for the adoption of direct mutual funds to optimize investment outcomes.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="identifying-the-eaters-of-your-invested-money">Identifying the Eaters of Your Invested Money:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/12#identifying-the-eaters-of-your-invested-money" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Identifying the Eaters of Your Invested Money:" title="Direct link to Identifying the Eaters of Your Invested Money:" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The author highlights the significant forces that diminish the potential growth of invested funds: inflation, taxes, and costs. To truly prosper, an investment must outpace these erosive factors. Halan emphasizes the importance of generating interest, dividends, and profits to ensure fruitful investments, making it essential for investors to strategize wisely.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="emphasizing-the-significance-of-asset-allocation">Emphasizing the Significance of Asset Allocation:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/12#emphasizing-the-significance-of-asset-allocation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Emphasizing the Significance of Asset Allocation:" title="Direct link to Emphasizing the Significance of Asset Allocation:" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>One of the most critical aspects of financial management is asset allocation, which empowers retail investors to exert control over their portfolios. While market conditions remain beyond an investor's influence, Monika Halan accentuates the impact of asset allocation in achieving not only profitability but also maintaining liquidity for future needs. This prudent approach allows investors to navigate uncertainties with a well-balanced and diversified portfolio.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="conclusion">Conclusion:<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/12#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion:" title="Direct link to Conclusion:" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Monika Halan's latest offering proves to be a compelling and gripping sequel, solidifying her position as a trustworthy guide for retail investors. Her expertise and knowledge shine through as she simplifies complex financial concepts, making them accessible to readers from all walks of life. For those seeking to enhance their financial acumen and optimize investment strategies, this book is an indispensable read. Monika Halan continues to inspire and empower individuals on their journey towards financial prosperity, and her latest work stands as a testament to her enduring commitment to financial education and literacy.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Stock Market Investing for Beginners Essentials to Start Investing Successfully by Tycho Press]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on Stock Market Investing for Beginners Essentials to Start Investing Successfully by Tycho Press]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/stock-market-investing-7d5bf6235309523903b92f0ddca42b6f.webp" width="317" height="475" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>My last book talk was on the topic of minimalism at home. As an effect of minimalism, we are going to save money and gain minimalism dividends.</p>
<p>Extending those lines, we are going to discuss another book on the topic of money. It's about stock market investing for beginners by Tacho press.</p>
<p>I remember this vividly, ever since I started watching the news on the television. There will be a 1-minute bulletin showing the Bombay stock exchange and just sharing the BSE Sensex numbers and the remaining 25 minutes for news.</p>
<p>I come from a country where financial literacy with technology is not widespread. Most Indians still rely on agents to walk into the door and pitch financial products.</p>
<p>Ask any Indian home about the stock market, they would say that it's a sure-shot way to lose money. That's because the stock market is not a place where your ambitions are respected, it's a place where process, research, and hard work are respected.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Losing money on taxes should not be the only reason why you should not sell profitable stocks after many years of holding them.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="why-read-this-book">Why read this book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11#why-read-this-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why read this book" title="Direct link to Why read this book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>This book helps you put the leg in the door of the stock market. The book talks at length about three main concepts and a lot of questions for beginners.</p>
<p>The book does not give stock calls or techniques. This book is mostly theoretical and filled with general advice.
Some topics from the fundamental and technical analysis are touched upon.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>10 hours of portfolio management per week shows poor time management. Spending less than an hour per week is foolishness.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-author">About the author<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11#about-the-author" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the author" title="Direct link to About the author" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Frankly speaking, there isn't a face behind the book or a page thanking mother/wife, etc. This book is published by a corporate author. That's all we know.</p>
<p>This is good in one way because we do not have to emphatize with their anecdotes. We can read the facts and go ahead.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="top-ideas-from-the-book">Top ideas from the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11#top-ideas-from-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Top ideas from the book" title="Direct link to Top ideas from the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="access-the-stock-from-3-angles">Access the stock from 3 angles<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11#access-the-stock-from-3-angles" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Access the stock from 3 angles" title="Direct link to Access the stock from 3 angles" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Valuation - undervalue stocks preferred</li>
<li class="">Growth - check the past 5 quarters' growth</li>
<li class="">Profitability - check the profitability of the business and compare it with the industry</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>news is a part of the stock investing game</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="selecting-stocks">Selecting stocks<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11#selecting-stocks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Selecting stocks" title="Direct link to Selecting stocks" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Identify a sector where you have some knowledge</li>
<li class="">Select 10 stocks in the sector</li>
<li class="">Perform valuation analysis</li>
<li class="">Perform growth and profit analysis</li>
<li class="">Remove bad apples from the rest. You would have identified 1 or 2 good stocks out of 10.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Believe in what you read, now what you hear</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="diversification">Diversification<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11#diversification" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Diversification" title="Direct link to Diversification" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Buy multiple stocks -holding 25 to 35 stocks is not the only sign of diversification</li>
<li class="">Buy from at least 6 sectors</li>
<li class="">Buy different types of investments like bonds, stocks, etc</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>If all stocks are falling, you need not be concerned. If only one stock is falling while others are moving up, then we have a problem.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="finding-the-percentage-of-stocks-and-bonds">Finding the percentage of stocks and bonds<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11#finding-the-percentage-of-stocks-and-bonds" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Finding the percentage of stocks and bonds" title="Direct link to Finding the percentage of stocks and bonds" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Minus your age of 110, that should be your stocks and the remaining is bonds. A 40-year-old can have 70% stocks and 30% bonds</li>
<li class="">If you are wealthy, you can bump up stocks allocation another 5%</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="ideas-i-do-not-agree-with">Ideas I do not agree with<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11#ideas-i-do-not-agree-with" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ideas I do not agree with" title="Direct link to Ideas I do not agree with" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Most of the book is based on factual information, there are no personal viewpoints of the author that I disagree with.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/11#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Most young Indians approach the stock market with the mindset of making 1% to 10% percent returns every month. They make a lot of trades and no wonder they make big losses in the first 5 years.</p>
<p>This book does one thing really well. It gives you pointers that act like guard rails so that you can approach the stock market and make money safely. It's a recommended read even for intermediate-level stock market professionals.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A stock market beginner should not do a lot of trades.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Minimalist Home by Joshua Becker]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on The Minimalist Home by Joshua Becker.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/the-minimalist-home-3c74bc410050e2d7a2d403689e8662f8.webp" width="1688" height="2550" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>I have been reading books about all things that matter in life. This is the first book about the most important place on earth "The Home". Each one's home is unique and I am going to talk about this book from a working-class person living in India.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Home is a place for rest &amp; focus. Find alignment between purpose &amp; possession in life.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-author">About the author<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10#about-the-author" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the author" title="Direct link to About the author" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The author is a minimalist guru and a staunch advocate of minimalism. If you are going to search for the word minimalist on any search engine or social media platform, you might run into the works of Joshua Becker. He has written multiple books on the topic of minimalism.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Goals shape us, goals change us</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of the ideas from his previous books which I follow meticulously is <code>remove duplicates</code>. Have 2 towels instead of 5. Wash the blankets and use them within the same day. You do not need to maintain multiple blankets.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="why-minimalism">Why minimalism<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10#why-minimalism" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why minimalism" title="Direct link to Why minimalism" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Prioritize extra time in hand and extra money in your pocket over extra things in the closet.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wanted you to observe the people around you. Some of them are super focussed on the things they do and deterministic about the things they own. While a vast majority of them are otherwise. If you lift your head and observe some legendary people like Steve Jobs &amp; Mahatma Gandhi, they were leading a minimalist life. They were spearheaded about the mission of their life. Both Steve Jobs &amp; Gandhi were not popular because they wore fancy dresses/clothing most of the time. They did not own fancy homes but the outcome of their work and the value they brought to the world is immeasurable.</p>
<p>In success literature, it's a trend to observe and reverse engineer the qualities of successful people or reverse the trend which is followed by the masses. In this context <code>minimalism</code> has hit a niche market and there is a good amount of education, adoption, and evangelism available out there.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You are bound by home instead of being freed by home.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let's answer the <code>why</code>, Minimalism is a philosophy so it's hard to punch in a scientific definition of minimalism. Minimalism is about focusing on things that matter to you and your goal in life. A minimalist tries to turn his surroundings, tools, and thoughts toward the main goal in life.</p>
<p>Let's observe Steve Jobs, he believed in good design. According to Jobs, design is not how it looks but how it works. His car, dress, office, products, and entire life were obsessively driven by design instead of being missold to random ideas or whims of the market. Nevertheless, he achieved great things in life.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Reimagine the environment around the goals in life.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="top-ideas-from-the-book">Top ideas from the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10#top-ideas-from-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Top ideas from the book" title="Direct link to Top ideas from the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The book is written around the topic of "Home". The author prescribes how to approach each room as a minimalist. Of course, if you were to follow this book. You might expect trouble from your family or roommates and the author has written about that too.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If your house does not have a basement, then your bed storage is your basement.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="stuff-problem">Stuff problem<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10#stuff-problem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Stuff problem" title="Direct link to Stuff problem" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Once in a while, Indian moms yell at their children for bringing home something useless. But the child feels it's the best thing they could buy in their life. As a grown-up adult, I purchased a few things which I am not proud of like expensive home gym equipment which was not used at all. My mom complained right on the day of purchase and even showed me alternates like running or using body weight. Let's say I did not have a mom and I go binge shopping. I would be left with 10 items sitting on the floor because they did not have a shelf to sit on all the time. My room would turn into a cave with all sorts of things that I do not use. That's exactly what the author calls out as a stuff problem.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you have nice things to impress your friends, then you got the wrong friends.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>People with stuff problems have trouble with shifting homes, spending more time on the upkeep and lastly, they cannot say where their things are. They keep misplacing things and spend a lot of time searching for them. Simple things like walking in the dark are not easy because they have stuff sitting on the floor. I have personally seen some Indian homes where the guests can clearly call out as a mess. Some guests would even give advice like "why don't you clear the textbooks from school which are stacked up on the floor in a corner of the room?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Nothing on the floor except 4 pieces of furniture per room.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="minimalism-dividend">Minimalism dividend<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10#minimalism-dividend" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Minimalism dividend" title="Direct link to Minimalism dividend" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>If you were given a chance to go back in time and were given a full refund for exchanging all the things you emotionally bought, how would more extra cash you would have? You would definitely have more money today. Imagine if you had invested correctly instead of buying things, that investment would have given you dividends.</p>
<p>If the above advice sounds too strict, hear it out. As a minimalist, you will buy things and some of your purchases might end up as clutter. But compared to a normal soul who is spending on things and loading his house with 30,000 items, you are doing much better.</p>
<p>Do not go by what advertisers call it out as trend-like colors to wear this summer etc. By not falling into consumerism, you avoid debts. This is an advantage of being a minimalist and this is what the author calls a "Minimalism Dividend" just like stock dividends.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Refusal to buy things that waste money and take up clutter pays you minimalist dividends.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="do-not-relocate-items">Do not relocate items<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10#do-not-relocate-items" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Do not relocate items" title="Direct link to Do not relocate items" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Most of us have done this. Let's say you purchased a flower vase thinking you would decorate it with beautiful flowers once a week. But as time goes by, the flower's cost and upkeep make you wonder if it's worth it. In that case, you accept the defeat and pack the vase and relocate the vase from display to a box in the basement. The Indian version is "top shelf of the room or below the bed". That's it, you forget and move on but that item is still sitting somewhere and adding to the clutter count.</p>
<p>Instead, the author recommends you donate or sell it at a garage sale. The Indian equivalent of a garage sale is <code>olx</code>. Either use the item or discard it. Before you discard it, run it through a small checklist like if your family member would get angry, when did you last use it? etc.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="ideas-i-do-not-agree-with">Ideas I do not agree with<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10#ideas-i-do-not-agree-with" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ideas I do not agree with" title="Direct link to Ideas I do not agree with" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>At the shopping mall or supermarket, the things we buy fall into 2 categories. They are <code>Consumables</code> &amp; <code>Durables</code>. The <code>Consumables</code> are food items, natural flowers, etc. The <code>Durables</code> are books, toys, and furniture. The author recommends buying consumables instead of durables as the consumables are spent for experiences but later bought for future use.</p>
<p>I like what the author says. Sometimes the books we do not start reading the books we read but we hold it thinking we will read them someday. The same with the DSLR camera which we bought. The authors advocate renting durables.</p>
<p>Having said that it's a noble idea to vote for consumables but not all consumables are safe. What if someone buys an addictive substance because he is not going to spend on durable? It's a possibility.</p>
<p>The Indian version would be to ask your mom/spouse to supervise the money for you. It works most of the time.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For investments, contact an advisor. For spending, you need a regulator.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/10#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Overall the book is an intermediate-level read where the reader is supposed to read and make changes not just to himself but to the lifestyle of the family. The goals of each room and the refusal to buy things that do not bring value or simply clutter are absolutely great ideas to explore at a young age.</p>
<p>If you are someone who walks with a plan, integrates parts of your life by design, and is willing to be counter-cultured, this book is for you. I will leave you with a quote from the book which I believe is so true.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Picture your dream home in mind, I bet it's not filled with clutter</p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[48 hour start-up formula, from idea to launch in 1 weekend by Fraser Doherty MBE]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/9</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/9</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on 48 hour start-up formula, from idea to launch in 1 weekend by Fraser Doherty MBE.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/48-hour-startup-817ba71f3d20bb776cd438f3f5727bed.webp" width="1994" height="2903" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>The first day of 2023 was spent on the couch with this book titled "48-hour start-up formula, from idea to launch in 1 weekend by Fraser Doherty MBE" in my hand.</p>
<p>The book falls in the <code>Business</code> genre. This genre is notorious for being tough to read, having way too theoretical ideas, beating the drum aka success literature, etc without any actionable items or take away for audiences. This book differs from the tough business books by staying up to date with the current omnichannel market strategy.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-author">About the author<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/9#about-the-author" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the author" title="Direct link to About the author" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The author describes his childhood vividly in the book, He was an enthusiastic child who wants to make money by selling very early as a school-going kid. In this process, he learns everything practically.</p>
<p>Over the period, he makes his success mark with a product called <code>SuperJam</code> which is a product developed with his talented grandma in their kitchen and sold door to door in the initial days. Later the product is put on supermarket shelves and it goes on to make a successful international brand.</p>
<p>The author is well qualified to write a book on startups and launching products. Given his practical learning, the author refrains from ideas that lead to analysis paralysis.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="top-3-ideas-from-the-book">Top 3 ideas from the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/9#top-3-ideas-from-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Top 3 ideas from the book" title="Direct link to Top 3 ideas from the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="usp-is-dead">USP is dead.<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/9#usp-is-dead" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to USP is dead." title="Direct link to USP is dead." translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>While finding the perfect idea for our startup, we were told to focus on something unique and not another copy product. But in reality, the real world is full of copy products which are a little different here and there. Maybe better, faster, cheaper, etc.</p>
<p>When there is no USP, we have to come to terms with people who are going to copy your product in parts or as a whole. In that case, the story behind the product is unique to each product and can be a strong anchor point in the customer's mind.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="be-second-first">Be second, first<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/9#be-second-first" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Be second, first" title="Direct link to Be second, first" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>The first mover advantage is great but the first mover has to experiment a lot with his time and money. He has to have a research team to learn about the market. After all this hard work, the chances of the first mover's success are very less compared to the guy who learned from a successful product, made reasonable changes, and sold it.</p>
<p>Someone who starts second has a 75% less chance of failing. This is a perfect example of the commodities/items at the supermarket.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-middle-of-the-road-pricing-is-dangerous">The middle of the road pricing is dangerous<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/9#the-middle-of-the-road-pricing-is-dangerous" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The middle of the road pricing is dangerous" title="Direct link to The middle of the road pricing is dangerous" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>The author discusses the 4P while developing an idea.</p>
<ol>
<li class="">P - Product, what am I selling</li>
<li class="">P - Promotion, how will I let the world know that the product exists</li>
<li class="">P - Place, where will my customers find me</li>
<li class="">P - Price, at what price can I get customers and make a profit</li>
</ol>
<p>When it comes to pricing, the improvised products take the middle road. They choose to place the price somewhere between the minimum and maximum. This technique is risky because the competition is intense and everyone is doing the same. The companies in the middle are on the decline. However, the space at the minimum and maximum has less competition and more profits.</p>
<p>For instance, Uber, Ryan Air, and Amazon are capturing low-end markets. Companies like Apple and Tesla are capturing high-end markets.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="something-i-do-not-agree-with">Something I do not agree with<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/9#something-i-do-not-agree-with" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Something I do not agree with" title="Direct link to Something I do not agree with" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Well, I agree with the ideas in the book. But planning something new minute by minute to be executed on a weekend comes at a cost. It means no time for weekend chores and I bet someone will distract us over the weekend unless you do all of this sitting in a private office.</p>
<p>The author emphasizes the importance of focused work and being in a great moment. Only through focus, the author tells with conviction that you can build your startup in 48 hours</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/9#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The book is written on an important topic that could change your fate and live the life of your dreams. The author has given his best at writing the book by loading it with the latest and greatest tools that he uses or found on the internet. A must-read for entrepreneurial-minded people.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ADAPTIVE WEB DESIGN Crafting Rich Experiences with Progressive Enhancement by Aaron Gustafson]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/8</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/8</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on ADAPTIVE WEB DESIGN Crafting Rich Experiences with Progressive Enhancement by Aaron Gustafson]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/adaptive-web-design-291368bc8221e9be32ea2e0e9f79f5c0.webp" width="586" height="872" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Written in 2013, a book on adaptive web design and how to do it with progressive enhancement. The title of the book might sound mouth full but let's look into it in parts.</p>
<p>Adaptive web design is the elder kin of responsive web design (RWD), Read more about <a href="https://xd.adobe.com/ideas/process/ui-design/adaptive-design-vs-responsive-design/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">RWD vs Adaptive web design</a>. In the context of the book, the book is a how-to literature on how to do adaptive web design. The main technique that was discussed was `progressive enhancement.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="top-ideas-from-the-book">Top ideas from the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/8#top-ideas-from-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Top ideas from the book" title="Direct link to Top ideas from the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Think of the user, not the browser</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="progressive-enhancement">Progressive enhancement<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/8#progressive-enhancement" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Progressive enhancement" title="Direct link to Progressive enhancement" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Progressive enhancement - the gold standard of how to approach the web. It's aimed at crafting experiences that serve the users by giving them access to content without technological restrictions.</p>
<p>Progressive enhancement relies on fault tolerance. A system can operate when it encounters an unexpected error.</p>
<p>Browsers play by the rules of fault tolerance and ignore anything they did not understand. Fault tolerance has been a part of HTML and CSS since the beginning. They are forever forward-compatible.</p>
<p>We all have special needs, and progressive enhancement wins.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="tools-for-progressive-enhancement">Tools for Progressive Enhancement<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/8#tools-for-progressive-enhancement" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Tools for Progressive Enhancement" title="Direct link to Tools for Progressive Enhancement" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>HTML and CSS are ideal tools for progressive enhancement. Javascript is not fault-tolerant, it breaks with an error. If the user turns off Javascript, the user is shown a blank white screen most of the time.</p>
<p>An ideal developer will have to check before executing JS and JS APIs.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="helping-assistive-tech-with-aria">Helping assistive tech with ARIA<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/8#helping-assistive-tech-with-aria" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Helping assistive tech with ARIA" title="Direct link to Helping assistive tech with ARIA" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>A gentle empathetic introduction to ARIA is always welcome. The book discusses</p>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p><code>aria</code> states</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><code>aria</code> roles</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p><code>tab index</code></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/8#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>A light read written in 2013. The world has moved towards working and testing apps on browsers with major browser share. The book reminds us of the importance of building sites/apps for past and upcoming technologies. After a long time, I was able to weigh in progressive enhancement vs graceful degradation. Overall an interesting light read.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Browsers ignore anything they do not understand</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The above line could be applied to life too!</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Web for Everyone Designing Accessible User Experiences by Sarah Horton, Whitney Quesenbery]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/7</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/7</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on Designing Accessible User Experiences by Sarah Horton, Whitney Quesenbery]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/web-for-everyone-94d176c8e1674ea60c719a742a9ef6c1.webp" width="622" height="805" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Equality on the web is an interesting and important topic. This is the second book related to accessibility.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="who-should-read-the-book">Who should read the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/7#who-should-read-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Who should read the book" title="Direct link to Who should read the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Books on accessibility relate to design or coding. This book relates to 80% of design and 20% of coding. If you are beginning with accessibility, then this book is the right fit.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-author">About the author<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/7#about-the-author" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the author" title="Direct link to About the author" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The author is well exposed to accessibility and the web. Sarah Horton is an expert from whom we want to learn and understand accessibility design.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://sarahhortondesign.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="">Sarah Horton Website</a></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="top-ideas-from-the-book">Top ideas from the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/7#top-ideas-from-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Top ideas from the book" title="Direct link to Top ideas from the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li class="">The personas of the disabled people</li>
</ol>
<p>Generally, books categorize people with disability and stop there. But the authors take this issue description in a well-recognized technical language called <code>Personas</code>. The persona description and images of the users illustrate to the readers about the user. This is important because all our lives we are not exposed to disabled people to a major degree.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li class="">Equations to simplify ideas</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>Ability + Barrier = Disability</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The barrier is to be broken with technology. For example, if a user has bad vision then we need to help them consume our content with a screen magnifier or screen reader. Web content should be accessible to the disabled audience</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/7#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The book is intense literature. As a front-end developer, I could understand the design process and a gentle introduction to WCAG 2.0. This book stands out with personas about disabled people. It helps you to empathize with disabled people.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Universal Principles of Design By William Lidwell, Kritina Holden & Jill Butler]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/6</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/6</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2022 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on Universal Principles of Design By William Lidwell, Kritina Holden & Jill Butler]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/universal-design-79c8cfbff4cda2b0fff5659d13786bc0.webp" width="427" height="500" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Design is a subjective topic and point of debate in several corporate meetings. The debate happens due to <code>Cognitive Dissonance</code>, <code>exposure effect</code> &amp; <code>consistency bias</code>. But wait, the last 3 terms are common in the design world and are universal to design. This book does not talk about how to design an app but this book helps you take an insider view of design, processes, and patterns in design.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-style-of-writing">About the style of writing<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/6#about-the-style-of-writing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the style of writing" title="Direct link to About the style of writing" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>This book is a short read, something you can read on a short plane. The book is written for beginners and the average joe who encounters design in his life. The audience could be software developers or marketing or someone who makes ad films.</p>
<p>The book has around 105 topics which are spread around 5 topics like perception, learning, usability, appeal, and design decisions.</p>
<p>The left side of the book has a short theory of the topic, and the right side of the book has real-life examples of the design topic.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-author">About the author<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/6#about-the-author" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the author" title="Direct link to About the author" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The authors hold eminent positions in various firms and institutes. Their intention is applaudable, and that is to help normal folks understand universal design principles with ease.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="best-parts-of-the-book">Best parts of the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/6#best-parts-of-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Best parts of the book" title="Direct link to Best parts of the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>As I am a software developer, here are a few topics that I liked from the book</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Accessibility</li>
</ul>
<p>Objects and environments should be designed to be used without modification, by as many people as possible.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Development cycle</li>
</ul>
<p>Successful products typically follow four stages of creation: requirements, design, development, and testing. All products progress sequentially through the basic stages of creation.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">
<p>Requirements - gathered through market research, customer feedback, etc. Design requirements are derived from direct knowledge or experience</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Design - the stage where design requirements are translated into a form that yields a set of specifications. Excellent design is usually accomplished through careful research of existing or analogous solutions, ample use of prototyping, and many iterations of trying.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Development - the development stage is where design specifications are transformed into an actual product.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Testing - The stage where the product is tested to ensure that it meets design requirements and specifications and will be accepted by the target audience.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Feedback loop - A relationship between variables in a system where the consequences of event feedback into the system as input, modifying the event in the future. Every action creates an equal and opposite reaction. When reactions loop back to affect themselves, a feedback loop is created.</p>
<p>Positive feedback amplifies output, resulting in growth. Negative feedback dampens output, stabilizing the system.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Immersion - A state of mental focus so intense that awareness of the real world is lost, generally resulting in a feeling of joy and satisfaction.</p>
<p>When perceptual and cognitive systems are under-taxed, people become apathetic and bored. If they are over-taxed, people become stressed and frustrated. Immersion occurs when perceptual and cognitive systems are challenged at near capacity without being exceeded.</p>
</li>
<li class="">
<p>Confirmation - A technique for preventing unintended actions by requiring verification of the actions before they are performed. Confirmations are used to prevent a class of errors called slips. Confirmations slow task performance and should be reserved for use with critical and irreversible operations.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/6#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>A wonderful book to get an introduction to the world of design. The knowledge of universal design is going to impact all walks of your life, for instance, you won't look at <code>Apple Store</code> as a mere structure. The Apple store is a classic example of Orientation Sensitivity and threat detection.</p>
<p>This book is a non-technical read and a must-read to walk and live with design sanity.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fundamental Analysis of shares, Become an intelligent investor By Ankit Gala & Khusboo Gala]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/5</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/5</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on Fundamental Analysis of shares, Become an intelligent investor By Ankit Gala & Khusboo Gala]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/fin-analysis-b441e0436e22bb38cea93d2793110d42.webp" width="323" height="499" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Hey there, great men say that you should make money while you sleep. If you agree with that saying then you should check the stock market or start your own business which can run without your presence. Historically many men &amp; women have made a good sum of money in the long term by investing in the right stock. Hey, the key to remember is <strong>Right stock</strong>. How do you know if you have chosen the right stock? The answer lies in the fundamental analysis of the stock.</p>
<p>When I was at the book, my eyes fell on the books titled <strong>Fundamental analysis of shares</strong> by Ankit Gala &amp; Khusboo Gala. I was interested in the book because I too wanted to stay invested in stocks.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-authors">About the authors<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/5#about-the-authors" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the authors" title="Direct link to About the authors" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>When you are choosing a subject that is about money, it's better to listen to the experts. Both authors have strong financial backgrounds and they have an understanding of the mindset of the retail investor.</p>
<p>In the preface, they mention that 90% of retail investors lose money in the stock market. This is because retail investors generally do little to no research about the stock. They listen to friends, and stock picks or tell a comfortable lie to themselves. The authors have given their best shot at breaking this practice by writing concisely about fundamental analysis.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="top-3-ideas-from-the-book">Top 3 ideas from the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/5#top-3-ideas-from-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Top 3 ideas from the book" title="Direct link to Top 3 ideas from the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>This book is not about ideas, it's about technical terms and definitions. Quoting a few of them.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="fundamental-analysis">Fundamental analysis<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/5#fundamental-analysis" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Fundamental analysis" title="Direct link to Fundamental analysis" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>If you are a day trader, then fundamental analysis is not required. If you are a long-term investor, then fundamental analysis is really important.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Fundamental analysis is the method of finding the intrinsic value of the stock to find long-term investment opportunities.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>EIC analysis</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Economic</li>
<li class="">Industry</li>
<li class="">Company</li>
</ul>
<p>4 phases of the economy</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Expansion Phase</li>
<li class="">Recession phase</li>
<li class="">Depression phase</li>
<li class="">Recovery phase</li>
</ul>
<p>2 phases of market</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Bull market</li>
<li class="">Bear market</li>
</ul>
<p>There is a difference of around 4 to 6 months between the economic phases and market phases to follow.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Ideally investments should be done at the start of the expansion phase and should be divested at the start of the recession phase.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Industry analysis</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Startup stage</li>
<li class="">Growth stage</li>
<li class="">Consolidation stage</li>
<li class="">Maturity stage</li>
<li class="">Decline stage</li>
</ul>
<p>Classification of Industry</p>
<ol>
<li class="">Growth industries</li>
<li class="">Cyclical industries</li>
<li class="">Defensive industries</li>
<li class="">Cyclical growth industries</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="financial-statements">Financial statements<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/5#financial-statements" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Financial statements" title="Direct link to Financial statements" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Balance sheet of the company - to get a snapshot of what the company owns vs what it owes. Key terms assets &amp; liabilities.</li>
<li class="">Profit &amp; loss account of the company - to analyze the fundamentals of the company. Also known as income statement. Key terms expenses, tax, profits, etc.</li>
<li class="">Cash flow statement - helps to understand how company operations are running.</li>
<li class="">Statement of changes in equity</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="financial-ratios">Financial ratios<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/5#financial-ratios" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Financial ratios" title="Direct link to Financial ratios" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Profitability ratios</li>
<li class="">Liquidity ratios</li>
<li class="">Management efficiency ratios</li>
<li class="">Leverage ratios</li>
<li class="">Valuation ratios</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="useful-websites">Useful websites<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/5#useful-websites" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Useful websites" title="Direct link to Useful websites" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li class="">Screener. in</li>
<li class="">Tickertape</li>
<li class="">Equitymaster</li>
<li class="">Value stocks</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/5#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Overall a great attempt to write about fundamental analysis of stocks from an Indian market context. Though the book looks small, it's a heavy read and someone new to finance has to read, re-read and discuss with peers to gain a deeper understanding.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Blindly following stock picks by big investors is not a wise thing to do - Rakesh Jhunjhunwala</p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hackers Diet how to lose weight and hair through stress and poor nutrition By John Walker]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on Hackers Diet, how to lose weight and hair through stress and poor nutrition By John Walker.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="hackers diet cover" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/hackers-diet-31863e071353e72d1677510fbefc47a0.webp" width="821" height="1158" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Hi, we are here discussing another health-related book. You may ask, why another health-related book? thanks to book discovery that happened through the previous read. The previous book had mentioned another health book for programmers so I picked this book titled <strong>Hackers Diet by John Walker</strong>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-author">About the author<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#about-the-author" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the author" title="Direct link to About the author" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The general trend of a health author profile looks like a nutritionist, sports hero, chef, or someone with a great body. Here we have an author who was fat most of his life. The author is the founder of AutoDesk, the AutoCAD software company and he is wondering about his success at work but failure at shedding his weight.</p>
<p>The author thought that fat was a problem to be solved and not a burden to withstand. Once he solved his weight problem, he is sharing the tools with us so that we live long and prosper.</p>
<p>The author has great expectations for the readers or his audience who want to lose weight. The audience should have</p>
<ul>
<li class="">An eye firmly fixed on the goal</li>
<li class="">Will power</li>
<li class="">A high tolerance for pain</li>
</ul>
<p>The author throws light on the word hacker. <code>Hacker is a person who derives joy from discovering ways to circumvent limitations.</code></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="timeline-of-the-book">Timeline of the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#timeline-of-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Timeline of the book" title="Direct link to Timeline of the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>The book was written in 1991.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="nature-of-weight-loss-strategy">Nature of weight loss strategy<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#nature-of-weight-loss-strategy" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Nature of weight loss strategy" title="Direct link to Nature of weight loss strategy" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>No prizes for guessing the theme of the book, i.e. How can I lose weight?</p>
<p>The author says "Eat less food than your body burns".</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="good-ideas-from-the-book">Good ideas from the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#good-ideas-from-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Good ideas from the book" title="Direct link to Good ideas from the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="eat-watch">Eat watch<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#eat-watch" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Eat watch" title="Direct link to Eat watch" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>It's a hypothetical concept that tells when you should start eating and when to stop. This concept is based on the fact that <strong>if people did not eat except when their bodies needed food, nobody would be overweight</strong>. Let hunger tell us the time when we should eat instead of the convention like meeting friends or family dinner etc.</p>
<p>For the eat watch to work, the food you eat needs to give feedback to the body to stop eating. Slim people have this built-in eat watch which tells <code>enough already</code> but in others, that circuit is broken.</p>
<p>To control weight, you need to eat the right amount of food for the rest of your life. This requires motivation and manipulation. Motivation comes from willpower. Manipulation is the technique you use to deceive yourself, let's say it's half past 9 pm, let's exercise tomorrow. To control manipulation, we need empowerment.</p>
<p>If weight is managed rightly, you are about to partake of a new and rich part of the human experience, the exultation of living in a healthy animal body.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="know-the-basics">Know the basics<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#know-the-basics" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Know the basics" title="Direct link to Know the basics" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>There are 3 parts to make a note of while losing weight</p>
<ul>
<li class="">What we put into the body in calories, we can control this</li>
<li class="">What amount of input calories get burnt in calories</li>
<li class="">What goes out of the body, we can ignore the measurement of this.</li>
</ul>
<p>It takes approximately 7000 calories to add a kilogram of weight to your body. It's a glorious idea to control your weight without changing the way you eat, but like so many attractive ideas, it doesn't work. Don't delude yourself into thinking that exercise can do the whole job. For many of us, exercising just causes us to eat that little bit more that cancels out its benefits. The calories burned by exercising, even counting the secondary effects on metabolism, can be erased by even the slightest increases in food intake.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Permanent weight control requires permanent attention to what you eat. Life-long, permanent attention.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="benefits-of-exercise-and-meal-planning">Benefits of exercise and meal planning<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#benefits-of-exercise-and-meal-planning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Benefits of exercise and meal planning" title="Direct link to Benefits of exercise and meal planning" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Exercising not only gives you more time to live, but it also makes the time you live more enjoyable. You'll feel better, think straighter, sleep more soundly and have more capacity and endurance for everything you wish to do. Regular exercise greatly reduces the effects of altitude. As you exercise, you increase the capacity of your heart to pump blood and your lungs to replenish the oxygen it carries.</p>
<p>Meal planning for predictable calorie intake is the central management tool that closes the circle and achieves control over weight. Meal planning requires total control over not just what you eat, but also how much. Also, eat at the same time every day. Avoid eating before sleep.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The faster you eat, the more you get.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here are steps to implement a weight control loop/feedback system</p>
<ol>
<li class="">Estimate calories</li>
<li class="">Plan meals</li>
<li class="">Log weight</li>
<li class="">Find a trend and adjust the estimation of calories</li>
<li class="">Repeat step 1</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="stress">Stress<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#stress" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Stress" title="Direct link to Stress" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Stress is an unavoidable consequence of living in our fast-paced high-tech culture. Stress is a primary cause of overeating and weight gain.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="something-i-wont-agree-with">Something I won't agree with<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#something-i-wont-agree-with" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Something I won't agree with" title="Direct link to Something I won't agree with" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Of course, modern science is vocal about metabolic disorders which could make a person fat. The author is fixated on the idea that our body is a pure function and the system can be mathematically modeled all the time.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/4#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Though the book has been written 3 decades ago. The fundamental ideas are the same.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Eat in moderation</li>
<li class="">Deliberately starve yourself to the good life</li>
<li class="">Avoid packaged food despite their tall claims</li>
<li class="">Exercise to beat cholesterol &amp; fat</li>
<li class="">Use excel sheets for some good cause like tracking calories, weight, etc</li>
</ul>
<p>If you want to pick a health-related book written by an engineer who built a great company, writes about planning with excel, talks about moving averages, lots of formulas, etc then this book is for you.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Healthy Programmer Get Fit, Feel Better and Keep Coding By Joe Kutner]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on nonfiction book related to health genre titled The Healthy Programmer Get Fit, Feel Better and Keep Coding By Joe Kutner.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="The Healthy Programmer Book Cover" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/the-healthy-programmer-cover-2cdb37a9ba51ff9f8e60406c1471374a.webp" width="500" height="600" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Hey there, let's discuss a book that explains health in a way that would captivate techies (techies here refer to people who sit before the keyboard) around the world. This book aims at refactoring your health. The book is titled "The Healthy Programmer". As a programmer myself, I did not think twice before picking up this book and read this book immediately. Let me explain how this book felt in parts.</p>
<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> Health-related books are intended only as an informative guide for those who wish to know health-related aspects however these books should not be treated as a replacement for licensed healthcare providers. Don't be the DIY guy trying to immunize or treat himself all the time.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Amish communities are known for their embrace of a rural lifestyle, manual labor, and a reluctance to adopt modern technology. It’s a far cry from the world of programmers, where we have to remind ourselves to get outside and walk around now and then.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-author">About the author<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3#about-the-author" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the author" title="Direct link to About the author" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="the-best-parts-of-the-book">The best parts of the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3#the-best-parts-of-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The best parts of the book" title="Direct link to The best parts of the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>I love to read this book because hacker slang creeps into the pages aptly. The book starts with <code>Let's Refactor your Health</code>. That's what most of us want anyways. Here are some of the good parts.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="lets-the-unit-test-our-health">Lets the unit test our health<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3#lets-the-unit-test-our-health" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Lets the unit test our health" title="Direct link to Lets the unit test our health" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Before performing refactoring on our body, let's perform a few unit tests like</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Do you lose your breath after climbing a single flight of stairs</li>
<li class="">Do you regularly sit for more than one hour without getting up?</li>
<li class="">In the last year have you experienced back, neck, shoulder, or wrist pain</li>
<li class="">In the last week have your eyes become dry, red, or difficult to focus</li>
<li class="">Have you eaten until you were comfortably full more than once in the last month</li>
<li class="">Have you been exposed to direct sunlight for less than 10 minutes today</li>
<li class="">Is it uncomfortable to bend over and tie your shoes</li>
<li class="">Has your pant size increased significantly in the last 5 years</li>
</ul>
<p>It's a brainer to figure out the associated risks related to each unit test. Once we identify the risk, we can plan to mitigate the risk.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="quick-checklist-to-visit-daily">Quick checklist to visit daily<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3#quick-checklist-to-visit-daily" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Quick checklist to visit daily" title="Direct link to Quick checklist to visit daily" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class=""><strong>Plan</strong> for health standup</li>
<li class=""><strong>Walk</strong> for 10000 steps with 20 mins brisk</li>
<li class=""><strong>Move</strong> 5 mins/hour. Change position every 20 mins</li>
<li class=""><strong>Eat</strong> 5 servings of fruits and vegetables</li>
<li class=""><strong>Build</strong> 5 Body building exercises</li>
</ul>
<p>Conduct a daily health standup</p>
<ul>
<li class="">What did I do yesterday to improve my health</li>
<li class="">What will I do today to improve my health</li>
<li class="">Is there anything blocking you from staying health</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="relation-between-exercise--learning">Relation between exercise &amp; learning<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3#relation-between-exercise--learning" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Relation between exercise &amp; learning" title="Direct link to Relation between exercise &amp; learning" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Programmers are lifelong learners &amp; and an avatar of students. Learning and keeping ourselves up to date is indispensable. one of the best ways to enhance your ability to learn is to get some exercise. There’s also a lot of laboratory evidence showing that our brains work better when our bodies are active. In particular, they become better at remembering new concepts, ideas, and patterns.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Studies show that doing exercise before or after learning something new can help you remember it.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="say-hi-to-walking-briskly">Say hi to walking briskly<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3#say-hi-to-walking-briskly" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Say hi to walking briskly" title="Direct link to Say hi to walking briskly" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Walking is our first guard in defense against lifestyle disease. Use the pedometer on your phone or wristband and clock 10000 steps every day. To get better results, walk often. Hitting the gym and sitting for 15 hours is not effective.</p>
<p>Walking 10000 steps in a day does not capture the intensity, instead, target the daily total of 10k steps to come from spurts of 3,000 steps in thirty minutes or 1,000 steps in ten minutes to ensure that some of your walkings are done briskly.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="other-tips">Other tips<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3#other-tips" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Other tips" title="Direct link to Other tips" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li class="">Get a minimum of 20 minutes of exercise every day</li>
<li class="">Watch your resting heart BPM. Measure and ensure BPM does not go up as you age. Losing weight, and reducing stress could be useful strategies</li>
<li class="">Mitigate the risks of sitting by<!-- -->
<ul>
<li class="">Sit for 20 minutes</li>
<li class="">Stand for 20 minutes</li>
<li class="">Walk if you can instead of stand</li>
<li class="">Change between sitting and standing often</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="">Every 20 minutes, focus on something 20 meters</li>
<li class="">Here is how you can boost immunity<!-- -->
<ul>
<li class="">Get enough sleep</li>
<li class="">Drink enough water</li>
<li class="">Avoid antibiotics</li>
<li class="">Eat fermented food</li>
<li class="">Get your vitamin D</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="something-that-i-do-not-agree-with">Something that I do not agree with<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3#something-that-i-do-not-agree-with" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Something that I do not agree with" title="Direct link to Something that I do not agree with" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>I do not agree with <code>Agile dieting</code> as mentioned in the book. Well, maybe the times have changed. Professionals can come up with specific diet programs which give better results</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/3#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>You cannot fool nature. You have to read this book because your quality of job &amp; life depends on your health. Give yourself the joy of being healthy.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Movement is the key to being healthy. Sitting for long hours is a death sentence for programmers.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Do It Today Overcome Procrastination, Improve Productivity, and Achieve More Meaningful Things By Darius Foroux]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/2</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/2</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on nonfiction book related to self help titled Do It Today Overcome Procrastination, Improve Productivity, and Achieve More Meaningful Things By Darius Foroux.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/book2-a2939a2547ce15562686730fcdd4b327.webp" width="1280" height="720" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Hey there, let's discuss an interesting short, light, and no-nonsense read from the <code>self-help</code> genre. Most self-help books try to address one or more than one broad problem in life. This book is no different in that aspect. As the title suggests, this book attempts to solve problems related to</p>
<ol>
<li class="">Procrastination</li>
<li class="">Focus</li>
<li class="">Meaning in life</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="about-the-author">About the author<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/2#about-the-author" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About the author" title="Direct link to About the author" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>A book cannot be separated from the author because it's the author who gave its form and contents. So the author's personality gets into the book. After reading the book, here is what I understand about the author.</p>
<p>The author is a seeker, and doer and wishes to be deterministic about what he does in life. He seems to avoid the <code>digital</code> life. He is cautious about the time drainers however he says he is not a robot and consumes entertainment.</p>
<p>Overall I like the author because his advice/tips are relevant to modern times.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="groundbreaking-ideas-from-the-book">Groundbreaking ideas from the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/2#groundbreaking-ideas-from-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Groundbreaking ideas from the book" title="Direct link to Groundbreaking ideas from the book" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>It's a short self-help book that looks like a book summary. From that content, here are my favorite ideas.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="turn-off-wifi-by-default">Turn off wifi by default<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/2#turn-off-wifi-by-default" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Turn off wifi by default" title="Direct link to Turn off wifi by default" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>I like this idea because I know successful people and peers at work who have benefitted from this policy. They would turn off data/notifications on the phone. The phone is used only for calls/SMS. I know of people who would reply to Whatsapp messages once a week, they are quite ahead of normal people.</p>
<p>At home, turning off the wifi can be helpful to focus on other aspects of life.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="focus-on-things-other-than-the-job">Focus on things other than the job<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/2#focus-on-things-other-than-the-job" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Focus on things other than the job" title="Direct link to Focus on things other than the job" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>As an adult, we are our job. We are identified by our job and trusted by banks based on our job so we get attached or dedicated to our job and ignore the rest. Here are other important things in life.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Reading</li>
<li class="">Exercising</li>
<li class="">Investing</li>
<li class="">Saving</li>
<li class="">Spending time with people etc</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="to-cut-procrastination-boost-productivity">To cut procrastination, boost productivity<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/2#to-cut-procrastination-boost-productivity" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to To cut procrastination, boost productivity" title="Direct link to To cut procrastination, boost productivity" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>Despite a million motivational videos, if we do not love what we do, we are most likely to procrastinate or give up on it. So find something you love to do.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Do the important things today not tomorrow</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Recipe for the good life. Focus on what you want and eliminate the rest.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/2#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<p>Paying bills is important but there is something more to life than bills themselves.</p>
<p>Overall an interesting short, crisp read which focuses on tactics over techniques for boosting productivity and beating procrastination.</p>
<p>In most places, the author has picked and phrased the best practices and ideas from other books which helps us to remember those ideas as well.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">For instance, the Pomodoro timer for crushing the work in front of you, we have heard of the same idea from multiple sources.</li>
<li class="">Plan the next day before we hit the bed, we have heard this many times but the authors improve the idea by asking you to visualize how you would feel when you get the tasks done tomorrow.</li>
</ul>
<p>This book is recommended for people who want to guard their time, build focus and improve their productivity.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="useful-links">Useful links<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/2#useful-links" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Useful links" title="Direct link to Useful links" translate="no">​</a></h2>
<a href="https://myreadforchange.com/do-it-today-book-summary-i-darius-foroux">Link 1</a>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TieI0FanmdM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"></iframe>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My Maid Invests in the Stock Market And Why You Should Too! By Bo Sanchez]]></title>
            <link>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/1</link>
            <guid>https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/1</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 15:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[booktalk on nonfiction book related to stock market titled My Maid Invests in the Stock Market And Why You Should Too! By Bo Sanchez.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="My Maid Invests in the Stock Market And Why You Should Too! By Bo Sanchez" src="https://dhbalaji.dev/assets/images/book1-03ec579a4dd1fa87cf793cd46707afb8.webp" width="553" height="769" class="img_jvCJ"></p>
<p>Let me start with my favorite line from the book.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you do not own a business, you should invest in business.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Financial books are the least favorite of readers because of 2 reasons.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Most financial books give orthodox advice which suits the stoics or individuals. Most normal people are not stoics, they have retired parents to take care of or they need to fund their sibling's education.</li>
<li class="">Most stock market books are not written for lower-wage earning audiences. They have a point, how can someone poor invest in a portfolio of stocks? But this author gives hope to people with day jobs.</li>
</ul>
<p>But this book is different, I am glad that I picked this read. This book is written by the author keeping their maids in mind who represent the young working-class audience.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="characters-in-the-book">Characters in the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/1#characters-in-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Characters in the book" title="Direct link to Characters in the book" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>There are 3 main characters in the book</p>
<ul>
<li class="">The financially savvy author who lives in Philipines</li>
<li class="">The maids who work at the author's home</li>
<li class="">The company owned by the author and its clients</li>
</ul>
<p>I liked the way the maid's persona was explained. The maids are young, working at the author's home to make money. They are good at saving money. They send some money back home so that their family eats and lives happily. The maids are also burdened with the task of meeting financial emergencies which could arise in the family like bad health etc.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="best-ideas-from-the-book">Best ideas from the book<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/1#best-ideas-from-the-book" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Best ideas from the book" title="Direct link to Best ideas from the book" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>It's a short book and a light read which can be read in an hour. It has 84 pages which are filled with great ideas. Here is my favorite part of the book.</p>
<p>Most books I read treat finances differently. The investment banker would not consider middle-class family problems like sending remittances back home to feed the family while writing a book on the stock market.</p>
<p>The author calls out a phrase called "Feeding the civilization", which means that the breadwinner has 2 families to take care of.</p>
<ul>
<li class="">The family consists of the breadwinner, spouse, children &amp;</li>
<li class="">The family consists of breadwinner parents, breadwinner siblings, etc</li>
</ul>
<p>Already the maids are working on a smaller wage but they have 2 families to take care of. So the maids are going to retire in a financially handicapped situation at old age because retirement is real. The employer whom maids have worked with and the family whom the maids raised are going to desert them when the maids are old and have no money to take care of themselves.</p>
<p>The author mentions a formula to separate your money once you get your monthly wage</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Tithe fund - 10% for Charity so that it creates an abundance mindset. The author is an advocate of God and religion.</li>
<li class="">Expense fund - 15% for Daily expenses and recreation.</li>
<li class="">Support fund - 30% for your family living in the village or elsewhere as a remittance so that they eat and live</li>
<li class="">Retirement fund - 30% for Retirement fund which sits in the share market and is built by monthly investing into the giant company stocks even during a market crisis</li>
<li class="">Emergency fund - 15% for the emergency fund which sits in the bank so that you do not break the retirement fund if a crisis hits</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>By investing 30% of the salary into the retirement fund for 20-plus years, the maids can retire as a millionaire.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The authors advise the maids to avoid</p>
<ul>
<li class="">Trading</li>
<li class="">Investing in risky stocks or penny stocks</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="something-that-i-do-not-agree-with">Something that I do not agree with<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/1#something-that-i-do-not-agree-with" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Something that I do not agree with" title="Direct link to Something that I do not agree with" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>10% of the salary to God or Charity for the maids is something I do not fully agree with. It's a good idea but I doubt if it's actionable.</p>
<p>10% of the book goes into explaining the trading company where the author works. It makes sense only for that geographic area but it does not apply to everyone who reads the book. A hyperlink to a blog article would have helped.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorTargetHideOnScrollNavbar_XFbs" id="verdict">Verdict<a href="https://dhbalaji.dev/my-reads/1#verdict" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Verdict" title="Direct link to Verdict" translate="no">​</a></h3>
<p>If you are looking for a short book, under 100 pages that resonate with working-class people. This book is for you. The author promises that his investing strategy of buying a certain sum of top company stocks for 20 years systematically is going to make you a millionaire.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Is there anyone who does not want to become a millionaire when they retire? I guess not so this book is for you.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>